<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04506">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John W. Wroth to Walt Whitman, 2 June 1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04506</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>John W. Wroth</author>
                    <title>John W. Wroth to Walt Whitman, 2 June 1887</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1887-06-02" xml:id="dat1">June 2, 1887</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 19, Reel 11&#8211;12</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt
                    Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Wroth, John W." ref="loc.04506_n2">John W. Wroth</persName>
                </person> 
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-02-18" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-02-18" who="#cb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-12-20" who="#ss">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-11-09" who="#aa">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.01559_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Albuquerque NM<ptr target="loc.04506_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1887-06-02">6/2/87</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Mr Walt Whitman</salute>
                <salute>Camden N.J.</salute>
                <salute>My Dear Mr Whitman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It seems to be but yesterday that I saw you riding on the cars talking to the driver
                on Stevens Street, &#38; it has really been nearly three years three years, this
                coming August since I left Camden. Time has flown so rapidly that it seems but a
                year &#38; yet, again, it seems ten years, since I felt the old home <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.01560_large.jpg" type="verso"/></p>
            <p>Your photograph greets me every time I go into my brother's office I have it hung
                there so we can both see it, &#38; you do not know how many people know you way out,
                in this western country.</p>
            <p>One of my friends came in the other day &#38; said, "you have still got his picture
                hung up," &#38; I said "yes! it would hang there until I go away &#38; then it will
                go <hi rend="underline">with me</hi>". it reminds me of so many pleasant chats with
                the original.</p>
            <p>New Mexico, has changed me so My Dear Mr Whitman that you would not<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.01561_large.jpg" type="recto"/> recognize me. I
                am only one inch short of six feet &#38; am heavily built in proportion, weighing
                150 lbs.</p>
            <p>The first year I came out I was a cowboy, &#38; altho' it is a very prosaic life,
                still I have some very pleasant reminiscences of that time. I have been out on the
                prairie with no house or food in sight when night came &#38; had nothing to do but
                to roll up in my blankets &#38; make the best of it, then again, horse breaking is
                one of the hardest times of the cowboys life. Many a tumble I have had off<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.01562_large.jpg" type="verso"/> of a broncho but
                you have to get up &#38; conquer the horse before you stop in spite of all the hard
                knocks you get.</p>
            <p>For a man with <hi rend="underline">money</hi> there <hi rend="underline">is</hi>
                wealth in the cattle business, but for a cowboy&#8212;only, a small ranche with a
                smaller number of cattle, to look forward to&#8212;after years of hard &#38;
                unceasing labor still a cowboy is always happy, contented &#38; what is the best of
                all&#8212;the finest &#38; constant friend, when you call upon him, that a man can
                have.</p>
            <p>I have been to Calafornia<pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.01563_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> I went about the first of April &#38; was gone two weeks. the
                scenery I think was the grandest that I ever saw. It was just magnificent. I thought
                how Mr Whitman would like to see it. At times we would be going through some deep,
                dark ca&#241;on &#38; then we would burst forth into the full glory of sun as we
                hastened over a level stretch of praire, then we would slowly slowly be going up a
                steep <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ss" cert="low"
                    >part</unclear> of the Rockies, only to come dashing down the<pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc_vm.01564_large.jpg" type="verso"/> other side with all the brakes set,
                hard &#38; objects flying by you like magic. I remember one morning we reached the
                top of the San Fransica Mts. just as the sun was rising &#38; it was grand to feel
                the sun &#38; look down the valley when all was as yet in complete darkness with the
                sun slowly ascending &#38; giving its light to the earth below. One place I remember
                well &#38; that was Ca&#241;on Diablo a great rent in the Earth 300 ft deep and 100
                ft wide<pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_vm.01565_large.jpg" type="recto"/> looking
                down that fearful hole your imagination will conjure up ideas that you would not
                think of elsewhere &#38; you can realize the freaks of nature to their fullest extent But I have
                not described the town of Albuquerque &#38; I will not attempt to do so, as I can
                never describe anything correctly, but will send you a magazine that I have sent for
                which describes it fully The inhabitants are in expectations of a boom which they
                say will take place in about three months, but<pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="loc_vm.01566_large.jpg" type="verso"/> as I am not a sanguine person I do
                not say so. I must close now as it is bedtime Mother &#38; Harry say "Remember us to
                Mr Whitman &#38; tell him that we often remember him &#38; wish we could see
                him"</p>
            <p>If you ever feel like it Mr Whitman a small letter from you would be very much
                appreciated &#38; promptly answered</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Sincerely Your Friend</signed>
                <signed>J.W. Wroth</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>address <address>
                        <addrLine>J.W. Wroth</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Albuquerque</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>New Mexico</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_vm.01567_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ww">from Johnny Wroth | New Mexico |
                (ans'd)</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_vm.01568_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
