<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00323">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 21 July 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
            <editor>Jerome M. Loving</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName>
               <persName xml:id="gp">Gillian Price</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>duk.00323</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>George Washington Whitman</author>
               <title>George Washington Whitman  to Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, 21 July 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-07-21">July 21, 1862</date>
               <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, George Washington">George Washington Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor">Louisa Van Velsor Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#ak" when="2015-01-26">corrected orgName, added pbs, added choice tags</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2009-12-18">Ken's proofreading changes</change>
         <change who="#ec" when="2009-08-24">style sheet proofreading</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#gp" when="2006-12-18">copy-edited transcription against source text and made necessary
corrections</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-12-15">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00323.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">Camp Lincoln, Newport <lb/>News Va</name>
                  <date when="1862-07-21">  July 21st /62</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Mother.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter dated July 16th came all right but the one you speak of <choice><sic>haveing</sic><corr>having</corr></choice> sent previous, I have never received.</p>
         <p>We are still laying on our oars here, keeping as cool as possible. The weather most of the time is pretty comfortable but once in a while we have a real old scorcher for a day or two. We get the New York papers here the next day after they are printed so that we keep pretty well posted in regard to the News in York. I thought by your letter that you appeared to be rather discouraged with the way the war is <choice><sic>progresing</sic><corr>progressing</corr></choice>. I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> see any thing very discouraging. Mc had to give way its true but it appears quite certain that the <choice><sic>enemys</sic><corr>enemies</corr></choice> loss <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00323.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>was considerable more than ours and he<ptr target="duk.00323_n1"/> must be in a position to take good care of himself or we would not be left here doing nothing, and I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> believe any man could have taken the force he had and done any better than he did,  so you see I have strong faith in McCleland if he did have to fall back.<ptr target="duk.00323_n2"/>
            </p>
         <p>Troops <choice><sic>arive</sic><corr>arrive</corr></choice> here everyday  the force that got licked down at James Island<ptr target="duk.00323_n3"/> are here  among which are the <choice><sic>celabrated</sic><corr>celebrated</corr></choice> 79th the Scotchmen you know, and the 8th <choice><sic>Michagan</sic><corr>Michigan</corr></choice> who have the name of being a first rate fighting Regiment  and when Mc gets ready for another move and has the Burnside crowd to back him he will walk into Richmond just as easy as <choice><sic>roling</sic></choice> off a log. Well Mamy we have not been paid yet but we are looking for the paymaster every day,  we expect to get our money the last <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00323.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>of this week and I shall send you about $125 just as soon as I get it  we have to pay pretty dear for everything we get to eat here.</p>
         <p>I am perfectly well now although I was a little under the weather the first week I came here  my eyes and face were as yellow as Jeffs whiskers used to be,  the doctor thought I had the Jaundice but it did not amount to much and  I am all right now  I think after we get paid I shall try and go down to see Bunkum at Suffolk<ptr target="duk.00323_n4"/> but I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> know certain as I can get away. If Jeff <choice><sic>aint</sic><corr>ain't</corr></choice> too <choice><sic>buisy</sic><corr>busy</corr></choice> he might take a run down here  it would not cost much for him or Walt to get on board one of the transports that come to Fortress Monroe from New York and there is a boat that runs from the Fort here. I did not a word from home from the 14th of June until the other day <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00323.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>when I got your letter of the 16 of July  I felt quite downhearted every time a mail <choice><sic>arived</sic><corr>arrived</corr></choice> and brought me no letter  I wish some of you would write oftener just to let me know how you are all <choice><sic>geting</sic><corr>getting</corr></choice> along.</p>
            <p>Well Mother it is time to turn in so I must bid you good night. My Pious regards to all the family and good night to all.</p>
            <closer rend="center">
               <signed>G.W. Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
