<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00401">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 19 February
                    1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00401</idno>
                <distributor>Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Charles L. Heyde</author>
                    <title>Charles L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 19 February 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-02-19" xml:id="dat1">February 19, 1885</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">The Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University Rare
                        Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heyde, Charles L." ref="n0299">Charles L. Heyde</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-06" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-05-21" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-02-21" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-19" who="#ss">encoded and checked</change>
            <change when="2014-12-05" who="#aa">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00401.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Burlington Vermont.</name>
                    <date when="1885-02-19">Feby 19, 1885.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Bro Walt.</salute> 
            </opener>
            <p>It is night, clear and cold: Han<ptr target="duk.00381_n2"/> has
                just left my room; gone to the east apartment: She prefers much to be alone. Cannot
                see visitors:<ptr target="duk.00399_n2"/> does not talk much; wearies her; so does
                reading: must not read aloud to her; or narrate any thing from newspapers:
                occasionally breaks out into some small gossip, furtively: Is weak: too much so to
                dress up. Languishes on the sofa, or by the fire, seated on a pillow, in a tall rocking chair: sometimes
                with a blanket around her, in <unclear reason= "illegible" cert= "medium" resp="#if">indian</unclear>
                <unclear reason="cut off" cert="medium" resp="#ss">fashion</unclear>: window partly
                raised, <choice><sic>freshning</sic><corr>freshening</corr></choice> the room: has been about since 9 O'clock; attended some to
                dinner. <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00401.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> prepared
                her own supper oysters stewed: baked apples: indian pudding, milk: prunes: takes no
                tea or coffee: She is come in again: sitting down by the stove: I am writing to
                Walt: says to give her love to him; wants to see him very much: had letter from Lou:
                yesterday; <unclear reason="cut off" cert="low" resp="#ss">reporting</unclear> you
                looking very well; <unclear reason="cut off" cert="low" resp="#ss">which</unclear>
                gave her great satisfaction. Lou<ptr target="n0368"/> sent her some time ago a box
                of underclothing, at my suggestion: She was badly off: I purchased a garment hose;
                could not wear it: could not endure a woman dress maker, to handle her; make such
                things for her was too nervous. She has now numerous blank<unclear reason= "cut off" cert="high" resp="#if">ets</unclear> and bed comforters: and
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00401.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> sleeps warm;
                bed warmed, between blankets. sleeps some; better: improves: does not feel her
                heartbeat in her brain so much; as she expresses it: does not use so much bromide:
                it is hurtfull to her: affects her seriously the next day: would craze her if she
                persisted: it is given to make her sleep; at too great a risk: <unclear
                    reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#aa">Doctor</unclear> was in last night:
                said she was not getting better very fast, but would <unclear reason="cut off" cert="medium" resp="#if">a</unclear>certaintly get well: She never
                can be as she was: look as well: be as strong. She has changed greatly: her neck and
                breast has shrunk: her face too: her eyes at times are sunken, glassy; her back is
                weak: her hair grows&#8212;<unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#ss"
                    >so</unclear> becomes thinner <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="duk.00401.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> very grey. Yet her voice is
                natural: her step firmer. When this hard cold winter is past, she may recuperate. She
                tried to sew a little to day: I was away 3 hours this morning, to <unclear
                    reason="cut off" cert="medium" resp="#if"><choice><sic>Winsor</sic><corr>Windsor</corr></choice></unclear> to get subscribers
                to my picture sale: cruel way to get a <choice><sic>livinng</sic><corr>living</corr></choice>: 60 dollars in frames: months of work
                on pictures: shall distribute them next month: I meet with much sympathy among
                people but times are hard: The landscape is truly <unclear reason="cut off"
                    cert="high" resp="#aa">enshrouded</unclear> a white country, snow <unclear reason="cut off" cert="medium" resp="#if">enveloped</unclear>, hill,
                valley, lake and river: Lou is to purchase two paintings: will help me much. Geo<ptr
                    target="n0700b"/> sent a check: he reserved for Han: It has cost me over 200
                dollars, this winter new stove, extra fires: frames, groceries, etc&#8212;have not
                recieved a line from the girls.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>C. L. H.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
