<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="hun.00052">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">John Burroughs to Walt Whitman, 31 March
    1868</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>John Burroughs</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina
        Bernardini</persName>
<persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>hun.00052</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>John Burroughs</author>
    <title>John Burroughs to Walt Whitman, 31 March 1868</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1868-03-31" xml:id="dat1">March 31, 1868</date>
    <idno type="callno"/>
    <orgName xml:id="hun">The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical
        Gardens </orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Burroughs, John" ref="n0129">John Burroughs</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-01">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-08-21" who="#cb">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-08-21" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-07-24" who="#js">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2012-07-13" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="hun.00052.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <address><addrLine>Washington D. C.</addrLine></address>
                    <date when="1868-03-31">March 31 1868</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Sir:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>The little essay in The "Galaxy"<!-- <ptr target="n0254"/> --> is hardly deserving the
                attention you give it; yet its author is not insensible to the opinion of so
                accomplished a critic as yourself. Let me thank you for your expressions of interest
                and appreciation.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="hun.00052.002.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>I certainly had no design to disparage genius &amp; culture much less to attack them
                but only to call up and emphasise other points&#8212;as it were put in a plea for
                the ground work, when nearly everybody is <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#js">soliciting</unclear> only about the pattern. The older I grow the more
                disposed I am to subordinate the author to the man, and the less satisfaction I have
                in mere literacy or scholastic <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="hun.00052.003.jpg" type="recto"/> attainments. I see that literature is served, perhaps alone
                deeply and finally served, by other things than literary culture. <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#js">Tried</unclear> by purely artistic
                standards, we should be obliged to pronounce half a dozen current poets great. The
                reason they are not great is because they are deficient as men. They have the knack,
                they have all that culture can do, and yet there is not one <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="hun.00052.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <hi rend="underline">life giving</hi> word in them. It was this idea which I tried
                to make the point of the essay. I cannot but feel that at least the tone and spirit
                of current criticism is "antagonistic" to this suggestion. As an opinion or an
                abstract statement, no doubt most persons would asscent to it; but let it be carried
                out in literature, let a poet or artist appear, who shall not aim to express mere
                book culture, or any of the <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="hun.00052.005.jpg" type="recto"/> artificial phases of our civilization&#8212;its exclusions from
                the air, the sun, the Earth, but to open up the abysses of <choice>
                    <sic>primative</sic>
                    <corr>primitive</corr>
                </choice> power and feeling, and quicken and fertilize the spirit as nature does,
                and what would the critics say, even the best of them? I demand therefore that
                literature shall express more than literature, more than what is usually meant by
                genius or refinement, or intellect, be it the best in the world. Indeed when <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="hun.00052.006.jpg" type="verso"/> I think of a supreme
                work or poem, I have in my mind one in which all these things are lost, and the
                total impression of which is the spirit of manly action and performance. The
                greatest poem savors of nothing indoors, nothing conventional, no premeditated
                polish, no craft, or model, not even art, but of the spirit of universal nature. It
                is something like this that draws me to the Greek poets. If I could read them in the
                original no doubt I <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="hun.00052.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                should be much more sensible of it. What impresses me particularly in Aeschylus<!-- <ptr target="hun.00052_n1"/> --> is his stern moral grandeur. His polish if he has
                such never obtrudes itself upon my attention.</p>
            <p>It seems to me almost useless to attempt anything in the usual complacent Addisonian
                style at this time and in this country, at least write a view to promote <hi rend="underline">American</hi> literature thereby. I see no possible chance for
                a national literature here, until we <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="hun.00052.008.jpg" type="verso"/> have something deep cut and original, some tremendous
                overwhelming genius and man, whose plowshare shall completely obliterate all this
                pretty ornamental scratching of garden tools at the surface and open up the soil for
                new and hardy crops. He must be coarse and broad as well as subtle and absorptive,
                and above all things audacious. Violence must be done. These deft and dainty
                gentlemen who think such a <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="hun.00052.009.jpg" type="recto"/> punch luck as "Katharena" a great poem
                must be shocked, and larger and more robust standards must be introduced.</p>
            <p>I find it easy, as you see, to predict the man we need when I believe in the living
                example before me. My prophecy follows the fact. My admiration for Walt Whitman has
                been of too gradual a growth and the source of too much moral and spiritual help to
                me for me ever to suspect that I have either over estimated, <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="hun.00052.010.jpg" type="verso"/> or misestimated him. I find him, on long
                and intimate acquaintance, even more suggestive and significant, as a man than as an
                author. Indeed he is, in his personal make and presence, the curious counterpart of
                his Book, and I doubt if I could ever have come to a complete understanding of the
                one without the other. Among other things his glory is that in an age when almost
                every book and poem is of a pathological character&#8212;the result of <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="hun.00052.011.jpg" type="recto"/> some mental or
                spiritual disease, or of some one faculty pushed beyond its legitimate sphere of
                development, he has produced a vast work which is perfectly consistent with the
                health and <hi rend="underline">wholeness</hi> of the individual. <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi> is the rare "phenomenon" of a work of the
                imagination and the intellect which is an actual stay to human longevity and
                strength. It is not a thought but an act, as creation is, and this is my definition
                of a supreme work of art. All the great poems are like <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="hun.00052.012.jpg" type="verso"/> deeds, and imply the same totality of
                the human being. In this way they are moral without having any direct moral aim; and
                poetical and intellectual in the same manner. I have written a little book about the
                poet which I shall take the liberty to send you.</p>
            <p>I yield to more in my admiration for Hawthorne<!-- <ptr target="hun.00052_n2"/> -->
                as a writer, as a manipulator of words. Yet I cannot say that he has ever been of
                much help to me, as Emerson has and as Whitman still <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word"/><!-- "more"? -->
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="hun.00052.013.jpg" type="recto"/> has. Hawthorne is
                exceptional; he does not stand in the regular order of things; he is not great on
                the common grounds, and I cannot think that such as he betoken the general soundness
                and well-being of the race, as Whitman does. I think even Thoreau<!-- <ptr target="hun.00052_n3"/> --> is a more
                auspicious sign.</p>
            <p>You see I am determined to hold part to the manhood test. There are enough to exalt
                polish, and art, and scholarship, so far as my voice goes it shall be raised only
                for that which goes forward with <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="hun.00052.013.jpg" type="verso"/> human life and strength.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Very Truly Yours</salute>
                <signed>John Burroughs<!-- <ptr target="hun.00052_n4"/> --></signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>