<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="hun.00057">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">John Burroughs to Walt Whitman, June
    1868</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>John Burroughs</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="js">John
        Schwaninger</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>hun.00057</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>John Burroughs</author>
    <title>John Burroughs to Walt Whitman, June 1868</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1868-06" xml:id="dat1">June 1868</date>
    <idno type="callno"/>
    <orgName xml:id="hun">The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical
        Gardens </orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Burroughs, John" ref="n0129">John Burroughs</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-01">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-07-24" who="#js">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2012-07-13" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="hun.00057.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <address><addrLine>Washington D. C.</addrLine></address>
                    <date when="1868-06">June 1868</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Sir:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I am happy to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of April 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. I appreciate your candor
                and friendliness and would reciprocate. I believe we agree pretty nearly in theory
                at least. I can hardly see how two reasonable persons can differ materially on so
                important a subject as culture, when they come to understand each other, <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="hun.00057.002.jpg" type="verso"/> of course we must have
                culture. We can be nothing without it either as a nation, or as individuals. We do
                not want Crab apples either in literature, or politics or religion or manners, be
                the fullest fruit nature can bring forth.</p>
            <p>I should differ from you perhaps as to the relative importance of artificial culture
                (culture from books art, society exclusively) to the production of a national
                literature, and the broader <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="hun.00057.003.jpg" type="recto"/> culture of life and of real things. The question with me is not
                what will <choice>
                    <sic>conduse</sic>
                    <corr>conduce</corr>
                </choice> to the production of scholars or a clan of witty, elegant and accomplished
                    <hi rend="underline"><unclear reason="illegible">litteratures</unclear></hi> for
                these obscure the true ends of literature as the priests pervert religion; but what
                comparts with grand primary bards upon whom a nation can build, I think of Homers
                Teachers and of <choice>
                    <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                    <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                </choice> and of all monumental everlasting men, and I see how little what is now
                called culture <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="hun.00057.004.jpg" type="verso"/> had to
                do with what they were or what they achieved.</p>
            <p>Whether or not we have culture enough in America, it is plain that there is as yet no
                full fruition of culture here, no triumph of the man <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#js">frality</unclear> in our literature over the conventional,
                and what is worse, is not likely to be.</p>
            <p>The matter often shapes itself to me in some such formula as this: The first step in
                culture is marked by a love for, and an acquiescence in, the Artificial; the second
                step shows a revolt against the artificial as in <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="hun.00057.005.jpg" type="recto"/> Byron<!-- <ptr target="hun.00057_n1"/> -->; the third and last step which
                not one poet in a century takes, shows no revolt against society, or civilization or
                art, but an absorption of them and a rising above them. I do not see as any of our
                own popular poets have ever taken the second step, the step which disturbs and
                unsettles and <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#js">presages</unclear>
                new things. To me Longfellow, as sweet and gentle a spirit as he is, is no more
                tonic than confectionery is. Lowell's whip has got a good snapper on it and he knows
                how to make <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="hun.00057.006.jpg" type="verso"/> it crack
                like a pistol, but is that enough?</p>
            <p>I think Emerson<!-- <ptr target="hun.00057_n2"/> --> has taken the last step
                in man and in religion, but the only modern who has taken it in art according to my
                judgment, is Walt Whitman. From the standpoint of culture I regard <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi> as a supreme work. It shows a maturity of
                the man beyond any other modern poem&#8212;the man, done with toys, done with
                ornaments, done with criticism, and solemnly confronting the terrible beauty and
                majesty <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="hun.00057.007.jpg" type="recto"/> of things.</p>
            <p>You must allow me the frankness to say that I think you do not understand it. You
                look into it for what the fact had no design of putting there at least of nothing
                the main matter, namely genius, specimen's "five things" highly wrought intellectual
                proclaim work &amp;c. It must be understood at the outset that this poem does not
                enter into competition with other modern works with reference to these things. It
                differs from them just as the landscape differs from a flower garden. It is
                absolutely new both in the <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="hun.00057.008.jpg" type="verso"/> theory of art upon which it is based and in the such which the
                poet had in view. This theory of Art I have attempted to <hi rend="underline">suggest</hi> in my book. It is briefly this: That nature affords the only
                adequate standard for a first class modern artist, that to elaborate is of no avail,
                but to hint, to stimulate to self going, is everything. Nature is perpetual
                transition. Everything passes &amp; presses on; there is no pause, no completion, no
                exhaustive elaboration. To produce and multiply endlessly and <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="hun.00057.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <!-- I feel a marked disconnect between this and the previous page. Are we missing a page? -->men
                of the most liberal and ample culture. To partially cultivated people he is
                meaningless and repulsive.</p>
            <p>You are wrong in saying I think the West superior to the East as respects literature
                or general culture. It would be silly to affirm such a thing. I think the West is
                    <hi rend="underline">prospectively</hi> superior to the East. I think a type of
                character is forming there which will eclipse anything that has yet appeared in the
                Atlantic States, though that character may be yet a long way off from literature.
                    <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="hun.00057.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <!-- Again, the disconnect. Another possible missing page? -->commit herself to no
                end or scheme is the law of nature. Something like this is in <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi>. A hint, a sound, a germ, a stroke, a significant book,
                and on the author goes, follow who can.</p>
            <p>I am as little in love with endeavors, and awkward or bungling worksmanship as you
                are, or with <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#js">aerid</unclear>
                unripe fruit, and any such thing in Walt Whitman would be his instant condemnation
                to me. Again, <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#js">I</unclear> any such
                charge I set the fact, that his moral heart recognition both in this country and
                Europe has been from. <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="hun.00057.011.jpg" type="recto"/>
                Neither did I wish to be understood as refering to
                "Kathiren" 
                as a work of true culture. It perhaps represents the average culture of the churches
                and schools, and its author has doubtless been cultivated fully up to his capacity
                for culture.</p>
            <p>I appreciate the need of good nature and hearty cooperation among literary men as
                much as any one, but we must be aware what price we are paying for them, I think
                Lessings example as a critic is a good one for young men to emulate, and <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="hun.00057.012.jpg" type="verso"/> that soft words are
                not always the best. The class of poets and critics who aspire to foster and lead
                public taste in this country are intensely obnoxious to me, because I see they are
                the sworn enemies of any large generous growth. The great standards and the
                principles of universal nature need to be revised and enforced at all hazards.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>With much respect I am</salute>
                <salute>Yours Truly</salute>
                <signed>John Burroughs</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>P. S. Let me call your attention to Whitman's paper on <hi rend="underline">Personalism</hi> in the May "Salary" which I think contains the deepest
                    layer word ever spoken upon the subject of culture</p>
                <p>J. B.</p>
            </postscript>
            <!-- This postscript in particular makes me think that these letters were not addressed to Whitman. Do we have images of an envelope to prove/disprose this? -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>