<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01457">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 19 December 1875</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01457</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 19 December 1875</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1875-12-19" xml:id="dat1">December 19, 1875</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8, Reel 5</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00151</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas" ref="n0196">Thomas Dixon</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-14" who="#smb">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2023-01-24" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-02" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-15" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2014-10-23">corrected image names</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-11-06" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-18" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-16" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-10-26" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01457.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">15 Sunderland Street</name>
                    <name type="place">Sunderland<ptr target="loc.01457_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1875-12-19">Dec 19, 75</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have mailed you and registered there. the following Books and printed matter. a Copy of "the Bhagavad Gita"<ptr target="n0079"/> 
                Thompson's<ptr target="n5001"/> translations. (a recent Edition.) Selections from the 
                <choice><sic>Sanscrit</sic><corr>Sanskrit</corr></choice> by John Muir<ptr target="n0425"/> D.D. a lecture on 
                English Literature by a Unitarian Minister of Birkenhead (to whom I gave a copy 
                of the Complete Edition of your Poems) lastly the Supplement to our town's paper. I would like you to look over 
                a Sketch by H.C. Andersen<ptr target="n0039"/> on two Candles, <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice>
                translated by one of your readers here. the other is a Story from Iceland being the first story in said 
                paper, it is also written by a warm friend of yours, he was once Editor of the paper but is now engaged in a 
                larger paper in a neighbouring town. a paper that is quite in advance of all our papers here about entitled 
                the Newcastle Chronicle it has got a Daily as well as weekly issue. I will send you a copy someday of the weekly
                one so that you may gauge its power and its principles. and also 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01457.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                contrast it with your own papers for I think there is large room for improvement in&#8212;many of them I see.
                they seem to contain matters of such trivial interest outside of the district they are issued in, now I think 
                your papers ought as a rule to be universal in a <choice><sic>lare</sic><corr>large</corr></choice> 
                portion of <choice><sic>there</sic><corr>their</corr></choice> topics. if your
                National poetry to a large extent is intensely European I think the papers to large extent are essentially 
                <hi rend="underline">local</hi> in <choice><sic>there</sic><corr>their</corr></choice> articles. at least
                with very few exceptions, such I find is the case in those 
                I <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice>. the best piece of 
                <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">hopeful</unclear> 
                outspoken utterance in print I see is the reports of the Free Religious Association<ptr target="loc.01457_n2"/> of Boston. 
                It seems quite in Keeping with what supposes and expects from the <choice><sic>cultureed</sic><corr>cultured</corr></choice> 
                people of your land&#8212;but perhaps you <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> see it? so that
                my reference to it will not be of use to you.
                I help all I can here its circulation. Well I hope you will enjoy our little gift I hope in the perusal of
                each work you will something akin to the width and depth of your own heart. these are old utterances. yet new to us in 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01457.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                this lands. "the Gita" is one of my favourite Books, it is the <hi rend="underline">gem</hi> of all Indian lore.
                it is as <hi rend="underline">wide</hi> in its teachings and runs deep too as anything I have ever yet seen 
                in printed Book. I have tried hard to induce a <hi rend="underline">few souls</hi> 
                to aid in the issue of a cheap universal Edition of it. but have utterly failed. its present publisher been
                lead to do it, in the hopes it may lead to some such recognition by some of our Literary 
                <choice><sic>associtions</sic><corr>associations</corr></choice>&#8212;I 
                read with deepfelt sympathy the slight utterances as E.A. Poe<ptr target="loc.02448_n12"/> He and his Works have
                long been in part dear to me.&#8212;but what is it that is not so. and to 
                Carlyle<ptr target="n0139"/> and my own nature too and lastly to you and your teachings. how can one but feel 
                interested and moved by such a Nature and then I ask? How comes the distance in such life as 
                own such Souls? <hi rend="underline">We We</hi> poor mortals sit in 
                judgement on such&#8212;who know nothing of the nature or the environments of such. 
                I pause in my thoughts on all such, and gaze on them in wonderment&#8212;even with awe and silence too.&#8212;</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01457.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>How much of the Speculations of our time did he not solve. and lies therein <choice><sic>embeded</sic><corr>embedded</corr></choice> 
                in these wild wild awful stories of his. Ah! that nature is one that used one's love and deepest sympathy, 
                not our <hi rend="underline">Hate</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Scorn</hi>. as alas too often is given it. 
                your sketch of him in the Storm tossed vessel is very very awful real and true. it made me tremble while I read 
                it.&#8212;and I have read it up to friends 3 times who call in to hear the news. 
                <choice><sic>bye</sic><corr>by</corr></choice> the way is the photograph you sent me with your Beaver on 
                procurable yet? If so where and what price? The friend whose letter I sent you on your Critique on
                Burns<ptr target="n0127"/> who lives in London wants a copy. he has seen the one you 
                sent me in 1869. Now lastly I feel glad to see in our papers you have seen Conway<ptr target="n0170"/> again, 
                I once spent a little time pleasantly with him in London in 1873. He's a right noble free spoken man, full of 
                wise helpful energy of all sorts in his neighborhood in London. I regretted his notes on you was so very brief. 
                Will my subscription to your New Edition of your works, if sent you direct to America, be of any real aid in your 
                new efforts? let me know I will
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01454.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                see what I can do in the matter of subscribing for a few Copies&#8212;I would gladly like to aid you if I can
                do so. I think all who read your Books ought to help you in some way that would really be helpful&#8212;</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01454.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I feel in your case that it is only by some such method we cannot really help forward the work you aim to do.
                Excuse that simple free scrawl.&#8212;</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Yours Thankfully</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">Thomas Dixon</hi></signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01457.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="topleft">Dixon&#8212;Jan '76 ans Feb. 2/76</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01457.002_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>