<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01460">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 16 February
    1876</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Thomas Dixon</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
<persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01460</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc><bibl>
    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 16 February 1876</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1876-02-16" xml:id="dat1">February 16, 1876</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 8 Reel 5</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas" ref="n0196">Thomas Dixon</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-11-06" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-16" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-27" who="#al">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-11-04" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01460.001.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <note type="editorial" place="bottom" resp="whitman">sent p.card March 5, '76</note>
            <note type="editorial" place="bottom" resp="whitman" rend="circle">Th. Dixon</note>

            <!-- The following 2 lines were added at the top of the letter, seemingly in Dixon's hand, next to the dateline and above the salutation. I was not sure how to indicate that in the trasncription order -->

            <note type="authorial" place="bottom" anchored="true">Thomas Dixon's Greeting</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="bottom" anchored="true">excuse this scrawl I am so anxious to reply I feel
                quite nervous.</note>

            <opener>
                <address><addrLine>15 Sunderland Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Sunderland</addrLine></address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1876-02-16">16 Feb. 1876</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir, &amp; Friend </salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I hasten to reply to your letter of the 2nd which came to hand just last night, and I
                must confess cheered me for I had been expecting its arrival for some weeks, and was
                growing somewhat dubious my letter and package had gone astray, but thanks to the
                powers that be they have reached you all safely, and seemed to have been cheering
                and welcome <choice>
                    <sic>to</sic>
                    <corr>too</corr>
                </choice>: Well that was indeed glad news to me, for I must confess I suffer <choice>
                    <sic>to</sic>
                    <corr>too</corr>
                </choice> from Bronchial <choice>
                    <sic>Ashma</sic>
                    <corr>Asthma</corr>
                </choice>, and it makes me somewhat doleful at times, so that I often feel in dread
                when I write letters I write them <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#km">hopeful</unclear>
                <choice>
                    <sic>to</sic>
                    <corr>too</corr>
                </choice>: Well it was very gratifying to learn and see you <choice>
                    <sic>where</sic>
                    <corr>were</corr>
                </choice> still able to write a little, and work also a little&#8212;glad and
                welcome news that I could be a subscriber direct to you: our Ruskin here publishes
                his own Books, and how he does I will let you know <choice>
                    <sic>bye</sic>
                    <corr>by</corr>
                </choice> and <choice>
                    <sic>bye</sic>
                    <corr>by</corr>
                </choice>&#8212;I am anxious to reply to day so cannot <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01460.002.jpg" type="verso"/> inform you now. neither can I give you
                the copies from Dear <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#km">Canon</unclear> Kingsley's<!-- <ptr target="n0137"/> --> Lectures that I hope will be
                cheer you to read some day. I mean to send them. it is hopeful <hi rend="strikethrough">and</hi> full of the spirit of your own poems which from a
                parson and Chaplain to a Queen was good news to read to a Democrat. I loved the man.
                I loved his works. I honoured him for what he had attempted to do for the people,
                years ago, when Democracy was not so respectable. I mean to send you his portrait.
                he was a fine noble healthy looking man, fine read and Whiteflesh, like a Cultured
                farmer or Fisherman and had a large big hand and heart and stood somewhat your <choice>
                    <sic>hight</sic>
                    <corr>height</corr>
                </choice>. as near as I can guess fine blue gray Eyes. I met him 3 years ago. we had
                often promised to <choice>
                    <sic>me</sic>
                    <corr>meet</corr>
                </choice>, but alas never did so but that once: then only for an hour or two. Yet
                how full of sublime love and true fellowship the time passed.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01460.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <!-- Should we transcribe the page number? -al -->
            <p>his Wife <choice>
                    <sic>his</sic>
                    <corr>is</corr>
                </choice> now busy writing a sketch of his life, and I must try to send you one. I
                know you will love the man&#8212;I enclose you a P.O.O. for $3.00 send me the set of
                your works&#8212;and one copy of the two Rivulets (I want it to give to the writer
                of the letter I sent you on your Essay on Burns) I note you the Editions I have of
                your Works. I felt a regret I lost one. Yet after all I ought not for <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">from</unclear> it we got the first
                English Edition by W.W.&#8212;Leaves of Grass 1860, 1861 <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">are</unclear> have 3 copies if not four in our
                neighbourhood.</p>
            <p>The press Copy of Leaves of Grass 1867 that was used by Rossetti for his Edition of
                your Poems. his copy London 1868.&#8212;</p>
            <p>Leaves of Grass Washington 1872. </p>
            <p>Burrough's. Poet &amp; person&#8212;</p>
            <!-- I don't think we can consider these paragraphs of their own.  We could either encode as a list or make each an <ab>? -al -->

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01460.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <!-- Page number? -->
            <p>I mean to let you know how many copies of the 1872 I have <hi rend="underline">sold</hi> and given to folks I thought would like your Poems. that <choice>
                    <sic>his</sic>
                    <corr>is</corr>
                </choice> the way I contribute to my religion, which is the Books I love and like,
                so I sell them, or I give them away. So E. Poe's works have grown and spread here
                and in the Circle I move in. so too <choice>
                    <sic>Brete</sic>
                    <corr>Bret</corr>
                </choice> Harte's<!-- <ptr target="n0293"/> --> work. and last Joaquin <choice>
                    <sic>Millers</sic>
                    <corr>Miller's</corr>
                </choice><!-- <ptr target="n0412"/> --> is growing here. I speak of you, and get folks to
                read your Works, then to buy them, then to love and honour you. I wish your people
                in America would cease to be so doleful about you, and your Works let them who love
                you cherish, and aid the sale of this Edition and all other Editions then let the
                world, the newspaper, the other Authors and great men go their way, and do their
                work as best <choice>
                    <sic>the</sic>
                    <corr>they</corr>
                </choice> may. let us do ours but no repining If we love M. Antoninus<!-- <ptr target="n0373"/> -->, <choice>
                    <sic>Epitectus</sic>
                    <corr>Epictetus</corr>
                </choice> Socrates, Christ, and you, and the Band of fellows like you, let us serve
                you and help you all we can in silent <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01460.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <!-- page number? --> noble faithfulness. I love silent worship <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">aid</unclear> and help. that is who I
                love Carlyle<!-- <ptr target="n0139"/> -->. for years he made no sign, but waited and the Sun
                shone at last. let us all be content to wait. let us do our very best who are
                believers to aid and help our singers. but in silence I feel glad Joaquin Miller
                calls to see you. I love the man. I love a deal he has written, especially <choice>
                    <sic>is</sic>
                    <corr>his</corr>
                </choice> life amongst the Modocs. <choice>
                    <sic>theres</sic>
                    <corr>there's</corr>
                </choice> a little band here loves him too his ride to Brazos struck a fire that has
                grown to a white heat with us all. I copied a lot of his account of the Indians and
                their treatment and the pollution of the Rivers and sent it to Ruskin&#8212;he was
                deeply interested with it and said he had no idea that the pollution of your
                beautiful stream had also taken place</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01460.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <!-- page number? -->
            <p>he intends to make use of my tracts some day. Shake hands with Miller for me. tell I
                yearn to see him&#8212;and to own his portrait. tell him I have his Wife's noble
                defence of him. that I have read it often to friends here. I hope some day I may see
                you all and shake your hands and talk a little too. I was glad to learn Tennyson<!-- <ptr target="n0625"/> --> has
                still corresponded with you, and that he writes you so Kindly too. I love him for
                the noble poems he has written and for his noble heart, for years ago
                <!-- strange mark here. not sure how to transcribe --> he sent me many kind letters
                of deep sympathy and friendships when I first commenced to do work for my fellow
                workman. Conway<!-- <ptr target="n0170"/> --> too is a fine noble fellow. the others I dont
                know but I feel glad to see despite the <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">Oraters</unclear> against you. the power you possess is telling. go on
                in the spirit, and in the spirit may <hi rend="underline">we help</hi> you</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01460.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="authorial" place="bottom" anchored="true">No 2</note>
            <!-- Kevin had this as a <p>, but I've changed it as it seems more appropriate as a note, though I'm not sure whether it's authorial or editorial, since it's in pencil and therefore maybe a different hand, like the page numbers? -->
            <p>I see them now while I write this. I look into <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#km">thine</unclear> eyes. I grasp thy hand. thou grasps it <hi rend="underline">hard</hi>. thou looks upon me with a smile. I hear thee say:
                "All is peace now young man the storm is indeed past I live once again in the Souls
                and memories of those <choice>
                    <sic>Hero's</sic>
                    <corr>Heroes</corr>
                </choice> and all is Well!" Oh could I tell thee my feeling when I read that which
                thou tells me of "<unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#al">Lincoln</unclear>"&#8212;I loved the man, though I never knew him. Ruskin once
                wrote me a Note (when I told him what a noble soul he was) "how is it, this was
                never <choice>
                    <sic>Know</sic>
                    <corr>known</corr>
                </choice> until now?" that was at his Death. I soon let him know from printed matter
                &amp; had by me how it was I loved the man. he wrote and thanked me, and then said
                he was indeed glad to know your people had been blessed with such a man, and he then
                deeply regretted his sad end for your <choice>
                    <sic>peoples</sic>
                    <corr>people's</corr>
                </choice> sake. &#8212;</p>
            <p>So, you see my friend, your Captain is also Known and his memory made dear in places
                thou <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#al">dreamed</unclear> not of:
                so I tell thee this to cheer thee: and to show thee though silent, thou livest still
                warm in my heart and in all the hearts of our little land: one letter I send thee,
                which I hope will please thee: for it is written by one I love dear.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01460.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I enclose thee <choice>
                    <sic>is</sic>
                    <corr>his</corr>
                </choice> portrait, so that thou may know him also. I send also some M.S.S. that I
                have had copied from Canon Kingsley's works especially for you by another of the
                circle. it seemed strange the very passages I noted to be done was selected by you <choice>
                    <sic>to</sic>
                    <corr>too</corr>
                </choice> for your "two Rivulets" I send it altogether simply because I did not care
                to <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">disjoint</unclear>: also it
                seemed that there is a deep bond of sympathy between us&#8212;when we both should
                unknown to each other have both selected the same passage. I got a nice poem from
                W.J. Linton<!-- <ptr target="n0360"/> -->: I felt sorry it did not give me his
                address&#8212;I had it reprinted in one of our local papers it seems to have made an
                impression on some of our people: I would like to have sent to him a copy of the
                paper had I <choice>
                    <sic><corr>is</corr><corr>his</corr></sic>
                </choice> address: I also would like to introduce to him a young friend of <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.01460.009.jpg" type="recto"/> mine that is in New
                York: the son of a Quaker of Manchester: a fine noble fellow who died very suddenly
                to our sad loss for he was a noble soul, full of good broad liberal ideas with the
                power to give expression to them: a fighter in all good causes. his son seems a
                noble fellow&#8212;and I would so like him to know a man like Linton or any such
                soul. I feel I would like to make my young friend Know to some good souls for I
                think there is stuff in him. so if you can aid me in my wish it will help to
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#km">knit</unclear> the firmer our
                bonds of unity and love, and he may someday go and see you, and then our love will
                still be dearer for I advised him to go to America, so that I feel deeply interested
                in him &amp; his welfare&#8212;</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.01460.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>He seems a fine lad to me and I could rejoice exceedingly if he should visit you, for
                I yearn to hear what either you or any soul like you, would think of him. I often
                think I would like to visit America. in fact to settle in it: How much <choice>
                    <sic>mony</sic>
                    <corr>money</corr>
                </choice> would it take to buy <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">travel</unclear>? for a fellow to live on decently? I of course am no Farmer,
                but I would like to live a Farmer's life and <choice>
                    <sic>dont</sic>
                    <corr>don't</corr>
                </choice> see any chance here. Land's so dear, I am only a bad sailor or else I
                would have been on my way to see you this year: I often have long wished to see your
                country and its people, and I yearned to see it and them just in the way you have
                done&#8212;so you see I see them through your eyes and so love them all and you <choice>
                    <sic>to</sic>
                    <corr>too</corr>
                </choice>&#8212;</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Thomas Dixon<!-- <ptr target="n0196"/> --></signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>