<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01910">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Rudolf Schmidt to Walt Whitman, 20 March 1874</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Rudolf Schmidt</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.01910</idno></publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <!--<biblStruct xml:id="traubel">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Horace Traubel</author>
                        <title>With Walt Whitman in Camden: Volume 4</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">356&#8211;358</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct> -->
                <bibl>
                    <author>Rudolf Schmidt</author>
                    <title>Rudolf Schmidt to Walt Whitman, 20 March 1874</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1874-03-20" xml:id="dat1">March 20, 1874</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00337</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Schmidt, Rudolf" ref="n3070">Rudolf Schmidt</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-07-31" who="#smb">updated notes</change>
            <change when="2023-07-10" who="#aja">final corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2022-10-25" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-03-07" who="#cn">checked, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2021-12-02" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2013-02-01" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-09-24" who="#nnk">corrected "illustreret"</change>
            <change when="2012-03-22" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-29" who="#al">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-01-12" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01910.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                <name type="place">Copenhagen,</name>
                <date when="1874-03-20">20 March 1874.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter of the 4<hi rend="underline">th</hi><ptr target="loc.01910_n1"/> I received this morning. 
                The number of Harper's<ptr target="n0290"/> magazine and of the New York Tribune<ptr target="duk.00474_n11"/>
                did <hi rend="underline">not</hi> follow, but most probably they will reach me; printed matter is very 
                often going an other way. If your "Prayer of Columbus"<ptr target="n0482"/> be not too long, I shall try to
                get a translation of it published in one of our papers.</p>
            <p>Immediately after my return from Germany (28<hi rend="underline">th</hi> February) I did write to you<ptr target="loc.01910_n2"/> and
                sent you a long article of your book in the paper "Fædrelandet"<ptr target="n0007"/> (fatherland);
                the last monday I for mailed for you another article in the weekly paper "Nær og Fjern" (Near and 
                Far).<ptr target="n0430"/> All these things have been sent to New Jersey. To the Treasury in Washington have been sent in all <hi rend="underline">three</hi> 
                copies of "Demokratiske Fremblik,"<ptr target="n0189"/> one in loose sheets (franked), one complete paper
                bound copy franked and an other unpaid (for greater safety, as unpaid letters and papers never fail their man). 
                Some copies of "Illustreret Fædrelandet" (peoples illustrated magazine) with 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01910.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                your portrait and some short biographical notices have also been sent to Washington.</p>
            <p>With Clausen<ptr target="loc.01711_n4"/> I sent you in the autumn 1872 a large portrait of mine, the only resembling 
                one, that ever has been taken. Write to Mrs Clausen, if they have not forwarded it to you.</p>
            <p>If you could, without troubling yourself too much, send me <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the pieces of Clemens 
                Petersen,<ptr target="n0780"/> that come to your eye-sight, I should be very glad. This singular man has 
                a great charm to me, though I never liked him.</p>
            <p>If my thoughts did not weaken and wither, when I try to give them expression in the English language, I should 
                on some sheets give you a due description of our political and literary doings. Although the word of Hamlet: 
                there is something rotten in the state of Denmark, still are true, I have the greatest belief of the vitality 
                of my people and the other Scandinavian peoples. We have been living here in the outskirts of civilization; we 
                have been endowed with its gifts, but we <choice><sic>have have</sic><corr>have</corr></choice> not been poisoned 
                with its venom. Ours is the future in Europe, small as we are.</p>
            <p>In no European country, and most probably also not in America, your personality, your mode of 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01910.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                viewing the things shall be more sure to touch the chord of the native mind as here and in Norway. We are made 
                of the true democratic stuff, we have not the venomous passions, but we have the high ideal aspiration. A peasant 
                on Fijen (one of our fertile isles) wrote to me in the spring for two years ago to thank me for my article on you. 
                Peasants are on the sundays holding the numbers of "for Ide og Virkelighed"<ptr target="n0239"/> 
                in their <supplied reason="illegible" source="#traubel" resp="#km">hard fists</supplied> 
                and read every word, though the matters often are very difficult.</p>
            <p>But on the <hi rend="underline">political</hi> arena our democratic leaders are dull and narrowminded persons, 
                to say nothing worse. None of them has named your book yet, most probably they won't name it at all. It is your 
                (political) adversaries, who write criticisms on you. But your adversaries are mostly your friends, they have 
                themselves a democratic mind and grant you much more than the editors of the American magazines. But your best 
                friends are the women. A young Baroness <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">Fraupe</unclear><ptr target="n5001"/> 
                has read your books with true enthusiasm. The women have understood, that the ordinary criticisms can as easily 
                be applied on a nature like yours as the process of hair cutting and shaving on a mountain forest. 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01910.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                "It is nearly comical", writes a young married lady to me, "to see the critics cut and crisp the broad
                American till they have given him their own small figure."</p>
            <p>Your early female friend Mrs <supplied reason="illegible" source="#traubel" resp="#km">Rorle</supplied><ptr target="n5001"/> lies 
                deathly over in Roma—poor thing.</p>
            <p>Professor Rasmus Nielsen<ptr target="n0443"/> has read your book with the greatest satisfaction. He is the only 
                man, who could give a true criticism on it, but he is an old man and not very willing to write in the papers.</p>
            <p>Hoping a speedy amelioration of your health<ptr target="duk.00621_n14"/> I remain</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours</salute>
                <signed>Rudolf Schmidt</signed>
            </closer>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="right">Rud. Schmidt March 20 '74</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>