<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01324">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Moncure D. Conway to Walt Whitman, 24 April
    1876</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Moncure D. Conway</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder
        Jaramillo</persName>
<persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01324</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>Moncure D. Conway</author>
    <title>Moncure D. Conway to Walt Whitman, 24 April 1876</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1876-04-24" xml:id="dat1">April 24, 1876</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Conway, Moncure D." ref="n0170">Moncure D. Conway</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-10-29" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-02" who="#js">proofed, added envelope encoding</change>
            <change when="2012-02-24" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-12-20" who="#ej">Transcribe/Encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01324.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <address><addrLine>2 Pembroke Gardens,</addrLine><addrLine>W. <name type="place">London</name>.</addrLine></address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1876-04-24">April 24 '76</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p><choice>
                    <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                    <expan>William</expan>
                </choice> Roſsetti has shown me your letter indicating annoyance at some
                telegram which has reached America, concerning a statement of mine in the Daily
                News. <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#js">Never</unclear> was no
                letter of mine in the paper or any paper, but a paragraph which I enclose to you
                written by the editor on the basis of a private letter from me. I wrote to him on
                receipt of a letter from you saying that you wished money to build on your Camden
                lot and paid board to your relatives. My motive was the necessity of saving you
                &amp; your relatives from the degradation implied in Mr. Austin's letter to the same
                paper in which he said "While we talk, he starves"; to defend your American friends
                (such as Burroughs, O Connor<!-- <ptr target="n0452"/> -->, myself &amp; others) from the
                outrageous insults heaped by that fellow Buchanan<!-- <ptr target="n0117"/> --> upon those of
                your countrymen who would share their last loaf with you; and to free you from the
                charge of getting aid on false pretences, of which you were in danger, and myself
                from equal peril of abutting what I knew to be a lie by silence; and you are not the
                man I take you for if you would have had me act otherwise. I can only suppose you
                have seen some bungled &amp; mutilated telegram embodying part of the statement of
                which I now send you the whole.</p>
            <p>You may remember that I talked to you in my bedroom about your circumstances, after I
                had conversed with your sister–in–law, and gathered from <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01324.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> you just what
                you have been kind enough to write to me, except that you did not tell me that you
                wished to build.</p>

            <p>In such matters as this the true thing is obviously the politic thing also. It is
                ludicrously false for Buchanan to say that you are in danger of starving, or that
                you have no appreciation in America (where books have been written about you, and
                where you have enthusiastic admirers!) Such absurd and false statements are sure to
                bring down contempt on them who make them, and sometimes imperil the good fame of
                those about whom they are made.</p>
            <p>Your friends here are quite at one here on the subject, and Rossetti<!-- <ptr target="n0522"/> --> wrote to me that
                he knew Buchanans statements were "exaggerations", before I wrote to the <hi rend="underline">News</hi>. The effort to circulate your books by a subscription
                will be succeſsful. Rossetti has had printed for private circulation your
                letter to him which gives substantially the same account of your affairs which is
                contained in the paragraph of the Daily News enclosed.</p>

            <p>I am much oppressed with work, I cannot write letters. I trust this will find you
                improving in health. Pray remember me kindly to Mr &amp; Mrs Whitman </p>

            <closer>
                <salute>I believe me your faithful friend</salute>
                <signed>M D Conway</signed>
            </closer>

            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01324.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01324.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>