<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01987">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Benton H. Wilson to Walt Whitman, 27 January
                    1867</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Benton H. Wilson</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska–Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt> 
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01987</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Benton H. Wilson</author>
                    <title>Benton H. Wilson to Walt Whitman, 27 January 1867</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1867-01-27" xml:id="dat1">January 27, 1867</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 19, Reel 11&#8211;12</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00423 </idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt
                    Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Wilson, Benton H." ref="n0810b">Benton H. Wilson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-09-24" who="#smb">final checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-07-21" who="#kjb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-01-24" who="#cn">checked, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2021-10-27" who="#aja">2nd check, notes</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-03-15" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-15" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-09-28" who="#kk">transcribed; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.01477_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <body>
            <opener> 
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Syracuse <date when="1867-01-27" rend="right"
                            >Jan 27<hi rend="underline">th</hi>/1867 <ptr target="loc.01987_n1"
                            /></date></name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend<ptr target="n0810"/></salute>
            </opener>
            <p>your letter of the 10<hi rend="underline">th</hi> of January<ptr target="n5002d"/>
                was received more than a week ago and should have been answered before this time but
                I have not been in the humor of writing and have kept putting it off till some more
                convenient season but I will try to be more punctual in the future.</p>
            <p>Father<ptr target="n0811"/> is staying with me again and he borrowed "Leaves of
                Grass," for me of Dr. Hawley<ptr target="loc.01987_n2"/> for a few days and was very
                much interested in it, but I <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.01478_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> will be candid with you.</p>
            <p>I think on the start I was more interested in it because it was your work, than for
                the good sentiments it contained, but as I got more acquainted with it I liked it
                for its own value, although I can not understand all of it I can not find anything
                indecent about it. But my kind Old Friend you must not think that because I wrote to
                you and mentioned it, that I wish you to send me the Book for that is not what I
                intended for you to think.</p>
            <p>Drum Taps<ptr target="n0819"/> I have not seen yet nor is it to be found at any of
                the stores in <name>Syracuse</name>. Dr. Hawley has been trying to get a copy of it
                for about a <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.01479_large.jpg" type="recto"/> month
                but all that was here were taken as soon as they arrived.</p>
            <p>We have splendid sleighing here now, and have had for about, two or three weeks or
                more.</p>
            <p>You say you wish me to write how I am situated what I am doing &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I wrote to you a year and more ago that I was married but did not receive any reply
                so I did not know but you was displeased with it.</p>
            <p>I was married to a New York Lady, Daughter of the late I.L.
                    Gage of the firm of Gage, Sloans &amp; Dater<ptr
                    target="loc.01987_n3"/>
                <name>No 83 <choice>
                        <sic>Chamber</sic>
                        <corr>Chambers</corr>
                    </choice> St and 65 <choice>
                        <sic>Reed</sic>
                        <corr>Reade</corr>
                    </choice> St</name> but like many others they went down in the crisis of
                    1857<ptr target="loc.01987_n5"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.01480_large.jpg" type="verso"/> I went into
                Business with a partner at manufacturing Parlor Brackets a little over a year ago
                and continued at it about six or Seven months and lost about one thousand dollars
                and found myself in debt six hundred dollars and finally came to the conclusion that
                it was time I closed up my business, so I did so about the first of July last, and
                am now at work at my trade in a Piano Forte &amp; Melodeon<ptr target="n0406"/>
                Manufactory and find that it pays me better than business on my own book. Now I
                think I have given you a good statement of my situation and hope it will be to your
                satisfaction</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.01483_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>If you come to <name>New York</name> next summer on a visit I shall expect you to
                take a short trip up here to see me (if I am here) and I will pay your fare and take
                as good care of you as we possibly can. Now if you come to <name>New York</name>,
                you must not fail to let me know it.</p>
            <p>Hamilton<ptr target="n5001"/> has returned from the west, his Brother<ptr target="n5001"/> is gaining slowly, he sends his love
                to you and says he will write to you.<ptr target="n5001c"/></p>
            <p>Father<ptr target="n0811"/> is living with me now, he says he wrote to you a few days ago<ptr
                    target="loc.01987_n4"/></p>
            <p>My Wife<ptr target="loc.01987_n6"/> wants me to send her love to you for she says she loves
                any body that I love <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.01484_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> I devote some of my leisure to reading and writing but I have not
                had any History except what we have got in the house, because I have not had access
                to the Libraries, but if you will write what history I shall get, I will get a
                library ticket and try to get them. History is my favorite reading</p>
            <p>I do not know as this letter will be very interesting to you so I will close for this
                time hoping to hear from you again soon.</p>  
            <closer>
                <salute>I remain as ever Your</salute>
                <salute>Boy Friend </salute>
                <salute>with Love</salute>
                <signed>Benton H. Wilson</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_vm.01481_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="envelope-marginala">B.H. Wilson, Jan 27 ans.
                Jan 31, '67</note>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="envelope-marginala">Atty Genls</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_vm.01482_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
