<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02980">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 12 September
                    1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ellen M. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02980</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ellen M. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 12 September 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-09-12" xml:id="dat1">September 12, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 13, Reel 8</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M." ref="n4137">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-06-27" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-05-29" who="#aa">second check</change>
            <change when="2019-04-29" who="#blh">first check</change>
            <change when="2016-10-13" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02980.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">North Perry, Maine.</name>
                    <date when="1889-09-12">Sept. 12. 1889.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Thank you for papers sent, &#38; for all loving thought. I hope you are "holding your
                own."</p>
            <p>I must have gained a little here, for I sleep more, and have a better appetite. I am
                going to be weighed, I weighed 95 the day before I left Washington.<pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02980.002.jpg" type="verso"/> I write now especially
                to tell you that I intend to leave here next Monday, Sept. 16, unless a storm should
                prevent. We have to go to Eastport 12 miles by wagon, &#38; then take steamer to
                Boston. If it is stormy, Mrs. Porter<ptr target="n5001"/> says we must take the next boat, that
                would be Sept. 18. Wednesday. But in any case after you get this letter, my
                    address<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02980.003.jpg" type="recto"/> will be
                care of my nephew in Boston which I will give in a separate slip. I shall make a few
                short stops with nieces &#38; others till I return home, &#38; as my nephew is a fixture, he will forward any thing to me
                wherever I am. I shall not go home till into October I think. We have had such a wet
                &#38; rainy summer there that I know I better wait a while. I <hi rend="underline"
                    >dread</hi>, dear Walt, I can't tell any<pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.02980.004.jpg" type="verso"/> one how much I dread the going back
                home. I say <hi rend="underline">home</hi>, but the sense of loneliness that
                overtakes me when I think of going is heart-sickening. And the uncertainty of all
                adds to it. If I were sure that I could make any arrangement to keep a home, I
                should feel better, but all is so cloudy &#38; misty. But I try to keep up a good
                heart, &#38; not to worry my friends with my troubles.</p>
            <p>I have one hope that I am clinging to, and that is that my sister Mrs. Channing<ptr
                    target="loc.02980_n1"/> may<pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.02980.005.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>
                come on. She has not been East since they went to Cal. five years next month, &#38;
                she wants to come if their finances will allow, &#38; it will be the greatest
                comfort &#38; help to me, as she can advise me better than any one, what to do,
                &#38; help me about disposing of William's<ptr target="n2002"/> papers &#38;c. He
                left all to me absolutely, but I should be so glad of help in many matters, &#38;
                wish I had any one near at hand who could advise with me.</p>
            <p>Do you think there is<pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.02980.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                any <hi rend="underline">good</hi> picture of William? one that you really like?
                Appleton has sent for me for the Encyclopedia,<ptr target="loc.02980_n3"/> &#38; I have not the one that I like
                best here with me, &#38; the <hi rend="underline">best</hi> of the late ones is not
                to <hi rend="underline">my</hi> mind. How do you like the one in "The Great
                    Cryptogram?"<ptr target="loc.02980_n2"/></p>
            <p>Thanks for the papers. Critic came yesterday with the Hawthorne letters. I was glad
                to see them.</p>
            <p>You will see what a remote place this is, &#38; how<pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="loc.02980.007.jpg" type="recto"/> protected the shore when I tell you that
                the heavy sea of last Sunday &#38; Monday did not reach us. It is the only seashore
                place that I ever touched where there is never any surf.</p>
            <p>Good by.</p>
            <p>I send my address on the enclosed slip.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>With love always&#8212;</salute>
                <signed>Nelly O'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>(over)</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.02980.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <p>I have a picture of William taken long ago that I like <hi rend="underline">very
                        much</hi> but would it be as satisfactory to the friends generally as the
                    later ones, taken four years ago?</p>
                <p>If you are able to write, I should like your thought in this matter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Yours&#8212;</salute>
                    <signed>Nelly O'Connor.</signed>
                </closer>
                <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" rend="circled">
                    the address is <address>
                        <addrLine>care Charles E Legg</addrLine> 
                        <addrLine>146 Devonshire St:</addrLine> 
                        <addrLine>Boston Mass:</addrLine>
                    </address></note>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
