<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.05439">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Abraham Paul Leech, 19 August [1840]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="em">Erel Michaelis</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt> 
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05439</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only. </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Abraham Paul Leech, 19 August [1840]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1840-08-19" xml:id="dat1">August 19 [1840]</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS77909, Box 1</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms005001.mss77909.002</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Walt Whitman Papers: Correspondence, Miscellaneous Manuscript Collection, 
                        Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="al"><persName key="Leech, Abraham Paul">Abraham Paul
                        Leech</persName></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="unk"><persName key="Unknown">Unknown</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Leech, Abraham Paul" ref="loc.05440_n1">Abraham Paul Leech</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-07-25" who="#aja">final corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2022-08-29" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-06-21" who="#kjb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-03" who="#em">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-07" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-30" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-28" who="#cn">transcribed,encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_gk.01477_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Purgatory Fields,<ptr target="loc.05440_n2"/></name> 
                    <date when="1840-08-19">Wednesday Aug 19.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Have you never heard people advance the opinion that earth is man's heaven or hell,
                according as he acts or is situated, good or evil?&#8212;I believe that doctrine;
                or, at any rate, I believe half of it, as the man said when he was told that his
                wife had twins.&#8212;That this earthly habitation, is a place of torment to my
                miserable self, is made painfully evident every day of existence.&#8212;Fate never
                made a place where dulness perched on every tree, obtuseness located himself on
                every hill, and despair might be seen "sittin on a rail," every ten yards, so
                completely as in this cursed Woodbury.&#8212;</p>
            <p>&#8212;Woodbury! appropriate name!&#8212;it <hi rend="underline"
                >would</hi>-bury me or any being of the least wish for intelligent society, in
                one year, if compelled to endure its intolerable insipidity without the hope of
                relief.&#8212;Before many weeks, I expect to be in the condition of those pleasant
                beings of whom it is said "They are nothing but skin and bone."&#8212;you do not
                know, my friend, nor can you conceive, the horrid dulness of this
                place.&#8212;Making money, plodding on, and on, and on; raising ducks, carting dung,
                and eating pork, are the only methods of employment that occupy the Woodbury
                animals.&#8212;And as avocations of this nature never met my fancy in any great
                degree, you may easily imagine what an interesting situation I am in.&#8212;</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_gk.01478_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I have eaten my dinner since the last line over leaf was written; but I don't know
                that I feel any the better as to good-humour.&#8212;What do you think I had
                for dinner?&#8212;Guess
                now.&#8212;Beef?&#8212;no.&#8212;Mutton?&#8212;No.&#8212;Pot&#8211;pie?
                No.&#8212;Salad and iced champagne?&#8212;No, no, no,&#8212;I'll tell you in the
                order that it was put up, or rather put down.&#8212;Firstly, two cold potatoes, with
                the skins on, one of said potatoes, considerably nibbled in a manner which left me
                in doubt whether it had been done by the teeth of a mouse or the bill of a chicken;
                secondly three boiled clams, that had evidently seen their best days;&#8212;thirdly
                a chunk of molasses cake made of buckwheat flour:&#8212;fourthly, a handful of old
                mouldy pot-cheese, with a smell strong enough to knock down an
                ox;&#8212;fifthly, and lastly, two oblong slats of a mysterious substance, which I
                concluded, after considerable reflection, must have been intended for
                bread:&#8212;this last would undoubtedly been very interesting either to a
                Grahamite, or to one fond of analyzing and studying out the nature of the <hi
                    rend="underline">mineral</hi> kingdom.&#8212;Wasn't this a feast for an
                Epicure?&#8212;Think, O thou banquetter on good things, think of such an infernal
                meal as that I describe and bless the stars that thy lot is as it is.&#8212;Think,
                moreover, that this diabolocal compound was wrapped up in huge piece of brown paper,
                and squeezed into a <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_gk.01479_large.jpg" type="verso"
                /> little tin pail, which said pail, being minus in the matter of a handle or bail,
                had to be carried by a tow string instead!&#8212;Imagine to yourself, now that you
                see me toting along with such an article as I been describing.&#8212;Don't I cut a
                pretty figure? O, ye gods, press me not too far&#8212;pour not my cup too
                full&#8212;or I know what I shall do.&#8212;Dire and dreadful thoughts have lately
                been floating through my brain.&#8212;The next you hear of me, I may possibly be
                arraigned for murder, or highway robbery, or assault and battery, at the
                least.&#8212;I am getting savage.&#8212;There seems to be no relief.&#8212;Fate is
                doing her worst.&#8212;The devil is tempting me in every nook and corner and unless
                you send me a letter, and Brenton remits me an armful of news, there is no telling
                but what I shall poison the whole village, or set fire to this old
                school-house, and run away by the light of it.&#8212;</p>
            <p>I suppose all "your folks" are the same as usual, and that Jamaica is "situate,
                lying, and being" as in November last.&#8212;But do for pity's sake foreward
                something or other to me soon, in the shape of mental food.&#8212;May you grow fat
                with peace and good cheer.&#8212;May the sun of peace warm you, and the dews of
                prosperity fall thick around your path.&#8212;May the Fates be busy with cutting
                other threads than yours&#8212;and may kind fingers shield you in the hour of
                death.&#8212;</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Adieu.&#8212;</salute>
                <signed>Walter Whitman</signed>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_gk.01480_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Abraham P. Leech</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Jamaica L. I.</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#al" place="left">W Whitman August 19th</note>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#unk" place="left">1840 Woodbury / 40</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
