<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01820">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 09 May
    1867</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>William D. O'Connor</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
<persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01820</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 09 May 1867</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1867-05-09" xml:id="dat1">May 9, 1867</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-27">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-11-28" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-05-02" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-30" who="#al">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-01-28" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01820.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <address><addrLine>Washington, D.C.</addrLine></address>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <date when="1867-05-09">May 9, 1867.</date></dateline>
                <salute>My dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I duly got your letter of May 5th and was very glad to hear from you. I sent you a
                letter which came for you on Monday, and which I hope
                you got, and herewith enclose another which Ramsdell<!-- <ptr target="n0494"/> --> left for you.</p>

            <p>I earnestly hope George will be better when this reaches you. We all felt sobered
                 to know that
                he was so badly. The turn in the weather today,
                 I think will be good for him.</p>

            <p>I can well imagine how you must have felt to see him so, and how sad it must be for
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01820.002.jpg" type="verso"/> your mother.</p>

            <p>I enclose a letter I got from that child of a burnt father, Allen<!-- <ptr target="n0033"/> -->, which you can bring back with you when you come. It is truly Pecksniffian, and
                seems to have been written on all&#8212;fours. You will see that it ends the matter
                of publishing the book, and he doesn't say a word about John Burroughs' book, but of
                course that is understood to be declined also. I have written him, saying that John
                will at once put the book to press himself.</p>

            <p>I had another letter from Raymond yesterday, very kind <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01820.003.jpg" type="recto"/> and friendly. He evidently does not yet
                know of the Allen–Carleton decision. Part of it is about my coming upon the
                    <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>&#8212;a sort of hankering treatment of the
                subject, but no offer, which of course he
                couldn't well make, not knowing exactly how useful or available my talent would be
                to him. He has not heard that I was in New York. I shall write him&#8212;today,
                 if I can.</p>

            <p>I think, on the whole, it is probably altogether best that Carleton should have
                nothing to do with "Leaves of Grass,"
                though I
                would well enough like him to publish the "Notes."</p>

            <p>&#8212;I write in a hurry, nearly <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01820.004.jpg" type="verso"/> on mail time. Nelly charged me to send you her love. Your letter
                was very sweet. I think a young girl finding herself beloved or admired by some one
                unsuspected before, must feel as I did when I read how the household thought of me.
                But I didn't lay myself out at all, as you say, and moreover, the evening I was
                there I had a shocking headache.</p>

            <p>Give my loving remembrance to all, especially your mother. I have not yet succeeded
                in telling you (you know we were interrupted each time we began to talk of it,) how
                deeply she affected me. Her cheerfulness, her infinite gentleness and tenderness,
                were  like the deep <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01820.005.jpg" type="recto"/> smile of the evening
                sky. As I saw her that night, with the children on each side, and each leaning a
                head upon her, I thought of the Madonna grown old.</p>

            <p>Charley bade me send you his love. He has been in the most extraordinary jolly humor
                all this week. It is as if the Cheeryble Brothers were
                rolled into one. The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> has done him the recent
                 honor of copying at length, and
                devoting an editorial to, besides, one of his late letters to the <hi rend="underline">Standard</hi>, in which he comes the bloody Roman centurion on
                a batch <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01820.006.jpg" type="verso"/>of politicians,
                sparing not one.</p>

            <p>H. Clapp will end by becoming a respectable citizen. When once a man enters upon the
                downward path, &amp;c. Like De Quincey's warning against the practice of <hi rend="underline">murder</hi>, on the ground that it leads to procrastination and
                Sabbath breaking, so one  can see
                as the guilty result of Bohemianism, a place in the Common Council or Board of
                Aldermen!</p>

            <p>Good bye.
                
                I hope George is better today.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Your very faithful</salute>
                <signed>W.D.O'C.<!-- <ptr target="n0452"/> --></signed>
            </closer>

            <!--    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01820.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <address><addrLine>Walt Whitman, Esq</addrLine><addrLine>Box 218</addrLine><addrLine>Brooklyn, N.Y.</addrLine></address>
            Notes in Whitman's hand:
            <note type="editorial" place="marginleft">Wm O'Connor</note>
            <note type="editorial" place="marginleft">May 1867.</note>-->
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>