<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.03546">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Helen E. Price to Walt Whitman, 2 February 1891</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Helen E. Price</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="hc">Heather Cooper</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="tb">Tara Ballard</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03546</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2022 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Helen E. Price</author>
                    <title>Helen E. Price to Walt Whitman, 2 February 1891</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1891-02-02" xml:id="dat1">February 2, 1891</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8&#8211;9</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00315</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Price, Helen E." ref="n4167">Helen E. Price</persName>
                 </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-07-29" who="#smb">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2022-03-01" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2022-02-11" who="#tb">rotated, added envelope images</change>
            <change when="2021-10-27" who="#cn">checked, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2021-07-30" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-12-06" who="#hc">transcribed, encoded; SLIS:6335: Metadata Theories and Applications Class, Fall 2020, Micah Bateman, 
                Lecturer, University of Iowa</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>    
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03546.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
            <opener> 
                <dateline>                
                    <date when="1891-02-02">Feb 2nd 91<ptr target="loc.03546_n11"/></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear friend Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> 
                I have not written to you all these years because I knew there were many others waiting for a word or line and 
                I could not bear to add even a feathers weight to your burden. I should not do so now only I think I am getting to 
                feel a little hungry for a sight of your hand writing once more, and a few lines of remembrance and affection.</p>
            <p>
                Mr Arthur Stedman<ptr target="n4177"/> came to see me several times 
                last week and gave me lots of information about you and your surroundings and 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03546.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>   
                friends in Camden. That was all good and I was indeed grateful for it, but I want just a few lines from you if you 
                feel able to write.</p>  
            <p> 
                What a long hard hill and strain it has been for you the last fifteen years. My eyes fill with tears when I think 
                of it. I knew you, as you know, in your splendid health and prime, and so realize the more keenly perhaps, what the 
                loss of all that has been and is to you. I know you have had a poor spell lately. Are you growing better? Let me 
                know dearest Walt just how you are.</p>  
            <p>
                We are all about as usual in Woodside. Emily<ptr target="loc.03546_n6"/> and her family are prospering. 
                Her oldest boy<ptr target="loc.03546_n7"/> nearly 21 is with Arthur<ptr target="loc.03546_n8"/> in Florida. He resigned from the Navy several years ago, and is 
                very cheerful and
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03546.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                contented in Florida on his orange grove; he writes me that he is a 
                good deal of a Hermit down there. Abby<ptr target="loc.03546_n2"/> has grown up into a beautiful young lady and quite accomplished in music. The 
                twins are fine boys The one I have is a Stenographer in a lawyers office.<ptr target="loc.03546_n3"/> He is truly the chief comfort of my life. 
                Walter<ptr target="loc.03546_n4"/> is a fine handsome little fellow now about 11, and crazy for horses; can ride horse back, 
                drive a four in hand, and in fact cares 
                very little for anything else.</p> 
            <p>
                I live very quietly in my little cottage, rent the lower floor and though I feel cramped a good deal sometimes 
                by poverty, yet am thankful to be as well off as I am.</p>
            <p>
                I was very much surprised to hear of Jeff's<ptr target="n0710"/> death. What was the cause? and are his daughters<ptr target="loc.03546_n5"/> married?
                and where are they? George<ptr target="duk.00425_n2"/> and Lou<ptr target="duk.00615_n6"/> I should like to hear about them and above all            
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03546.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>     
                Eddie<ptr target="n1047"/> Mr. S. told me he was living.</p> 
            <p>
                There is a matter that has come to my notice lately that I am very anxious to get at the truth about, and 
                is one reason for writing to you now.</p>
            <p>
                When you revised the matter for Dr Bucke's<ptr target="n0119"/> book<ptr target="loc.03546_n9"/> at our house did you do so from the original documents 
                or from proof sheets of the same. The letter he published written by you to my mother<ptr target="loc.00940_n6"/> about the 
                hospitals<ptr target="loc.03546_n1"/> and sacred almost to me came back torn and mutilated A change was made in the wording 
                and meaning of a sentence and the correction torn out. 
                         
                There was not a line or erasure anywhere 
                else on the letter, though you made a number of changes yourself, I think from the proof sheets. 
                Let me know please dear Walt what you remember about it It is important to me though I shall make 
                no use of the information whatever. I only want to be sure that it was not you that multilated it.</p>
            <p>
                Mr S. showed me the <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#hc" cert="low">large</unclear><ptr target="loc.03546_n10"/>      
                last edition of Leaves of Grass.<ptr target="loc.04811_n6"/> Also November Boughs<ptr target="n3999"/> which I had not seen. How much is 
                it a copy. I must have one.</p>
            <p> Talking with him brought up the old times so vividly. 
                When our dearest mothers were 
                living and well. Those dear old days are gone never to return again. Ah me! Life is somewhat 
                of a tragedy, is it not?</p>
            <p>
                Write me soon if you feel able, dear Walt. I am so desirous of knowing that you are better</p>   
            <closer> 
                <signed>Affectionately</signed>
                <signed>Helen</signed>
            </closer>            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_tb.00116.jpg" type="recto"/>  
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_tb.00117.jpg" type="verso"/>  
        </body>
    </text>    
</TEI>
