<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.02882">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 18 May 1875</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.02882</idno></publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <!--<biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Garden City, New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1964">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">126&#8211;128</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>-->
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 18 May 1875</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1875-05-18" xml:id="dat1">May 18, 1875</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS45443, Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms002007.mss45443.0111</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842–1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc> 
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-10" who="#smb">updated notes</change>
            <change when="2023-06-26" who="#aja">final corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-03-24" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-01-19" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-11-21" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-12" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-06-05" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-05-18" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-04-23" who="#al">Checked with microfilm images.</change>
            <change when="2011-08-07" who="#zk">transcribed and encoded from Harned; annotated AG and family</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02882.001_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>50 Marquis Rd. Camden Sq.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>London</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <date when="1875-05-18" rend="right">May 18, 1875</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dearest Friend,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Since last I wrote to you at the beginning of April<ptr target="n5002d"/> (enclosing a little photograph of the 
                old avenue just by our cottage at Colne) I have been into Wales for a fortnight to see Percy<ptr target="n2000"/>
                &amp; have looked, for the first time in my life, on the Atlantic—the ocean my mental eyes travel over 
                &amp; beyond so often, and that your eyes and ears &amp; heart have been fed by, have communed with and
                interpreted, as in a new tongue to the soul of man. Looking upon that, 
                watching the tides ebb &amp; flow, that ebb &amp; flow on your shores, sharing, through my
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02882.002_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                
                beloved book, in those greatest moments you have spent alone with it—that was a new joyful experience, 
                a fresh kind of communing with you.—I went to Wales because I felt anxious about Percy, who is not happy
                just now. I must not tell friends here about it (except his brother &amp; sisters but I am sure I may tell you,
                for you will listen with sympathy. He has attached himself very deeply, I think it will prove, to a girl, &amp; 
                she to him, whose parents welcomed him cordially to their house for a year or two &amp; allowed plenty of
                intercourse till they became aware, through Percy himself who thought it right 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02882.003_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                to tell the father as soon as he was fully aware of his own feelings &amp; more than suspected 
                Norah's<ptr target="loc.02882_n6"/> response to them) that there was a strong affection growing up between the two. 
                Then they peremptorily forbad all intercourse,—not because they have any objection to Percy—quite 
                the contrary they say; but solely and simply because he is not yet earning money enough to marry on, &amp; 
                they hold that a man has no right to engage a girl's affections 
                till he can do so. As if these things could be timed to the moment the money comes in! Percy 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02882.004_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                was in hopes &amp; so was I, that if I went down, I might get sense enough into their heads, 
                if not kindness &amp; sympathy into their hearts, to see that the sole effect of such arbitrary &amp; 
                narrow sighted conduct would be to alienate &amp; embitter the young people's feelings toward them, 
                while it would make them more restless &amp; anxious to marry without adequate means. Whereas if a reasonable
                amount of intercourse were allowed, it would be a happy time with them, &amp; Norah 
                being still so young, (18), &amp; Percy,— 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.02882.005_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                working away with all his might, doing very well for his age &amp; sure, conscientious thorough capable 
                &amp; well trained worker that he is (for the L. School of Mais gives a first-rate scientific preparation 
                for his profession) to be making a modest sufficiency in a year or two. Well, they were very courteous &amp; 
                indeed friendly to me &amp; I think I have won over the mother but the father remains obdurate, 
                &amp; Percy feels bitterly the 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.02882.006_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/>
                separation—all the more trying as they live almost within sight of each other. So 
                Beatrice<ptr target="n0260"/> &amp; Grace<ptr target="n0261"/> are going to spend their holidays with 
                him this summer to cheer him up. Meanwhile, dear friend, I am on the whole happier than not about him. 
                I liked what I saw of Norah &amp; believe he has found a very sweet affectionate girl of quiet, 
                domestic nature, practical—industrious sensible—thoroughly well to suit him, 
                &amp; that there is true &amp; deep love between them—also she took to me very much &amp; I 
                feel will be quite another
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.02882.007_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                child to me. It is besides no little joy to me to find how Percy has confided in me in this &amp; chooses me 
                as the friend to whom he tells all—far from being any separation as sometimes happens this love 
                of his seems to draw us closer together. Only I am very, very anxious for his sake to see him in a better
                berth—they would let her marry him on £300 a year; now he has only £175. He is quite competent 
                to manage iron or copper or tin works, only he looks so young, not having yet 
                any beard or moustache to speak of. That is the end of my long story.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.02882.008_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>This will reach you on your birthday perhaps my dearest Friend; at any rate it must bear you a greeting of 
                love and fond remembrance for that dear day such as my heart will send you when it actually comes: 
                patiently waiting heart, with the fibres of love and boundless trust &amp; joy &amp; hope which bind me to 
                you bedded deep, grown to be, during these long years, a very part of its immortal substance untouchable
                by age or varying moods or sickness, or death itself, as I surely believe. I 
                long more than words can tell to know how it fares with you now in health &amp; spirit. 
                My children are all well &amp; growing &amp; unfolding to my heart's content. Beatrice &amp; 
                Herbert<ptr target="n0262"/> deeply influenced by your Poems.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Goodbye my dearest Friend.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">A. Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>