<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03723">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Caroline K. Sherman to Walt Whitman, 27 November
                    1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Caroline K. Sherman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="as">Ashlyn Stewart</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03723</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Caroline K. Sherman</author>
                    <title>Caroline K. Sherman to Walt Whitman, 27 November 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-11-27" xml:id="dat1">November 27, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>  
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Sherman, Caroline K." ref="n7019">Caroline K. Sherman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-01-08" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2018-09-27" who="#blh">Second check</change>
            <change when="2018-09-20" who="#as">First Check</change>
            <change when="2016-10-27" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03723.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">225 S. Leavitt St.</name>
                        <name type="place">Chicago. Ill.</name>
                        <date when="1889-11-27">Nov. 27. 1889.</date>
                        <name type="place">Walt Whitman</name>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I enclose a notice of Edward Carpenter,<ptr target="n0141b"/> whom I think you
                    know and like</p>
                <p>I hope your health is such that life is still a joy to you.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Very truly yrs</salute>
                    <signed>Caroline K. Sherman</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03723.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03723.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <head><handShift rend="printed"/>HE'S AN ENGLISH THOREAU<ptr target="n0633"
                    /></head>
                <byline><handShift rend="printed"/>Caroline K. Sherman Writes a Letter on Edward
                    Carpenter.</byline>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Admirers of Edward Carpenter will be interested in the
                    following letter written to T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> H<hi rend="smallcaps">ERALD</hi> by Caroline K.
                    Sherman:</p> 
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Among the many attempts to solve the social and
                    economic problems which at the present time engage the minds of all thoughtful
                    persons that of the Englishman, Edward Carpenter, is one of the most interesting
                    and, perhaps, one of the most reasonable. Mr. Carpenter saw the innumerable
                    difficulties that lie in the way of a satisfactory adjustment of the present
                    order, or disorder, of things, and yet, firmly believing that such an adjustment
                    was not impossible, he set to work, not so much to put forward some new theory
                    of the conduct of life, which others ought to follow, as to realize practically
                    in his own life the conditions essential to this better adjustment. He had
                    graduated at Cambridge with distinguished honor, and although his studies had
                    been mainly in the direction of mathematics and science, ethics and humanitarian
                    interests generally occupied no small share of his attention. He was at this
                    time decidedly conventional&#8212;his fortune, social standing and college
                    education favoring the more conservative views of life. For a time he was
                    engaged as university extension lecturer, giving to the masses in the larger
                    towns the information, in a somewhat diluted form, which was furnished at the
                    universities. During his engagement as extension lecturer he came across the
                    writings of Walt Whitman, which, strange to say, made the turning point of his
                    life. He began to question conventionalities and to weigh and estimate customary
                    forms, and while he did not underrate their possible value, his disposition was
                    to ignore them unless they were the worthy expressions of a genuine spirit. This
                    naturally led him to a closer sympathy with humanity and to the belief that
                    there might be a truer meaning of the word "equality" than is given in legal
                    vocabluaries and a broader and more determined sense of justice than is found in
                    the courts of equity. He saw, too, that there were indications here and there in
                    all classes of a deeper feeling of human solidarity and genuine brotherliness,
                    which might in time, if it became at all general, lead to a better order of
                    society. This insight, however, did not lead Mr. Carpenter into the fatal
                    mistake of supposing that a millennium can be had for the asking, or that a
                    better condition of things can be brought about simply by passing a law
                    commanding it. He knew well that before changing laws it is necessary first to
                    change the aims and ideals of men, and that this cannot be effected by any
                    sudden or violent process. In his own unaffected English he says:</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"A change of society without change of heart amounts
                    to nothing. If it is to be a substantial movement it must mean a changed ideal,
                    a changed conception of daily life. These things first, and a larger share of
                    the pudding afterward."</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The change to which Mr. Carpenter refers is greater
                    simplicity of living, courage of one's own convictions, needful charity of the
                    faults and failings of others, and that spirit of helpfulness to the weak which
                    enables them to help themselves. And he adds:</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"If you have such a new ideal within you it is your
                    clearest duty, as well as your best interest, to act it out in your own life at
                    all apparent cost."</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>As to his own efforts in this direction Mr. Carpenter
                    tells us:</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"I began to wonder if the most sensible and obvious
                    thing for me to do were not to just try and keep at least one little spot of
                    earth clean, actually to try and produce clean, unadulterated food, to encourage
                    honest work, to cultivate decent and healthful conditions for the workers and
                    useful products for the public, and to maintain this state of affairs as long as
                    I was able, taking the chance of the pecuniary results to myself. It would not
                    be much, but it would be something. Just a little glimmer, as it were, in the
                    darkness, but if others did the same the illuminations would increase and after
                    a time we would be able to act our way better."</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>In accordance with this purpose Mr. Carpenter bought a
                    little place of a dozen acres, erected a very simple cottage, and commenced
                    raising vegetables for market, going to market himself with his pony and cart
                    and selling his own produce. In this way he makes his living, benefiting at the
                    same time those who choose to buy of him, since he is bent on being
                    straightforward in all his dealings, and never palms off an inferior article as
                    better than it actually is. In his dress he is simple and unaffected, wearing
                    the flannel shirt and soft hat so becoming to the tourist. He chooses to wear
                    sandals rather than boots, merely because they offer greater freedom of motion.
                    This simple and altogether natural mode of life affords ample opportunity for
                    thought and study, which is almost impossible to be found in<pb
                        xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03723.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> luxurious
                    households, where the care and anxiety in regulating as well as maintaining the
                    establishment absorb most of the comfort and the greater part of the time. In
                    many respects Mr. Carpenter is not unlike our own Thoreau&#8212;in his desire
                    for a life that has some higher significance than meaningless conventionalities,
                    in his purpose to realize practically what appears to him the most rational mode
                    of life, making animal and sensuous wants subordinate to the higher intellectual
                    and spiritual needs. He is like Thoreau, also, in that he is no professed
                    philanthropist or propagandist, but resolutely follows his own bent, believing
                    that to be the best course for himself. If others see a better way, let them
                    pursue that. There is, however, this difference between the two men: Thoreau was
                    disposed to be indifferent, not only to the common courtesies of life, but even
                    to the real interests of humanity. It shocks us that he could write, as he did,
                    in the memorable spring of '61, when the country was on the eve of its great
                    civil war: "I do not so much regret the present condition of things in this
                    country as I do that I ever heard of it. Blessed are they who never read a
                    newspaper, for they shall see Nature, and through her, God." Mr. Carpenter, on
                    the contrary, is keenly alive to anything pertaining to the real well-being of
                    humanity, and watches with interest all honest efforts that tend to its
                    advancement.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The little cottage in which Mr. Carpenter chooses to
                    live is large in its hospitalities. Its unpretentious rooms are open to persons
                    of widely different stations in life, for its owner will tolerate no artificial
                    distinction. Here he has written a series of essays giving his own views of life
                    and what to him makes life most desirable. These essays are widely known and
                    appreciated in England, and have recently appeared in book form under the title
                    of "England's Ideal." He has also written a volume of poems, somewhat
                    Whitmanesque in style, for it is a curious fact that while Walt Whitman is read
                    but little in America, and appreciated still less, he is read quite extensively
                    in England, and the influence of his style as well as his thought is perceptible
                    on many of the younger English writers. Whatever varying opinions there may be
                    as to the peculiar views of men like Thoreau, Tolstoi, Edward Carpenter and
                    others who advocate simpler modes of living as the essential requisite to the
                    higher and more rational forms of happiness, there can be but one opinion as to
                    the value of men like these, whose integrity of purpose and honest endeavor go
                    far toward making even the humblest life desirable, and without which the most
                    affluent circumstances do not make life worth living.</p>
                    <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>CAROLINE K. SHERMAN.</signed>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
