<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05438">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Abraham Paul Leech, 26 August
                    [1840]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="em">Erel Michaelis</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05438</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only. </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Abraham Paul Leech, 26 August [1840]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1840-08-26" xml:id="dat1">August 26, [1840]</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS77909, Box 1</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms005001.mss77909.002</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Walt Whitman Papers, Miscellaneous Manuscript Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="al"><persName key="Leech, Abraham Paul">Abraham Paul
                        Leech</persName></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="unk"><persName key="Unknown">Unknown</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Leech, Abraham Paul" ref="loc.05440_n1">Abraham Paul
                        Leech</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-09-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-08-26" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-06-21" who="#kjb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-30" who="#em">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-07" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-29" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-27" who="#cn">transcribed,encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_gk.01473_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1840-08-26">Wednesday August 26.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dearly beloved&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Moved by the bowels of compassion, and pushed onward by the sharp prickings of
                conscience, I send you another epistolary gem.&#8212;For compassion whispers in mine
                ear that you must by this time have become accustomed to the semi-weekly
                receipt of these invaluable morsels, and therefore to deprive you of the usual gift,
                would be somewhat similar to sending a hungry man to bed without his
                supper.&#8212;Besides, conscience spurs me to a full confession; which generally
                operates on me like a good dose of calomel<ptr target="loc.07126_n8"/> on one who has been stuffing
                immoderately, making a clear stomach and comfortable feelings to take the place of
                overburdened paunch and rumbling intestines.&#8212;Excuse the naturality of my
                metaphor.&#8212;</p>   
            <p>Speaking of "naturality" reminds me of the peculiarities that distinguish the
                inhabitants, young and old, of this well-bred and highly romantick
                village.<ptr target="loc.05440_n2"/>&#8212;For instance, I was entertained the other day at dinner, with a very
                interesting account by the "head of the family" (families of fourteen or fifteen, in
                these parts, have but one <hi rend="underline">head</hi> amongst them) of his
                sufferings from an attack of the gripes; how he had to take ipecachuana,<ptr target="loc.05438_n3"/> and
                antimonial wine;<ptr target="loc.05438_n4"/> the operation of those substances on his stomach; the colour and
                consistency of the fluids and solids ejected from the said stomach; how long <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_gk.01474_large.jpg" type="verso"/> it was before
                epsom salts<ptr target="loc.05438_n5"/> could be persuaded to take pity on his bowels; with many and singular
                concomitant matters, which, you may well imagine, contributed in a high degree to
                the improvement of my appetite.&#8212;I frequently have the felicity of taking my
                meals surrounded by specimens of the rising generation&#8212;I mean little young
                ones getting out of bed; and as "to the pure all things are pure,"<ptr target="loc.05438_n6"/> the scene of
                course is in a high degree edifying to my taste and comfort.&#8212;</p> 
            <p>We have had delightful weather out here for the past few days.&#8212;The sun at this
                moment is shining clear, the cool breeze is blowing, the branches of the trees
                undulate, and all seems peace and joy but the mind&#8212;the <hi rend="underline"
                    >mind</hi>, that strange unfathomable essence, which is, after all, the main
                spring of our happiness here.&#8212;My period of purgation is almost up in these
                diggins.&#8212;Thank the pitying fates! in two weeks more I shall wind up my
                affairs, and with tears in my eyes bid a sorrowful adieu to these hallowed
                precincts.&#8212;Shady walks, venerable old school-house, dismantled farms,
                innocent young ideas&#8212;all&#8212;all&#8212;will I look upon for the last
                time.&#8212;But I must stop&#8212;I cannot carry out the affecting thought any
                farther.&#8212;My heart swells, and my melting soul almost expires with the
                agonising idea.&#8212;Let me hold out a little longer, O, ye powers!</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_gk.01475_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>How are politicks getting along down your way?&#8212;Is hard cider<ptr target="loc.05441_n3"/> in the ascendant;
                or does democracy erect itself on its tip-toes and swing its old straw hat
                with a hurrah for "Little Matty?"<ptr target="loc.05438_n1"/> Down in these parts the people understand about as
                much of political economy as they do of the Choctaw language; I never met with such
                complete unqualified, infernal jackasses, in all my life.&#8212;Luckily for my
                self-complacency they are mostly whigs.&#8212;If they were on my side of the
                wall, I should forswear loco-focoism,<ptr target="loc.05438_n2"/> and turn traitor in five minutes. We had a
                swinging meeting at the Court house, last Saturday.&#8212;I tell you what, our
                speakers went as far ahead of "the fat gentleman in striped trousers," as a
                Baltimore clipper does beyond a North River dung boat.&#8212;There was no
                'kimparysun.'</p>
            <p>Can't you look around Jamaica and find out whether they dont want a teacher
                somewhere, for a quarter?&#8212;I shall probably drop down there in the course of a
                week or two, and stay a day.&#8212;See to it, and oblige me.&#8212;I hope that holy
                angels will have you in keeping, and that the fragrance of plenty and the musick of
                a pleasant heart, will never be foreign to you.&#8212;Sweet blossoms bloom beneath
                your eyes, and the songs of birds gladden your hearing!&#8212;</p> 
            <closer>
                <salute>Farewell,&#8212;</salute>
                <signed>Walter Whitman</signed>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_tb.00302.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="center">Abraham P. Leech | Jamaica, L.I.<ptr target="loc.05437_n4"/></note>
            </closer>
            <note type="editorial" place="right" resp="#al">W Whitman | Aug 26 1840</note>
        </body>
    </text>   
</TEI>  
