<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03205">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Sidney H. Morse to Walt Whitman, 11 July 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Sidney H. Morse</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="rf">Ryan Furlong</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03205</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2020 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Sidney H. Morse</author>
                    <title>Sidney H. Morse to Walt Whitman, 11 July 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-07-11" xml:id="dat1">July 11, 1890</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 13, Reel 8</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00284</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Morse, Sidney H." ref="duk.00863_n3">Sidney H. Morse</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-04-01" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2019-07-25" who="#bbb">Second check, added notes</change>
            <change when="2019-07-22" who="#rf">First Check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-07-19" who="#if">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03205.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">374 E. Division St. Chicago&#8212;</name>
                    <date when="1890-07-11">July 11, 1890.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                I have lately discovered in Englewood a nest of your friends, &#38; among them to particularly mention are Dr Champlin &#38; wife.<ptr target="loc.03205_n4"/> The Dr is a genuine sort of an oddity with brains and generous human impulses. 
                He is proud of an oration he gave before the County Normal School in 
                which he has a <choice><sic>refference</sic><corr>reference</corr></choice> to you. At my request he sends the paragraph on the back of his own photo. His wife has for years been an invalid &#38; 
                they are not blest with children. He has a certain glumness of facial expression and and
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03205.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                abruptness of speech, and a dont-care-a-bit air about him, which deceives some 
                of his neighbors, &#38; they put him down as "pessimistic." (By the way, that is a word so common just now with aspiring people 
                here. Wheresoever I go some one will be sure to say&#8212;"Yes, but dont you 
                think he (or she) takes a pessimistic view of life?" And I feel so like retorting bluntly &#38; vehemently,&#8212;"Damn it, no! 
                Why in hell should he?" The smack of <choice><sic>incincere</sic><corr>insincere</corr></choice>, pretentious "culture" 
                is so apparent and exasperating.) Champlin simply despised so much of the gibberish that he is forced to 
                encounter, and hasn't the grace to conceal his <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#if">growl</unclear>. 
            </p>
            <p> 
                But poor Mrs. C. is mild-mannered and considerate while she is equally fun &#38; intelligent. She thinks very much of your poems
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03205.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                and has been ever since she heard that I had seen you eager to know all I could tell her. I gave her the little plaque I made of you,<ptr target="loc.03205_n6"/> which 
                hangs conspicuously in the little study&#8212;What do you think, (or <hi rend="underline">whom</hi>, rather) she wants me to make as 
                companion? Why, old Socrates!<ptr target="loc.03205_n5"/> I suppose I must do it. She is utterly helpless save 
                a slight use of her hands, and sits all day in a low wheeled-chair; Suffers much &#38; has tears of great frustration. But when I go over to 
                talk of you, or Emerson,<ptr target="n1044"/> Carlyle<ptr target="n0139"/> or Cleveland,<ptr target="n4271"/> whom she has a liking for, 
                she puts her ailings aside. My drawings and my clay greatly interest her and a large company of boys &#38; girls who flock to her porch 
                ("stoop" I called it to the wonderment of the children). The Dr is anxious that I should teach modeling at the Normal School <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#smb">this</unclear>
                next year, but all I know can be put in so small a space I fear it would not stretch through a whole season.  
            </p>  
            <p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03205.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                It would greatly interest her &#38; soften her affliction if she had a line of yours written with your swan's pen. When years ago 
                she admired your "Leaves of Grass" the wrapper had something written on it which she preserves.</p>
            <p>
                I am glad to hear how comfortable you keep, despite the beseiged body, and hope you may count yet many more birth days on the already good list.
            </p>
            <p>
                As for myself I am hopeful amid tribulations of pocket that seem to pursue me ever. 
                I think it would be a good psychological study for some one to regard me as I am for a week or two and then suddenly endow me with a warm 
                million. In the various drudgeries I have performed in past years (for 
                the sake of somewhat worthwhile if I never get it) I am sure I have earned it all. 
                I'd not say "Beggar that I am, I thank you," but, "Ah, ha! God sends my due&#8212;or approximates it. My busts sell, but my 
                landlord stands at the door. 
            </p>  
            <p>
                My<ptr target="loc.03205_n2"/> lectures succeed, but the money they bring takes me back home, 
                &#38; then comes a dying whisper&#8212;"nothing left&#8212;exhausted."
            </p>
            <p>
                Kind<ptr target="loc.03205_n3"/> regards to Mrs. D.<ptr target="n6113"/> In the Fall or Winter I mean to come to Camden.
            </p>
            <closer> 
                <salute>Sincerely</salute>
                <signed>S. H. Morse</signed>
            </closer>
        </body> 
    </text> 
</TEI>


