<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03312">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 25 September 1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03312</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 25 September 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-09-25" xml:id="dat1">September 25, 1885</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt
                    Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-07-28" who="#smb">final check, added notes, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-06-11" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2014-11-20" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-11-17" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03312.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="top">Third letter from Ernest Rhys&#8212;the
                little English selection from L. of G. is out since, &amp; the whole edition
                (10.000) sold.</note>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="left">return no hurry</note>
            <!-- written in red ink -->
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">59 Cheyne Walk</name>
                    <name type="place">Chelsea,</name>
                    <name type="place">London, S. W.</name>
                    <date when="1885-09-25">25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September 1885</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> Twice I have written to you before,&#8212;and whether my letters have ever reached
                you, or whether you have had other nobler &amp; more important thing to prevent your
                attending to mere secondary matters, or&#8212;whatever the reason may be&#8212;(and
                indeed I know how many reasons, remembering too that you have been ill this summer,
                there are for it). I have waited very <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.03312.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> anxiously for a reply so far in
                vain. You know this anxiety,&#8212;of a young man, in the first hard fight of life
                &amp; poetry in a great careless town, rebuffed over &amp; over, coming almost every
                day&#8212;to all appearance otherwise&#8212;to his last penny. Not that I wish to
                pretend to any great misery&#8212;for perhaps there never was a happier life than
                mine, in most ways&#8212;; but disclosing my present standpoint, at odds with the
                fortunate ordinary aspects, you may be more ready to give me your helping hand of
                comradeship &amp; cheer. </p>
            <p> The exact nature of the help you can give is this,&#8212;(as perhaps I ought to
                assume you know already, unless my former letters have not reached you)&#8212;the <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03312.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> giving
                permission for a new &amp; cheap edition of <hi rend="underline">Leaves of
                    Grass</hi> in England. The conditions of the Series of poets in which it is
                proposed to include your name are not altogether satisfactory may be; certain
                details are rather out of keeping with the tremendous scheme &amp; infinite scope of
                the Leaves of Grass. But at the same time there are advantages in such an
                association which can not be overlooked, as for instance the immediately extended
                audience which is obtained by the appearance in a popular series of this sort. The
                more incompatible features of the edition, &#8212;such as red-line borders,
                prettified cover &amp; so on, we must insist on having done away with in the case
                of the Leaves of Grass volume; and indeed I think if you strongly expressed your
                disapproval of the general conditions of the series, at the same <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03312.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> time not
                objecting to the most urgent part of the request&#8212;for a cheap edition simply
                that is&#8212;I think the publishers would be persuaded to issue the volume
                specially &amp; by itself, as a small square volume with plain cover &amp; simply
                the emblem of a tuft of grass, and this would be a size &amp; shape which could be
                easily carried about anywhere in the pocket. (My own copy of <hi rend="underline"
                    >Leaves of Grass</hi> [Philadelphia, 1883 <choice>
                    <abbr>edit'n</abbr>
                    <expan>edition</expan>
                </choice>] I have taken to pieces &amp; carry the different parts as I may want them
                about in a little parchment wallet; for the whole book is too big to be conveniently
                pocketed.) The publishers have asked me to forward you as a proof of their
                honourable intention ten guineas, and I am sure if the edition proved successful
                they would readily repeat <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03312.005_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> the remittance. Last week I saw William Rossetti,<ptr target="n0522"/> &amp; he advised
                me to send the amount through the Post Office, which I will do accordingly early1
                next week. </p>
            <p> William Rossetti said he thought the proposed <choice>
                    <abbr>edit<hi rend="superscript">n</hi></abbr>
                    <expan>edition</expan>
                </choice> very desirable, and was altogether so kind that I felt a good deal cheered
                (though we only had a moment or two's talk) &amp; determined to consult him again as
                the arrangements progressed. Last Sunday as a further step I lectured on <hi
                    rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi>, as you will see by the bill enclosed, in
                Islington, north London, &amp; thanks to my subject, the adventure was successful,
                &amp; I have been asked to redeliver the lecture in two other places. We had been
                threatened beforehand with a fierce opposition, but to our surprise it utterly
                collapsed after the lecture, &amp; one lady present <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc.03312.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> spoke with enthusiasm on the right
                side. For my own part I can't tell you with what elation &amp; pride I recited some
                or the noblest passages in Leaves of Grass&#8212;firing them off as it were into the
                enemy's camp like the rifles Ruskin<ptr target="n3013"/> calls them. </p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="underline">29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Sept:</hi>&#8212;This is my
                chief claim to be your interpreter at all in England then&#8212;that I stand with
                the band of young men who have the future in their hands, young men of the people,
                not academics; not mere University students, but a healthy, determined, hearty band
                of comrades, seeking amid all their errors &amp; foolishnesses to help the average,
                everyday men about them. You could have a thousand writers of more culture &amp;
                literary student faculty than mine, but none I think with more love &amp; enthusiasm
                &amp; heat of youth. So far my accomplishments in life &amp; song <pb
                    xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03312.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> has not been
                much, having struggled through endless phases of literary tradition, being too
                occupied with the mining of coal &amp; the living of a free open-air country life in
                the North. But give me your word, and I will try not to be unworthy of it. </p>
            <p> There is a temptation to say more about myself in the past &amp; present, but
                perhaps it's better not to, especially as before long I may be able to send you a
                book,&#8212;"The Book of Browney Valley," (Browney being the name of the little
                river by which I lived for some years,) which will tell what is to be told at
                length. Now, on the banks of the Thames, whose current, &amp; craft of all
                kinds&#8212;sailing, steaming, rowing&#8212;, are fresh every morning to this attic
                window. I gather with tremendous zest materials for a larger volume,&#8212;The Book
                of Thames Valley, which will owe to <hi rend="underline">Leave of Grass</hi> more
                than I can well say. </p>  
  
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03312.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p> Ah, I often wonder what your days are like in Camden,&#8212;how the sun shines, how
                the winds visit you,&#8212;wonder too whether you would mind if one day yet another
                young messenger came with some English leaves of grass in his hand for a token to
                your door. Only before that there's a great deal I must do, for tonight remembering
                that admonitant voice in <hi rend="underline">Calamus</hi><ptr target="n4128"/>. I seem a very poor &amp;
                weak &amp; inefficient follower. But <q>"Therefore release me &amp; depart on your
                    way,"</q> as ominously runs the last line I will not! </p>
            <p> I shall wait very eagerly for some word from you; with great love (in which William
                Rossetti asked to be included) from this London nook of the world, </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Faithfully</salute>
                <signed>Ernest Rhys</signed>
            </closer>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="left">P O order for 10 LGs enclosed</note>
            <!-- written in blue pencil -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
