<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01884">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">William Michael Rossetti to Walt Whitman,
    14 April [1875]</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>William Michael Rossetti</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01884</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc><bibl>
    <author>William Michael Rossetti</author>
    <title>William Michael Rossetti to Walt Whitman, 14 April [1875]</title>
    <date cert="medium" when="1875-04-14" xml:id="dat1">April 14, 1875</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Rossetti, William Michael" ref="n0522">William Michael Rossetti</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2013-01-31" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-18" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-10-06" who="#kk">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-10-05" who="#cb">transcribed; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01884.001.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <opener>
                <address><addrLine>56 Euston Sq.</addrLine><addrLine>London, N.W.</addrLine></address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1875-04-14">14 April</date>.</dateline>
                <salute>Dear Mr. Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p> I am always proud to receive any scrap of your handwriting, &amp; pleased as well: <choice>
                    <sic>tho'</sic>
                    <corr>though</corr>
                </choice> the pleasure was a somewhat melancholy one yesterday, owing to the far
                from favourable account <choice>
                    <sic>wh.</sic>
                    <corr>which</corr>
                </choice> you give of yourself. It seems a singularly perverse arrangement of nature
                (but <hi rend="underline">you</hi> are not the man to complain of her) that you,
                with your exceptionally vigorous mould, &amp; still hardly beginning to be an 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01884.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                elderly man, <choice>
                    <sic>sh.d</sic>
                    <corr>should</corr>
                </choice> be subject to so lingering as well as severe an attack. Believe that you
                have in this country some most sincere sympathizers, to whom news of your complete
                recovery <choice>
                    <sic>wd</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> be among the very best news that they <choice>
                    <sic>cd</sic>
                    <corr>could</corr>
                </choice>hear.</p>
            <p>I look forward with great interest to your proposed volume of prose &amp; verse. The
                last thing I saw of yours was that temperate &amp; discriminating but yet hearty (or
                it <choice>
                    <sic>wd</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> not be yours) estimate of Burns. I put something about it into a literary
                weekly review I write in, The Academy. This was
                copied
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01884.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                into some (I dare say
                numerous) English papers; and one Editor wrote asking what was the American paper in <choice>
                    <sic>wh.</sic>
                    <corr>which</corr>
                </choice> your remarks had been printed, as he wished to look them up, &amp; reprint
                them in full&#8212;<choice>
                    <sic>wh.</sic>
                    <corr>which</corr>
                </choice>has probably been done <choice>
                    <orig>ere</orig>
                    <reg>here</reg>
                </choice> now. I shall now put into the Academy the substance of your last note,
                &amp; the article in the New Republic. Symonds therein mentioned (at least I suppose
                it is the <hi rend="underline">same</hi> Symonds) entered years ago into a
                correspondence with me, on the sole basis of his great admiration of your poems.
                Clifford is regarded as a shining light among our younger
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01884.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                men of science, very bold in his tone of thought.</p>
            <p>I forget what the date may have been when I last wrote to you: more shame to me
                perhaps, as showing that it must at any rate have been a long while ago. Perhaps it
                may even have been before May 1873. In that
                month I went to Italy on a short trip with some friends, one of them being the
                daughter, whom I had known from childhood, of one of my oldest intimates Ford Madox
                Brown (a distinguished historical painter&#8212;she herself being also a painter of
                no small attainment). Before we came back from 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01884.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                the trip, we had resolved that we had
                better part no more, &amp; in March 1874 we married. My wife is greatly interested
                in you &amp; what concerns you, and bids me not fail to say that she "admires you as
                much as I do". I remember that her sister, then perhaps barely 17 years of age,
                seemed more fascinated with your poems, when my selection of them came out towards
                1868, than with any other poetical work she had ever seen. She also is an able
                painter&#8212;now married to Dr. Hueffer<!-- Franz Hueffer -->, a German learned
                in musical &amp; other matters, who has of late contributed some musical articles to
                the N.Y. Tribune. There was also a brother, Oliver Madox Brown, who
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01884.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                showed a singular extent of genius, both as painter &amp; as writer: a romance of his, Gabriel Denver, was published in 1873, &amp; his other remaining writings will probably soon be issued. Unfortunately he died in Nov. last of pyaemia, aged less than 20. Many a time have I heard him refer to your writings in an enthusiastic spirit.</p>
            <p> Last month I for the first time in my life faced a public audience (in Birmingham)
                to deliver a lecture&#8212;on Shelley: &amp; I found myself less unfitted for the
                task than I had apprehended. It was a <hi rend="underline">written</hi> lecture.
                There must be a great 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01884.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                satisfaction in addressing a large audience, for one who can speak wholly or almost
                extempore, &amp; who feels the magnetic personal thrill between his hearers &amp;
                himself. You, I think, have on various occasions experienced this pleasure.</p>
            <p> This afternoon I shall be seeing one of the interesting old men surviving from a
                past generation&#8212;Trelawny<!-- Edward John -->, the friend of Shelley<!-- Percy, I assume? --> &amp;
                Byron. He has always been a wonderfully strong man, in all senses of the word: &amp;
                now, well past so, he wears no under-clothing &amp; no great coat, bathes constantly
                in cold water &amp; in the sea, prefers to dispense with stockings as he sits at
                home 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01884.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
                slippered&#8212;&amp;c. He has been in
                all parts of the world &#8212; N. &amp; S. America included: always markedly
                temperate&#8212;even in his youth, when the contrary habit was universally
                prevalent here.</p>
            <p> I hope I have not wearied you with this talk. At all events believe me to be always </p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Yours with affection,</salute>
                <signed>W. M. Rossetti</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript><p>Have you wholly relinquished the idea of visiting Europe?</p></postscript>
        </body> 
        
     <!--   <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.01884.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <address><addrLine>Walt Whitman</addrLine><addrLine>Camden</addrLine><addrLine>New Jersey</addrLine><addrLine>U.S.A.</addrLine></address>
        Notes in Whitman's hand:
        <note type="editorial" place="marginleft">W. M. Rossetti</note>
        <note type="editorial" place="marginleft">April 14, '75</note>-->  
        
    </text>
</TEI>