<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05155">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 5 September
                    1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Addington Symonds</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt> 
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor> Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder> National Historical Publications and Records Commission </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05155</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p> Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only. </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>John Addington Symonds</author>
                    <title>John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 5 September 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-09-05" xml:id="dat1">September 05, 1890</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 17, Reel 10&#8211;11</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc"> The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Symonds, John Addington" ref="n0615">John Addington
                        Symonds</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-14" who="#smb">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2019-12-06" who="#blh">Second check</change>
            <change when="2019-06-13" who="#if">First check</change>
            <change when="2018-06-04" who="#bjo">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00353.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener> 
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">
                        <handShift rend="printed"/> AM HOF,<lb/> DAVOS PLATZ,<lb/>SWITZERLAND.<lb/>
                    </name>
                    <date when="1890-09-05" rend="right">
                        <handShift rend="manuscript"/> Sept: 5. 1890 </date>
                </dateline> 
                <salute>My dear Master</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I am sincerely obliged to you for your letter of August 19.<ptr
                    target="loc.05155_n1"/> It is a great relief to me to know so clearly &#38;
                precisely what you feel about the question I raised. Your phrases "gratuitous &#38;
                quite at the time undreamed &#38; unrecked possibility of morbid
                inferences&#8212;which are disavowed by me &#38; seem damnable," set the matter as
                straight as can be, base this doctrine of Calamus upon a foundation of granite.<ptr
                    target="loc.05155_n2"/></p>
            <p> I am not surprised; for this indeed is what I understood to be your meaning, since I
                have studied Leaves of Grass in the right way&#8212;interpreting each part by
                reference to the whole &#38; in the spirit of the whole. The result of this study
                was that the "adhesiveness" of comradeship had no interblending with the
                "amativemess" of sexual love.</p>
            <p> Yet you must not think that the "morbid inferences," which to you "seem damnable,"
                are quite "gratuitous" or outside of the range of possibility. Frankly speaking, the
                emotional language of Calamus is such as hitherto has not been used in the modern
                world about the relation between friends. For a student of ancient literature it
                presents a singular analogue to the early Greek<pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_vm.00354.jpg" type="verso"/> enthusiasm of comradeship in
                arms&#8212;as that appeared among the Dorian tribes, &#38; made a chivalry for
                prehistoric Hellas. And you know what singluar anomalies were connected with this
                lofty sentiment in the historic period of Greek development.</p>
            <p> Again, you cannot be ignorant that a certain percentage (small but appreciable) of
                male beings are always born into the world, whose sexual instincts are what the
                Germans call "inverted". During the last 25 years much attention, in France,
                Germany, Austria &#38; Italy, has been directed to the psychology &#38; pathology of
                these abnormal persons. In 1889 the Penal Code of Italy was altered by the erasion
                of their eccentricities from the list of crimes.</p>
            <p> Looking then to the lessons of the past in ancient Greece, where a heroic chivalry
                of comradeship grew intertwined with moral abominations (I speak as a modern man),
                &#38; also to the Contemporary problem offered by the class of persons I have
                mentioned&#8212;who will certainly have somehow to be dealt with in the light of
                science, since the eyes of science have been<pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc_vm.00355.jpg" type="recto"/> drawn towards them: looking, I say, to
                both these things, it became of the utmost importance to know for certain what you
                thought about those "morbid inferences". For you have announced clearly that a great
                spiritual factor lies latent in Comradeship, ready to leap forth &#38; to take a
                prominent part in the energy of the human race. It is, I repeat, essential that the
                interpreters of your prophecy should be able to speak authoritatively &#38;
                decisively about their Master's <hi rend="underline">Stimmung</hi>, his radical
                instinct with regard to the emotional &#38; moral quality of the comradeship he
                announces.</p>
            <p> I am sorry to have annoyed you with this discussion. But you will see, I hope now,
                that it was not wholly unnecessary or unprofitable.</p>
            <p> With the explanation you have placed in my hands, in which you give me liberty to
                use, I can speak with no uncertain voice, &#38; with no dread lest the enemy should
                blaspheme.</p>
            <p> The conclusion reached is, to my mind, in every way satisfactory. I am so profoundly
                convinced that you are right in all you say about the great good which is to be
                expected from Comradeship as you conceive it, &#38; as alone it can be a salutary<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00356.jpg" type="verso"/> human bond, that the
                power of repudiating those "morbid inferences" authoritatively&#8212;should they
                ever be made seriously or uttered openly, either by your detractors or by the
                partizans of some vicious crankiness&#8212;sets me quite at ease as to my own
                course.</p>
            <p> I will tell my bookseller in London to send you a copy of the "Contemporary" in
                which there is an essay by me on the "Dantesque &#38; Platonic Ideals of Love." You
                will see something there about the Dorian Chivalry of Comradeship to w<hi
                    rend="underline">h</hi>. I have alluded in this letter. It seems to me, I
                confess, still doubtful whether (human nature being what it is) we can expect wholly
                to eliminate some sensual alloy from any emotions which are raised to a very high
                pitch of passionate intensity. But the moralizing of the emotions must be left to
                social feeling &#38; opinion in general, &#38; ultimately to the individual
                conscience.</p>
            <p> I am greatly interested in your "Rejoinder"<ptr target="loc.05155_n3"/> (w<hi rend="underline">h</hi>. by the
                way has been reprinted in the PMG). Anything you say about the inception &#38;
                performance of your great life-work has value.&#8212;I have been ill; six days in
                bed with high fever, a lung-inflammation serious to me; only just up again for a few
                hours.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Ever yours with deep gratitude &#38; true affection.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">John Addington Symonds.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
