<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.04201">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 3 August
                    1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Addington Symonds</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04201</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>John Addington Symonds</author>
                    <title>John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 3 August 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-08-03" xml:id="dat1">August 3, 1890</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 17, Reel 10&#8211;11</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00380</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Symonds, John Addington" ref="n0615">John Addington
                        Symonds</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-21" who="#smb">updated notes</change>
            <change when="2023-07-15" who="#aja">checked, corrected, added DOI</change>
            <change when="2019-06-24" who="#aa">second check</change>
            <change when="2019-06-12" who="#if">First check</change>
            <change when="2018-08-07" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">  
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00347_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>Am Hof,</name>
                    <name type="place">Davos Platz,</name>
                    <name type="place">Switzerland</name>
                    <date when="1890-08-03"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>August 3 1890</date>
                </dateline>    
                <salute>My dear Master</salute>
            </opener>   

            <p>I received your card of July 20<ptr target="n5002c"/> in due course two days ago. It makes me feel how very
                remiss I have been in not acknowledging the volume of your Complete Works,<ptr
                    target="n4195"/> which I am already in the habit of calling to myself "Whitman's
                Bible," &#38; which remains the colossal monument of your arduous
                life-labours&#8212;monumentum aere perennius, as Horace says.<ptr
                    target="loc.04201_n1"/></p> 

            <p>Reading this great book, I found on p: 291 in "Collect"<ptr target="n4121"/> the
                passage I quoted from the essay known to me under its old title of "Poetry of the
                Future." But it was then too late to alter the reference in my own essay on
                "Democratic Art" w. had been printed a considerable time before it was published.<ptr target="loc.04201_n10"/>
                I hope to have a second edition of my "Essays Speculative &#38; Suggestive" (for only
                750 copies were printed); &#38; if I do so, I shall remodel the whole drift of that
                article.</p>

            <p>Now I must thank you for the generous &#38; to <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_vm.00348_large.jpg" type="verso"/> me most highly acceptable, by me most
                reverently guarded, gift of your portraits&#8212;a sheaf of portraits unique in
                their significance &#38; interest.<ptr target="loc.04201_n5"/> Many friends have
                shared with me the pleasure &#38; profit of studying &#38; comparing them. If you
                have no objection to the idea, I should like to have some of the photographs of
                middle &#38; later life reproduced by a permanent process, which has recently been
                invented by a very able chemist at Munich: Obernetter.<ptr target="loc.04201_n2"/> I
                will send you a specimen of his skill, the reproduction of one of Rembrandt's
                etchings,<ptr target="loc.01118_n1"/> which will bear the closest comparison with the original.</p>

            <p>I want next to ask you a question about a very important portion of your teaching,
                which has puzzled a great many of your disciples &#38; admirers. To tell the truth,
                I have always felt unable to deal, as I wish to do, comprehensively with your
                philosophy of life, because I do not even yet understand <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc_vm.00349_large.jpg" type="recto"/> the whole drift 
                of "Calamus."<ptr target="loc.04201_n11"/> If you have read Mr. Havelock 
                Ellis' "New Spirit,"<ptr target="loc.04201_n3"/> w. contains a study of your work in thought &#38;
                speculation, you may have noticed on p: 108 that he expresses some perplexity about
                the doctrine of "manly love", &#38; again on p: 121 he uses this phrase "the
                intimate &#38; physical love of comrades &#38; lovers".</p>

            <p>This reference to Havelock Ellis helps me to explain what it is I want to ask you. In
                your conception of comradeship, do you contemplate the possible intrusion of those
                semi-sexual emotions &#38; actions which no doubt do occur between men? I do not
                ask, whether you approve of them, or regard them as a necessary part of the
                relation? But I should much like to know whether <hi rend="underline">you are
                    prepared to leave them to the inclinations &#38; the conscience of the
                    individuals concerned?</hi><ptr target="loc.04201_n7"/></p>

            <p>For my own part, after mature deliberation, I hold that the present laws of France
                &#38; Italy are right upon this topic of morality. They place the personal relations
                of adults of both sexes upon the same foundation: that is to say, <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00350_large.jpg" type="verso"/> they protect minors,
                punish violence, &#38; guard against outrages of public decency. Within these
                limitations, they leave individuals to do what they think fit. But, as you know,
                these principles are in open contradiction with the principles of English (and I
                believe American) legislation.</p>

            <p>It has not infrequently occurred to me among my English friends to hear your
                "Calamus" objected to, as praising &#38; propagating a passionate affection between
                men, which (in the language of the objectors) has "a very dangerous side," &#38;
                might "bring people into criminality."</p>

            <p>Now: it is of the utmost importance to me as your disciple, &#38; as one who wants
                sooner or later to diffuse a further knowledge of your life-philosophy by criticism;
                it is most important to me to know what you really think about all this.</p>

            <p>I agree with the objectors I have mentioned that, human nature being what it is,
                &#38; some men having a strong natural bias toward <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc_vm.00351_large.jpg" type="recto"/> persons of their own sex, the enthusiasm
                of "Calamus" is calculated to encourage ardent &#38; <hi rend="underline"
                    >physical</hi> intimacies.</p>

            <p>But I do not agree with them in thinking that such a result would be absolutely
                prejudicial to social interests, which I am certain that you are right in expecting
                a new Chivalry (if I may so speak) from one of the main &#38; hitherto imperfectly
                developed factors of the human emotional nature. This, I take it, is the spiritual
                outcome of your doctrine in Calamus.</p>

            <p>And, as I have said, I prefer the line adopted by French &#38; Italian legislature to
                that of the English penal code.</p>

            <p>Finally, what I earnestly desire to know is whether you are content to leave the
                ethical problems regarding the private behaviour of comrades toward each other, to
                the persons' own sense of what is right &#38; fit&#8212;or whether, on the other
                hand, you have never contemplated while uttering the Gospel of Comradeship, the
                possibility of any such delicate difficulties occurring.</p>

            <p>Will you enlighten me on this? If I am not allowed to hear from yourself or from some
                one who will communicate your views, I fear I shall never be <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc_vm.00352_large.jpg" type="verso"/> able to utter what I want to tell the
                world about your teaching, with the confidence &#38; the thorough sense of not
                misinterpreting you in one way or the other which are inseparable from truly
                sympathetic &#38; powerful exposition.</p> 

            <p>The precise drift of "Whoever you are"&#8212;what the one
                indispensible thing is&#8212;I cannot get at; &#38; I am not sure what the drift of
                "Earth my likeness" is.&#8212;Ah, if I could only once
                have spoken to you, you would certainly have let me know.&#8212;Lieber Mann,
                geehrter Meister, das fehlt mir doch!<ptr target="loc.04201_n4"/>&#8212;</p>

            <p>It is perhaps strange that a man within 2 months of completing his 50th year should
                care at all about this ethical bearing of Calamus. Of course I do not care much
                about it, except that ignorance on the subject prevents me from forming a complete
                view of your life-philosophy.</p>    


            <closer>
                <salute>Believe me truly gratefully &#38; affectionately yours</salute>
                <signed>John Addington Symonds</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
