<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04404">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">James William Wallace and John Johnston to Walt
                    Whitman, 18 May 1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04404</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>James William Wallace</author>
                    <title>James William Wallace and John Johnston to Walt Whitman, 18 May
                        1887</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1887-05-18" xml:id="dat1">May 18, 1887</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 18, Reel 11 or Box 11, Reel 7</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Wallace, James William" ref="n6121">James William Wallace</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Johnston, John">John Johnston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-08" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-02-18" who="#cb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-12-20" who="#ss">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-11-09" who="#aa">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.01021_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">54 Manchester Road Bolton<ptr target="loc.04404_n1"/></name>
                    <name type="place">111 Engle St Bolton</name>
                    <date when="1887-05-18">May 18th/87.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>In no less familiar or colder terms can we bring ourselves to address you, the most
                loved of friends, though such a salutation from strangers to anyone but yourself
                would seem an impertinence</p>
            <p>We, two friends chiefly united by our common love of you, wish to congratulate you on
                your birthday and express to you personally our very best wishes and love. To you we
                owe not only affection but endless gratitude and reverence. One of us, a doctor,
                owes to you entirely his spiritual enfranchisement &#38; deliverance from
                soul-benumbing scepticism, into which, not without pain, he had gradually fallen.
                Your books are his constant companions, his spiritual nourishment, his continual
                study and delight. And not least of his debts to you is "the glory" you have shown
                him, "in his daily walk &#38; trade" which you have ennobled and made beautiful for
                him.</p>
            <p>The writer in many obstructions &#38; difficulties is strengthened and comforted by
                your example and words. In past heavy bereavement (of a mother to whom he has often
                mentally applied the words you use of yours) <hi rend="underline">your</hi> words
                have best tallied his deepest experience and hopes. For years he has been, and is, a
                lover and grateful student of Carlyle<ptr target="n0139"/> and, in turn, of
                    Ruskin.<ptr target="n3013"/> He has also, on the <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_vm.01022_large.jpg" type="verso"/> other hand been long familiar with
                    Emerson<ptr target="n0218"/> and reveres his memory. But <hi rend="underline"
                    >your</hi> teaching, far more than Emerson's, has appealed to him as the fitting
                offset to and complement of theirs, and as a veritable "Gospel" bringing "glad
                tidings of great joy."</p>
            <p>We both study your writings as much as possible, and glean every help that critiques
                and notices can give. We endeavor to assimilate them in our lives and try to
                introduce them to others. We occasionally call friends together in your name to
                spend "a Whitman evening", to read your books and talk about them. We shall not fail
                to do so on the 31st, and shall rejoice to believe that you know it and that there
                is a <hi rend="underline">real</hi> communion between us, though far sundered</p>
            <p>We are anxious to have the pleasure of giving you some little tangible token of our
                love. We do not know what else to send you so venture to ask you to accept a money
                present of &#163;10. It will be a lifelong pleasure to us to feel that we have thus been
                in personal communication with you and that something you hold has been supplied by
                    <hi rend="underline">us</hi>.</p>
            <p>Hoping you will do us this favour, and wishing you long continued health and
                strength. We are,</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours gratefully and affectionately</salute>
                <signed>John Johnston M.D.</signed>
                <signed>J. W. Wallace.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.01039_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.01040_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
