<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01086">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Carolan O'Brien Bryant to Walt Whitman, 10 June
                    1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Carolan O'Brien Bryant</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01086</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive June be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Carolan O'Brien Bryant</author>
                    <title>Carolan O'Brien Bryant to Walt Whitman, 10 June 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-06-10" xml:id="dat1">June 10, 1885</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Brien Bryant, Carolan" ref="loc.01086_n7">Carolan O'Brien
                        Bryant</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-03-14" who="#ss">checked, encoded, and annotated</change>
            <change when="2015-03-14" who="#aa">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01086.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">1617 Chestnut St</name>
                    <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>
                    <date when="1885-06-10">June 10th 85</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Walt Whitman</salute>
                <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have just picked out of my "pocket Coleridge" your letter of a year ago, published
                in the papers and which I cut out when I was living in New York.<ptr
                    target="loc.01086_n1"/> I looked it up the other day to see if your birthday was
                the 30th of May, for I would please myself with the idea that when the ephemera of
                the ruthless old camp life was gone out of present view&#8212;when we are no longer
                "crowd the mournery" of this generation, and they are all "gone and done joined"
                with their dead&#8212;I should be glad to realize the substitution for the
                forgotten, the name of that one which alone would deserve the national festival
                &#38; sacrifice&#8212;the immemorial feast of the bards&#8212;the May Morris<ptr
                    target="loc.01086_n2"/>&#8212;Baal-Tinne<ptr target="loc.01086_n3"/> as our
                commemoration of the Poet of the Leaves of Grass. </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01086.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>Today, on receiving a request from the West for a copy of your poems, I looked up the
                letter to get your address. It seems to me also that the manner of the request might
                please you, so I sent a sheet from the letter. It indicates the edition you "intend
                to <hi rend="underline">stand by</hi>&#8212;with some indication also that there are
                those who will <hi rend="underline">stand</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">with</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">you</hi>, in the most sanctified recesses of our best
                households&#8212;without "expurgation." </p>
            <p>I have my self the same thin green covered quarto,<ptr target="loc.01086_n4"/> your
                own edition&#8212;which you gave me personally not long after its first appearance.
                I came to meet you by request of a very manly friend, Sinclair Toussey,<ptr
                    target="loc.01086_n5"/> at his news stand (the great American News Co of today)
                then behind the Herald office in Nassau street, where my old master Bennett<ptr
                    target="loc.01086_n6"/> founded the independent press on the head of an empty
                barrel. I met you with momentary embarrassment and incredulity&#8212;but a few
                moments </p>
            <gap reason="cut off"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01086.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>My sister learnt to read and understand you about as soon as I did and it has been a
                sort of propaganda with both of us to give away all the copies of your books we
                could get, to those whom we thought would appreciate their priceless worth, as the
                gospel of pure and sober joy serene. </p>
            <p>You will not remember me by name, although I enjoyed your friendly
                consideration&#8212; before the war&#8212;I have pound <unclear reason="illegible"
                    cert="medium" resp="#ss">vast</unclear> volumes of type matter on the people of
                these states since, and led them and their leaders about like bee-swarms with noise
                of cowbells or other clatter. I want a little repose and came here to the Friendly
                City. Some go to Europe, but these states are good enough for me&#8212;especially
                the "friendly city." I have what is called success; made a good swath of greenback
                fodder to leave to my two children. Have ten or fifteen years of better work in
                me yet with good health &#38; clearer brain &#38; spirits than ever. </p>
            <p>I send you $10.00 for the copy to send west, of your poems&#8212;and my photograph
                too if you recollect me.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Carolan O'Brien Bryant</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01086.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
    </text>
</TEI>
