<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.05436">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Abraham Paul Leech, 11 August [1840]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="em">Erel Michaelis</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor> Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder> National Historical Publications and Records Commission </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05436</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Abraham Paul Leech, 11 August [1840]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1840-08-11" xml:id="dat1">August 11, [1840]</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS77909, Box 1</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms005001.mss77909.002</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">Walt Whitman Papers, Miscellaneous Manuscript Collection, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>  
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Leech, Abraham Paul" ref="loc.05440_n1">Abraham Paul
                        Leech</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-10-12" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change> 
            <change when="2022-08-23" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-06-18" who="#kjb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-30" who="#em">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-07" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-29" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-27" who="#cn">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_gk.01465_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Devil's den,<ptr target="loc.05440_n2"/></name>
                    <date when="1840-08-11">Tuesday, Aug. 11.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Why the dickins didn't you come out to the whig meeting at the court house, last
                Saturday week?&#8212;I went there, with the hope of seeing you and one or two
                others, as much as for any thing else.&#8212;I dare say you would have been much
                gratified; at any rate you would have been astonished, for the <hi rend="underline"
                    >orator</hi> of the day related <hi rend="underline">facts</hi>, and cut capers,
                which certainly never before met the eye or ear of civilised man.&#8212;Just before
                sundown the performance concluded, and starting from the C. H. I was overtaken by a
                most impertinent shower, which drenched me to the skin; probably all the whig
                enthusiasm generated on that occasion was melted down again by this unlucky shower,
                for we passed loads of forlorn gentlemen, with draggle-tailed coats,
                crest-fallen hats, and sour-looking phizzes.&#8212;The mighty patriotism
                they felt was <hi rend="underline">drowned</hi> by a tormenting slipperiness of
                coat, shirt, and pantaloons.&#8212;</p>
            <p>Were you ever tried?&#8212;I don't mean tried before Squire Searing<ptr target="n5001"/> or Judge Strong<ptr target="loc.05437_n5"/>
                for breach of promise or theft; but tried as they try mutton fat, to make candles
                of&#8212;boiled down&#8212;<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_gk.01466_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>melted into liquid grease?&#8212;tried as they try martyrs at the
                stake?&#8212;If you havn't&#8212;I have.&#8212;The scene was "Huckleberry plains,"
                The Day Friday last&#8212;the time, from twelve o'clock, M. until 3&#189;
                P.M.&#8212;You see I'm particular.&#8212;The awful occasion impressed indeliby upon
                my memory every agonising moment of that infernal excursion. It was what the ladies
                and gentlemen of this truly refined place called a party of <hi rend="underline"
                    >pleasure</hi>.&#8212;Yes; it was delightful; fun to the back-bone: but it
                cost me a sun-burnt face and neck, from which the skin is even now peeling,
                and four mortal pounds of flesh which ran off in a state of dilution from my
                body.&#8212;The sun poured down whole lumps of red hot fire&#8212;not a tree not a
                shed to shelter us from the intolerable glare.&#8212;</p>
            <p>I gave you in my last some account<ptr target="loc.05436_n3"/> of my first "huckleberry frolick," but this beats
                it all hollow.&#8212;I can only wonder why I was such a thundering fool as to try it
                again.&#8212;</p>
            <p>How are you all in Jamaica?&#8212;What is the news?&#8212;Do you have any games at
                Twenty Questions?&#8212;Does "our portrait" yet remain in the condition of the
                southern banks?&#8212;O, how I wish I was among you for a few hours: how tired and
                sick I am of this wretched, wretched hole!&#8212;I wander about like an evil spirit,
                over hills <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_gk.01467_large.jpg" type="recto"/> and
                dales, and through woods, fields, and swamps. In the manufactory of Nature, the
                building of these coarse gump-heads that people Woodbury, must have been given
                to some raw hand; for surely no decent workman ever had the making of
                them.&#8212;And these are the contemptible ninnies, with whom I have to do, and
                among whom I have to live.&#8212;O, damnation, damnation! thy other name is
                school-teaching and thy residence Woodbury.&#8212;Time, put spurs to thy
                leaden wings, and bring on the period when my allotted time of torment here shall be
                fulfilled.&#8212;Speed, ye airy hours, lift me from this earthly purgatory; nor do I
                care how soon ye lay these pudding-brained bog-trotters, amid their
                kindred earth.&#8212;I do not believe a refined or generous idea was ever born in
                this place; the whole concern, with all its indwellers, ought to be sunk, as Mosher<ptr target="n5001"/>
                says, "to chaos." Never before have I entertained so low an idea of the beauty and
                perfection of man's nature, never have I seen humanity in so degraded a shape, as
                here.&#8212;Ignorance, vulgarity, rudeness, conceit, and dulness are the reigning
                gods of this deuced sink of despair.&#8212;The brutes go barefoot, shave once in
                three weeks, call "brown cow" <hi rend="underline">"brown ke-ow"</hi>; live on sour
                milk, rye bread, and strong pork; believe L.I. sound and the south bay to be the ne
                plus ultra of creation; and the "gals" wear white frocks with red or yellow
                waist-ribauds.<ptr target="loc.05436_n2"/>&#8212;</p> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_gk.01468_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>Think, my friend, think on all this; and pray nightly for my deliverance from this
                dungeon&#8212;where grace or good-breeding never were seen, and from whence
                happiness fled shrieking twenty years ago.&#8212;Farewell&#8212;and may the
                blessings of hope and peace, the sunshine of a joyous heart, never be absent from
                you.&#8212;May the bloom of health glow on your features, the tide of joy swell in
                your heart, and care and grief be strangers to your dwelling</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>W. Whitman</signed>
                <note type="authorial" place="center">Abraham P. Leech | Jamaica, L.I.<ptr target="loc.05437_n4"/></note>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>
