<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03512">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Frederick York Powell to Walt Whitman, 8 January
                    1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Frederick York Powell</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03512</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Frederick York Powell</author>
                    <title>Frederick York Powell to Walt Whitman, 8 January 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-01-08" xml:id="dat1">January 8, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8&#8211;9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 
                    1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Powell, Frederick York" ref="loc.03510_n1">Frederick York Powell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-01-04" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2017-07-12" who="#if">checked</change>
            <change when="2017-03-02" who="#cb">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-09-08" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
            <change when="2016-09-08" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">  
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03512.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline> 
                    <name type="place">Christ Church<lb/>Oxford</name>
                    <date when="1889-01-08">8.I.1889</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>

            <p>I am just writing this after reading your November Boughs.<ptr target="n3999"/> I want to tell you that I
                was glad of the Book. It comes to me in a time of trouble for me and it is a
                help&#8212;I think you will not be sorry to know this. If I were face to face with
                you there are many things in your last poems and writings I should like to talk over
                with you, but it is all too long for a letter and we cannot, save with difficulty, <hi rend="underline">talk</hi> on paper.
            </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03512.002.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>Your sketch of <hi rend="underline">Elias Hicks</hi><ptr target="n0301"/> is very
                pleasant to see, as like yourself I am proud of having Friends among my forebears,
                and their early history is a noble one, surely. You record some folks opinion that Elias was ambitious, but I don't see it in his
               face nor in the tone of the words you quote, nor in your <gap reason="illegible" quantity="4" unit="chars"/>
                impressions and I <gap reason="illegible" quantity="9" unit="chars"/> against it. You did a service 
                <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#smb">before</unclear> in showing people the truth about  
               Old Tom Paine, Blake's friend, and I think many will be thankful for your work on Elias Hicks.</p>  
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03512.003.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <p>I am going to send you a pamphlet which has in it a sketch of William Grimm<ptr target="loc.03512_n3"></ptr> by my best friend
                and fellow-worker <hi rend="underline">Gudbrand Vigfusson</hi>.<ptr target="loc.03512_n2"/> I hope and think you will like it. 
                He that wrote it is I fear <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">now</unclear>
                seriously ill, but he is patient and cheery as your soldier-lads and he has
                waged a good fight too.</p>

            <p>You have many friends here and we do not doubt the success of your <hi
            rend="underline">sortie</hi> you have told the truth and you know there are
            and must be a great-many people that don't like it and don't want to hear it, and feel it unpleasant, and 
                <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">hate</unclear> the light
            because they and their ways are of darkness.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03512.004.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>I don't suppose Dante's Commedia was popular with those he judged, but the next
               generation did not sympathize much with them, and I am sure that the next generation in
               your new land (where the little silly imitators and make-believers are gonewith their lengthy foolish croaking and chattering that 
                <gap reason="illegible" quantity="3" unit="chars"/> such folks go)&#8212;will
                be listening to your truths.</p>
            
            <p>If I could I would cross the water this summer for I should like to see you in the
              flesh, but that is in the hands of the powers, I do not know how my ways may lie 
             these six months hence.</p>  
               
            <p>But anyhow you will know that 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03512.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                your last book has been a help for which I am grateful to you as I am for the
                    former ones and their influence.
                 I only feel that I do not do you justice as with the performance
                 too often lags behind understanding and the spirit is weak too often also.</p>
                 
            <p>But I have no right to trouble you with myself or my concerns and I will stop here wishing you the best you
                can wish for yourself for this year and<pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc.03512.006.jpg" type="verso"/> those to follow</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>I am faithfully yours</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">Frederick York Powell</hi></signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>If you see Dr Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/> I should be glad to be remembered to him and his niece.</p>
            </postscript> 

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03512.007.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <postscript>
                <p>There are a number of <hi rend="underline">young</hi> men I know that read your
                    books&#8212;not merely men of mid-age who follow Gilchrist<ptr target="n0262"/> and Rossetti<ptr target="n0522"/>. 
                    You will like to know this.</p>
            </postscript>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03512.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
