<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.08166">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>  
            <titleStmt> 
                <title level="m" type="main">Richard Maurice Bucke to Walt Whitman, 10 August 1891</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Richard Maurice Bucke</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor> 
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="zs">Zainab Saleh</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt> 
                <edition>
                    <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2021 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.08166</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Richard Maurice Bucke</author>
                    <title>Richard Maurice Bucke to Walt Whitman, 10 August 1891</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1891-08-10" xml:id="dat1">August 10, 1891</date> 
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 6, Reel 3–4</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00102</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, 
                        Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName> 
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Bucke, Richard Maurice" ref="n0119">Richard Maurice Bucke</persName> 
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName> 
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2021-07-25" who="#smb">completed director's corrections</change>
            <change when="2021-05-03" who="#bjo">second check</change>
            <change when="2020-12-12" who="#smb">first check, added DOI and notes</change>
            <change when="2020-02-18" who="#zs">Added images</change>
            <change when="2019-12-04" who="#cn">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_zs.00436.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">49 Comeragh Road<ptr target="loc.08166_n1"/></name>
                    <name type="place">West Kensington</name>
                    <name type="place">London W.</name> 
                    <name type="place">England<ptr target="loc.03165_n2c"/></name> 
                    <date when="1891-08-10"><hi rend="underline">Monday</hi></date>
                    <date when="1891-08-10">10 Aug '91</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>On Saturday I went again to the Smiths<ptr target="loc.08165_n3"/> at Haslemere. Mrs C.<ptr target="loc.03838_n4"/>
                was (and is) away on the Continent (Mr C.<ptr target="n6114"/> too).
                I had plenty of talk with Mr, Mrs, and Alys<ptr target="n7014"/> &amp; Logan S.<ptr target="n6122"/> Logan desired me to 
                send his love to you <hi rend="underline">he</hi>
                is very friendly to you, Mr S. only moderately so &amp; Mrs &amp; A.S. <hi rend="underline">not at all</hi>
                as far as I can find out. Mrs C. I believe is in her heart friendly but "for reasons" she says nothing—this
                matter is too<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_zs.00437.jpg" type="verso"/> delicate to <hi rend="underline">write</hi> about even to you
                but I will tell you all when we meet abt. 2<hi rend="underline">d</hi> or 3<hi rend="underline">d</hi> Sept.
                When I returned to town today I found your letters &amp; card of 24<hi rend="underline">th</hi>, 26<hi rend="underline">th</hi>
                &amp; 29<hi rend="underline">th</hi><ptr target="loc.08166_n2"/> and a couple of letters from H.<ptr target="n4267"/> besides letters from home &amp;c. I am well pleased
                to see that you keep, if not fairly, at least not markedly worse and I hope to find you "right side up with care"
                on my return about 2<hi rend="underline">d</hi> Sept. (not a very long time now). I have the "Lip." and find
                that the "Dinner Piece"<ptr target="loc.08150_n2"/> comes out <hi rend="underline">well</hi>—I think it as good an <hi rend="underline">ad.</hi>
                as we have had. But the main thing I want to talk about to you today is my<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_zs.00438.jpg" type="recto"/>
                visit yesterday to Lord Tennyson.<ptr target="n0625"/> I was (as I have said) at Mr S.<hi rend="underline">s</hi>  and he sent me 
                with a man &amp; buggy to L. T.<hi rend="underline">s</hi> place some 5 ms. away. I drove thro' one of the wildest
                and most beautiful pieces of country (in a drizzling rain) that I have seen anywhere, hills, woods, brush, everywhere,
                but with splendid <hi rend="underline">English</hi> roads to drive on. Got to T.<hi rend="underline">s</hi> place
                (a fine almost stately mansion) a little before 4 P.M. got out, rang the bell—a footman opened the door,
                I gave him your letter and my card &amp; said "please give these to Lord Tennyson." He left me in the hall and disappeared
                in the house—soon he came back and conducted me into a room on the ground floor to the left of the main hall—I went
                in and sat down—in a few minutes a quite young looking and handsome man came in—he held out his hand to me and said
                "good day to D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B." I shook hands with him saying at same time "you are Hallam Tennyson?"<ptr target="loc.02196_n1"/>
                He said he was and<pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_zs.00439.jpg" type="verso"/> we had a little talk—then after saying that "his father"
                was sleeping—that he always lay down for a couple of hours in the afternoon &amp; would not be up until 5 O'C. he asked
                me if I would wait—I said certainly I would wait if he thought L. T. would see me. He said "I don't know, but I would like
                you to wait" then he asked me if I would step in and see Lady T.<ptr target="loc.08166_n3"/> I said I sh<hi rend="underline">d</hi> be very happy to do so.
                He took me to the next room where L. T. was lying on a sofa—a very pale &amp; delicate but a very spiritual, intellectual
                &amp; pleasing face. I sat down by her sofa and we talk<pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_zs.00440.jpg" type="recto"/> for a good half hour about
                Canada &amp; the Canadians—about the late sir John Macdonald,<ptr target="loc.08126_n3"/> about Carlyle<ptr target="n4301"/> &amp; 
                Mrs C.<ptr target="loc.08166_n4"/> (she said they were not understood,
                that Froude's book<ptr target="loc.07242_n2"/> did them injustice—that they were plenty attached to one another &amp;c. She said she had seen Mrs C.
                once when some disparaging remark was made about C. burst into tears) and other things—then Hallam asked me to go with him upstairs
                to see Mrs Tennyson<ptr target="loc.08166_n5"/>—I went (of course)—Mrs T. is a very young looking and almost beautiful woman with an air 
                of considerable distinction—she<pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_zs.00441.jpg" type="verso"/> received me in a half stately but very kind
                manner and we had quite a little talk. (I had been at least half an hour with Lady T. and it was now nearly 5 O'C.)
                A little before 5 Hallam asked me to go with him to Lord T.<hi rend="underline">s</hi> room—I did so. I found L. T.
                in a large room on the first floor (up one stair, as yours is) containing bookshelves and many books—he was sitting on a sofa 
                and as I went in did not see me so as to know who was there —in fact when I went up to him he thought I was Hallam—I spoke
                to him and took his hand (which he thought strange thinking I was H.) however he soon realized who it was and there welcomed me. We then talked
                with perfect unconstraint for an hour. T. is not much for compliments, very blunt and downright—he spoke of you with
                much good feeling but my reception at the house, by the whole family, was a far greater compliment to you than a volume of soft phrases
                would have been.</p> 
                <p>None of the Tennyson's I imagine (I had hardly any talk about L. of G. except with Hallam who spoke very freely and pleasantly<pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_zs.00442.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                on the subject) have read you so as really to understand you or what you are after—but have read you enough to know in a more 
                or less vague way that you are a great force in this modern world. Had I been introduced to the Tennysons by the greatest prince in Europe 
                they could not have received me more courteously, nor had I been a near relative could they have shown me greater friendliness—all this
                of course was for your sake since they did not know of me by name even. But<pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_zs.00443.jpg" type="recto"/> after all I fear I can give
                you but a faint notion of the pleasure my visit was to me. The Smiths had said that T. was old and queer and that he certainly
                would not see me—that <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi> H. would see me &amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c. So that I was totally unprepared
                for the reception they gave me. And the Smith's seemed as much surprised as myself when I went back and told them about it. T.<hi rend="underline">s</hi>
                presence is imposing but does not make as strong an impression of <hi rend="underline">great personality</hi> as I expected.
                He is still handsome but so shortsighted that his eyes have little expression. He is not nearly<pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_zs.00444.jpg" type="verso"/>
                so reserved, careful and dignified in conversation as I looked for—says (with somewhat rapid enunciation) whatever comes uppermost—said
                (for instance) "there—I have caught you in an Americanism" and then pointed out the phrase. Said "I <hi rend="underline">hate</hi>
                that word 'awfully' they might as well say 'bloody' at once—they both <hi rend="underline">mean</hi> the same". Then showing a lot of pictures
                    &amp; busts of self and family (different members) done by Ward<ptr target="loc.08166_n7"/>—Millais<ptr target="loc.08166_n8"/> &amp;c. &amp;c. he said: "The best of it is they never cost me
                a penny—they were all done for nothing."</p>
            <p>I am asked to go back to the Smith's but probably shall not as time is getting short. I sail 26<hi rend="underline">th</hi> inst. &amp; must leave
                London for the north about 20 or 21, Mr Costelloe is to be back in town tomorrow and then we see what is to be done about the meter.<ptr target="loc.07230_n2"/> I have the Danish
                W. W. piece<ptr target="loc.08164_n4"/> translated—am now at Knortz'<ptr target="loc.08166_n9"/> have a lot of work to do yet—give Horace
                my love and show him this letter—tell him to
                <hi rend="underline">keep it</hi>, I may want to see it again as I have no other record of the T. interview. Tell him <hi rend="underline">it must not get out</hi>
                on any account, that would <hi rend="underline">never do</hi>.
            </p>   
            <closer>   
                <salute>Best love to you dear Walt,</salute>
                <signed>R M Bucke</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_zs.00445.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ht">see notes August 20 &amp; 21<hi rend="underline">st</hi> 1891</note>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ww">Visit to Tennyson</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc_zs.00446.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body> 
    </text>
</TEI>