<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01447">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 8 September
    1874</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Thomas Dixon</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
<persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01447</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 8 September 1874</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1874-09-08" xml:id="dat1">September 8, 1874</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 8 Reel 5</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. </orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas" ref="n0196">Thomas Dixon</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-10-29" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-14" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-22" who="#al">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-10-25" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01447.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <handShift rend="print"/>
                <address><addrLine>15. SUNDERLAND STREET.</addrLine><addrLine>Sunderland,</addrLine></address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1874-10-08"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>8 Sept <handShift rend="print"/>18<handShift rend="manuscript"/>74</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><hi rend="underline">Dear Sir</hi>,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I was right glad to hear of you again through the medium of the newspaper, you so
                kindly sent me, I have been thinking of writing you a few lines these months past,
                only I was afraid your illness would prevent you <choice>
                    <sic>form</sic>
                    <corr>from</corr>
                </choice> feeling any interest in one so far away as me, and I also felt so deeply
                for you that I did not like to disturb the repose you seemed to need from your <hi rend="underline">Duty</hi>. the enclosed papers will show you the use I have
                made of the paper, so that other English friends of yours should also learn the good
                news from Camden. Hope these few <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.00560.002.jpg" type="verso"/> Chapters upon you and your work may make your work and you more
                known to our working Classes the periodical in which they were published as
                principally its main subscribers amongst them. the Writer of them is a fellow of
                deep sympathy and has contributed from time to time some fine feeling and
                Sympathetic articles to its pages. the first one I noted was on W.Blake our Poet
                Artist of whom <choice>
                    <sic>Swineburne</sic>
                    <corr>Swinburne</corr>
                </choice><!-- <ptr target="n0610"/> --> has written of so nobly and so well. I post these by
                letter (and send also two by newspaper Post,) so that I may feel somewhat certain
                some of them will reach you. I had some hopes of seeing you in our land, and <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01447.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <!-- Not sure whether or not to transcribe the printed letterhead on the second page, as it is no longer functioning as part of the "opener" or dateline. I have left it untranscribed for now. KM -->
                was delighted beyond measure when I saw in our papers our Tennyson<!-- <ptr target="n0625"/> --> had written to invite you to visit him, I also feel glad to be
                enabled to inform you that W.M. Rossetti's Edition<!-- <ptr target="n0520"/> --> has been <hi rend="underline">all sold</hi>. and the 1872 are subscribed too by our English
                Publisher has also met with a good sale, of course in a way that is not very
                complimentary to English appreciation of your Work. I.E. by being sold in what is
                termed the <hi rend="underline">"remainder sale"</hi> of course my own feeling
                respecting this is, it gives to people of small means an <choice>
                    <sic>oppertunity</sic>
                    <corr>opportunity</corr>
                </choice> to possess a Book they otherwise would never have, "so out of evil cometh
                forth <hi rend="underline">good</hi>" so saith the <hi rend="underline">Old
                    Book</hi></p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.00560.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>last year I was down at oxford at the time <choice>
                    <abbr>Emerson</abbr>
                    <expan><name type="person">Ralph Waldo Emerson</name></expan>
                </choice> was there, I had no <choice>
                    <sic>oppertunity</sic>
                    <corr>opportunity</corr>
                </choice> to speak to him of you, that as I did not think it wise to open the
                question at the times when I saw, I would gladly have done so, only I was not quite
                certain how he felt towards you, so as he did not name you out anytime I was in his
                company as a listener at Max Muller's<!-- <ptr target="n0426"/> -->, I thought it best to be
                silent, and while at oxford I wandered through the Marketplace (for I love to mingle
                with all kinds of my fellow men, but I <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">most</unclear> especially love country folk, fisher folk, and hard
                workers amongst our people I dearly love to mingle with and chat in their ways, and
                to enjoy a kind feeling of sympathy one with the other on these <choice>
                    <sic>occassions</sic>
                    <corr>occasions</corr>
                </choice>,) well while I wandered here and there I saw a stout wellbuilt man in a
                small shop selling paper and when I looked at his <hi rend="underline">wares</hi> I
                saw thereon your Family name, so felt a desire to talk with him. I bought small
                paper then had small talk and he said the only persons he Knew bearing the name
                lived at Egham in Surrey and <choice>
                    <sic>where</sic>
                    <corr>were</corr>
                </choice> mostly Market Gardners. <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01447.005.jpg" type="recto"/> and one branch of the family had been Stewards of the Duke of
                Richmond, and one had emigrated to America some distant relation of his family years
                ago, but they had never heard any news of them&#8212;so when I told him there was
                such a name in America owned by a family there and one of them was a poet, he
                thought perhaps it might be possible you <choice>
                    <sic>where</sic>
                    <corr>were</corr>
                </choice> a <choice>
                    <sic>desendant</sic>
                    <corr>descendant</corr>
                </choice> of that distant relative. he was quite a build of man like you, a noble
                large bodied and large featured man, full of seeming good honest purpose in his
                nature, and more like a farmer than a humble Stationer, so that he did honour to the
                Stock, though not exactly in his trade. he was a type of man I like to see, only he
                seemed rather confined in his ideas of Books.&#8212;</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.00560.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I sent to him some small notice of you and your work, from Chambers paper, but I
                never received any reply, so feel afraid your work is not of a kind to suit his
                tastes. I note also recently your Poem on Lincoln has been read in London at a <choice>
                    <sic>Liberary</sic>
                    <corr>Library</corr>
                </choice> Association, so slowly though I suppose and hope certainly will you become
                known to us more widely and truly. Well I must conclude this rambling note, with a
                hearty wish that you will be once again able to do some more work for our race and
                help on the Life, that our hope is, yet shall <hi rend="underline">be</hi>. Ruskin
                is also working hard too to help on a nobler life, and one not much unlike the one
                you also long to see. so many souls labouring for one end must someday effect the
                accomplishment of the "Golden Days" so long sung, so long toiled for, prayed
                for&#8212;and fought for!!</p>


            <closer>
                <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">T Dixon<!-- <ptr target="n0196"/> --></hi></signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>