<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?> 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01374">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe to Walt Whitman, 1 October
                    1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="es">Jeannette Schollaert</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01374</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe</author>
                    <title>Mary Whitall Smith Costelloe to Walt Whitman, 1 October 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-10-01" xml:id="dat1">October 1, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Costelloe, Mary Whitall Smith" ref="loc.02189_n1">Mary Whitall
                        Smith Costelloe</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-03-15" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-10-28" who="#cb">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-06-27" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-12-14" who="#es">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01374.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right"><handShift rend="typescript"/>Llwynbarried,
                        Rhayder, Wales.</name>
                    <date when="1888-10-01" rend="right"><handShift rend="typescript"/>October 1.
                        1888.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="typescript"/>Dear Mr. Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="typescript"/>Thy welcome card came just as we were leaving London
                last week,<ptr target="loc.001374_n1"/> after a very sad week with my cousin Saidee, whom thee may remember. She
                has been living for the last year &#38; a half in Berlin, her husband being
                correspondent for the N.Y. Herald, &#38; a few weeks ago the summons came for him to
                go back to New York. So they planned to stop in London for a couple of weeks on
                their way home, do their necessary shopping &#38; say their goodbyes to all of us.
                    Frank<ptr target="n6114"/> &#38; I were in Scotland when we first heard of this
                plan, &#38; we hastened to come down &#38; meet them, full of all kinds of joyful
                anticipations. Saidee &#38; I were most eager to compare, the great rivals, her
                little boy a year &#38; a half old, &#38; Ray her baby girl almost the same age.
                Besides little Charley, Saidee had another baby to show me, a dear little creature
                only a month old. Mother &#38; father lent their house&#8212;No. 44&#8212;to
                them for their London stay, so that we were close together. When we arrived from
                Scotland, however, we found everything in confusion. The journey had been too much
                for them all: Saidee was ill in bed, both babies were ailing, &#38; the youngest one
                dangerously ill. Mr. Nordhoff, Saidee's husband, had not crossed with her, but was
                travelling in Germany with a changing address, so that he could not be telegraphed
                to, &#38; soon after we came the doctor, contrary to all professional ettiquette
                gave up the baby's case, &#38; they did not know to whom to apply. So all our week
                which we had been looking forward to as a happy reunion, was given over to anxiety
                &#38; telegrams to doctors and nurses who all seemed to be out of town. At the end 
                of the time, on Saturday, the baby died in his mother's arms. The next day Mr.
                Nordhoff arrived &#38; then we came away, as I was quite worn out with the
                responsibility &#38; anxiety. We have been resting here for a week now, &#38; <pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01374.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01374.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> we have news
                that Saidee &#38; the other child are better, &#38; that they expect to sail on the
                same day that this letter begins its voyage to cross to thee.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="typescript"/>I had a welcome letter from Dr. Bucke<ptr
                    target="n0119"/> giving good news about thy health, &#38; from thy pen this
                morning in the Century are the army reminiscences which we have all enjoyed
                exceedingly. So I do not feel, somehow as if we were all the world apart. I can
                imagine myself tomorrow crossing the Camden ferry &#38; coming to find thee in thy
                den ready to talk as if I had not ever been away at all. I only wish it could come
                true! I wonder if Mr. Gilchrist<ptr target="n0262"/> is with thee now, &#38; whether
                he has got his professorship in the Art Academy. He promised to write &#38; tell me,
                but I have never heard from him.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="typescript"/>We are at work upon our belated philosophy, grinding
                out the first few chapters which we have long had in the shape of scrappy notes. I
                dont know whether I ever told thee our ambitions. We want to write a philosophy in
                terms simple enough for anyone to understand, explaining what Kant has done in the
                investigation of knowledge, &#38; then going on to make use of the same critical
                method to find out what presuppositions lie at the basis of action. So that we hope
                to establish a method of studying ethics on the same secure basis which philosophers
                now have for the examination of knowledge. But it is incredibly hard to open the
                results of close thinking to people who do not care enough to take the trouble to
                think out for themselves, &#38; every time we try our MS. on one of the uninitiated
                we are profoundly discouraged. I am using these days of leisure to mature a scheme
                of education for Ray,<ptr target="loc.01354_n3"/> &#38; enlarge my list of books for her. I want to begin her on
                the folklore of all the different nations for her fairy tales, &#38; lead her on
                from that to an interest in the history &#38; geography &#38; government of those
                nations. Logan<ptr target="loc.01350_n3"/> &#38; Frank &#38; I are also reading a
                little Greek together, &#38; our spare time we give to play&#8212; </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01374.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
