<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01456">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 15 April 1875</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nsb">Noelle Bates</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.01456</idno></publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
                    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 15 April 1875</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1875-04-15" xml:id="dat1">April 15, 1875</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8, Reel 5</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00151</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas" ref="n0196">Thomas Dixon</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-08" who="#smb">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2023-07-28" who="#aja">final corrections for Matt</change>
            <change when="2023-05-12" who="#aja">updated notes</change>
            <change when="2022-11-15" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-07-28" who="#nsb">checked and revised</change>
            <change when="2021-12-11" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-04-24" who="#ak">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change when="2014-08-15" who="#el">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-10-29" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-15" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-23" who="#al">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-10-25" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01456.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <handShift rend="printed"/>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">15. SUNDERLAND STREET.</name>
                    <name type="place">Sunderland,</name>
                    <date when="1875-04-15"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>15 April <handShift rend="printed"/>18<handShift rend="manuscript"/>75</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I was glad to see again once more a scrawl from you, even in a paper. I felt also glad to see there is someone 
                else more gifted <choice><sic>then</sic><corr>than</corr></choice> me trying to honour you and make your 
                <hi rend="underline">Work</hi> known in our Old land. 
                I noted the French Review—fain
                would I have read it, but alas I can only read my own tongue. I <hi rend="underline">often</hi> and 
                <hi rend="underline">often</hi>—wish one could conjure up some Spirit to give one the meaning of much 
                I see in other tongues, but alas though I <hi rend="underline">often call</hi> up spirit alas—comes 
                to aid me at my call. Well to <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#me">cease</unclear> 
                I got your Essay on Burns<ptr target="n0127"/> reprinted here in two local papers. I enclose one rejoinder 
                from a canny Scot, a decent soul, a man that came here a Journeyman and now is the working Manager of 500 men.
                he is also a <choice><sic>Ryhmer</sic><corr>Rhymer</corr></choice> one little Sketch of his I enclose you.<ptr target="n5002f"/>
                you will see he is of a narrow school of thought, wants <hi rend="underline">width</hi>, 
                <hi rend="underline">he has</hi> got a <hi rend="underline">good heart though</hi></p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01456.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I must confess I felt <choice><sic>disapointed</sic><corr>disappointed</corr></choice> somewhat in the Burns. 
                I fear you are not well up in Burns' Life. he was to all intents and purposes a Nature akin to yours. 
                true not so wide, not so democratic, still a democrat. he lost promotion through his sympathy with the 
                French Revolution 1793—he sent some guns to them which were stopped. that speaks for the man's sympathy
                with the <hi rend="underline">cause</hi> of man. Carlyle's<ptr target="n1065"/> Essay on him and 
                his Poems is by far the justest I have read with <choice><sic>Lockheart</sic><corr>Lockhart</corr></choice>'s<ptr target="n0365"/> 
                Life of him. feeling how much there is of real Kinship between your two natures I felt sorry to find you 
                had not fully grasped the hand of my Hero of Scotland in 1793. <hi rend="underline">A man's a man for ah 
                    that."</hi><ptr target="loc.01456_n1"/> what a cheering voice that is to any soul that is able to read it. 
                then again his idea that even 
                "auld Nick "might be saved if he only would take a thought and mend" is the widest stretch of true charity I
                find in any—Poetry. I find his poetry comes home to the heart of all human Kind. I find in my travels 
                and talks with men, many of their poor hard 
                toiling souls to whom his Poems are the very gospel of consolation and hope.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01456.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I hope you will look it up again for us if possible. He will repay some thought I think I only wish I 
                had you here beside me, then we could talk it over together so nicely. the stray notices I could place
                into your hands would enable you to see the full <hi rend="underline">man</hi>. I feel glad you have done
                what you have, but yearn for <hi rend="underline">more</hi>. give us Essays on Emerson<ptr target="n1044"/>
                &amp; Tennyson.<ptr target="n0625"/> I often try to make out for myself what you really think of these two men.
                you are so dear to me, I often wish I was by your side. I feel there is so much I sympathise 
                and love in Literature.—that we could chat over. and I think <choice><sic>where</sic><corr>were</corr></choice>
                it so, how many nice Essays would be done that would rejoice the hearts of brothers in the same grand school 
                of human sympathy. the great hearts of our Time are <choice><sic>begginning</sic><corr>beginning</corr></choice> 
                to wake up—we are <choice><sic>begginning</sic><corr>beginning</corr></choice> to shake 
                <choice><sic>of</sic><corr>off</corr></choice> the bondage cast over us by the Jewish Race through their
                Books and the priesthood that has arisen from them.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01456.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I learn with sorrow and deep regret, your Poems are still a venture of your own. are your pupils too poor? 
                What are we think you? if our prophet starve? excuse me being <choice><sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr></choice> 
                bold: The great heart of America surely cannot long allow this to be true? or is it the penalty all prophets 
                pay for being such to a people? Well I hope <hi rend="underline">sunshine</hi> will come, and that soon. 
                If I can in anyway be helpful let me know. I can at least try. we are far apart that is true. 
                yet even here something I might do as a manifestation of my love and fellowship. I enclose some 
                cuttings that have been saved for your reading.<ptr target="n5002g"/> with a kind of boy's care I have 
                gathered them. I would have sent them by news post, only I was afraid they would get lost, so thought this way 
                was the best. I write you these few lines, simply as a quick reply to your scrawl, not by any means all I 
                hoped to write you. If silent never once think you are <hi rend="underline">forgotten</hi> 
                even by one of the Old land.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours in true sympathy of heart</salute>
                <signed>Thomas Dixon</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>