<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01986">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">A. Simpson &amp; Co. to Walt Whitman, 19 August 1867</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>A. Simpson &amp; Co.</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01986</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>       
<bibl>
    <author>A. Simpson &amp; Co.</author>
    <title>A. Simpson &amp; Co. to Walt Whitman, 19 August 1867</title>  
    <date cert="high" when="1867-08-19" xml:id="dat1">August 19, 1867</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 16 Reel 10</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
              
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="A. Simpson &amp; Co.">A. Simpson &amp; Co.</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-09-19" who="#cb">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-06-26" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-05-21" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01986.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
             <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><p><handShift rend="printed"/>MESSRS. A SIMPSON &amp; CO.</p>
                 <p>RESPECTFULLY ANNOUNCE THAT THEY HAVE ESTABLISHED A</p>
                 <p>PUBLISHING HOUSE</p>
                 <p>AT</p>
                 <p>60 Duane Street,</p>
                 <p>and in connection therewith the AGATHYNIAN PRESS.</p>
                 <p>They purpose devoting their energies to the printing and publication of useful and valuable books, which will be produced in the highest style of the Typographical Art.</p>
                 <p>MR. SIMPSON, of this firm, has been the superintendent of the Bradstreet Press from its organization to the present time, and will have the immediate charge of the Typographical Department of the house.</p>
                 <p>Special attention will be given to the publication of Medical and other Scientific Books, though, at the same time, all the higher branches of literature will be included.</p>
                 <p>The attention of American authors is respectfully invited to the facilities which Messrs.  A. SIMPSON &amp; Co. possess for bringing their works prominently before the public in a beautiful and artistic form.</p>
                 <p>Being Printers and Publishers for several Printing Clubs, and having a large assortment of type of old and modern styles, they will be enabled to undertake the reprint of old books in fac-simile.</p>
                 <p>MESSRS. A. SIMPSON &amp; Co. are publishers of the following periodicals:</p>
                 <list type="simple">
                     <item>I.&#8212;The NEW YORK MEDICAL JOURNAL.  A monthly record of medicine, and the Collateral Sciences.  Edited by William A. Hammond, M.D., and E. S.  Dunster, M.D. Subscription, <!-- dollar sign [$] may also be an eight [8] --> $5.00 per annum.</item>
                     <item>II.&#8212;The QUARTERLY JOURNAL OF PSYCHOLOGICAL MEDICINE AND MEDICAL JURISPRUDENCE.  Edited by William A. Hammond, M.D. Subscription, <!-- dollar sign [$] may also be an eight [8] --> $5.00 per annum.</item>
                          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01986.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                     <item>III.&#8212;<hi rend="bold">The Philobiblion</hi>. A Bibliographical Journal, containing critical notices of, and extracts from, rare, curious and valuable old Books.  Edited by George P. Philes.  This Journal will be revived in October next. Subscription, <!-- dollar sign [$] may also be an eight [8] --> $5.00 per annum.</item>
                     <item>IV.&#8212;The Publications of the AGATHYNIAN CLUB.  Of these, one volume has appeared&#8212;the ADVICE TO THE OFFICERS OF THE BRITISH ARMY; and the second, <hi rend="bold">The Proverbs of Erasmus</hi>, edited by George P. Philes, is nearly ready.  The third issue, the Works of the famous Antiquary, Polydore Vergil, will be ready October 1st, 1867, and will be printed at the Agathynian Press.  Subscription, $5.00; 120 copies only will be printed, of which 100 will be for sale.  No pains or expense will be spared to make those publications superior to the first, which obtained such favorable commendations from the lovers of beautiful typography.</item>
                     <item>V.&#8212;The Publications of the DALIAN CLUB. 125 copies only printed.  The form is small quarto, the typography of the very highest excellence.  The first issue will be ready September 1st.</item>
                 </list>
             </div1>
            <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N"><head>ANNOUNCEMENTS.</head>
            <p>Messrs. A. SIMPSON &amp; Co. respectfully announce for early publication, the following works by Foreign and American Authors:</p>
               <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                    <head>GENERAL SCIENCE</head>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <head>I.</head>
                    <item>METEORS, AËROLITES, AND FALLING STARS. By T. L. Phipson, Doctor of Science, etc.</item>
                    <item>An admirable little work, written in simple language, and treating of a most interesting department of science.</item>
                    </list>
<list type="simple">
    <head>II.</head>
    <item>GEOLOGY FOR GENERAL READERS. A series of Popular Sketches in Geology and Palæontology. By David Page, F.R.S.E., etc.</item>
    <item>In this work the author has endeavored to produce a treatise which every intelligent person can understand.  It should find a place in every library, large and small.</item>
</list>
                <list type="simple">
                    <head>III.</head>
                    <item>POPULAR LECTURES ON FOOD.  By E. Lankester, M.D., F.R.S., etc.</item>
                </list>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01986.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <list type="simple"><head>IV.</head><item>THE USES OF ANIMALS IN RELATION TO THE INDUSTRY OF MAN.  By E. Lankester, M.D., etc.</item><item>Both the above works are exceedingly interesting and instructive, and are freely illustrated.</item></list>
                <list type="simple">
                    <head>V.</head>
                <item>THE REASONING POWER IN ANIMALS.  By the Rev. John Selby Watson.</item>
                </list>
                <list type="simple">
                    <head>VI.</head>
                        <item>PHYSIOLOGY AT THE FARM, IN AID OF REARING AND FEEDING THE LIVE STOCK.  By William Seller, M.D., etc., and Henry Stephens.  A book for every Farmer and Rearer of Cattle.</item>
                </list></div2>
                <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                    <head>MEDICAL SCIENCE.</head>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <head>I.</head>
                        <item>BELLEVUE AND CHARITY HOSPITAL REPORTS.  A collection of monographs by Physicians and Surgeons of these great hospitals, and by other medical gentlement of eminence, similar in general scope to Guy's Hospital and other English Hospital Reports, to be published on the 1st of January of each year.  The first volume is now in preparation, and will be published January 1st, 1868. Subscriptions will be received by the undersigned.  Price to subscribers, $5.00; to all others, $6.00.  A limited edition only will be printed.</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <head>II.</head>
                        <item>A MANUAL OF MINOR SURGERY AND SURGICAL DRESSINGS.  By James L. Little, M.D., Lecturer on Operative Surgery and Surgical Dressings in the College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York.  (In preparation.)</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <head>III.</head>
                        <item>A TREATISE ON EMOTIONAL DISORDERS OF TEH SYMPATHETIC SYSTEM OF NERVES.  By William Murray, M.D., etc.  (In press.)</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <head>IV.</head>
                        <item>LIGHT; IT'S INFLUENCE ON LIFE AND HEALTH.  By Forbes Winslow, M.D.  (In press.)</item>
                    </list>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01986.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <list type="simple"><head>V.</head><item>A TREATISE ON MELANCHOLY.  From the French of Dr. E. Du Vivier.</item></list>
                </div2>
                <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                    <head>BELLES LETTRES AND GENERAL LITERATURE.</head>
                    <list type="simple"><head>I.</head>
                    <item>POEMS By F.S. Cozzens, author of the "Sparrowgrass Papers," etc. (In preparation.)</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <head>II.</head>
                        <item>THE SAYINGS OF DR. BUSHWHACKER, AND OTHER LEARNED MEN; By F. S. Cozzens, (author of the Sparrowgrass papers) et al. (In press.)</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="simple">
                            <head>III.</head>
                            <item>POEMS FROM THE PORTUGUESE OF LUIS DE CAMOENS; with Remarks on his Life and Writings.  By Lord Viscount Strangford.  (In press.)</item>
                        </list>
                    <list type="simple">
                        <head>IV.</head>
                        <item>GALILEO.  HIS LIFE, HIS DISCOVERIES, AND HIS WORKS.  From the French of Dr. Max <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#js">Partlioppe</unclear>.  (In preparation.)</item>
                    </list></div2>
                    <closer>
                        <address>
                    <addrLine>A. SIMPSON &amp; CO.,</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>PRINTERS &amp; PUBLISHERS,</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>No. 60 DUANE ST, NEW YORK.</addrLine>
                </address>
                    </closer>
            </div1>
         <!--   <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01986.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>the Agathynian Club,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>18 BEEKMAN STREET,</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>New York.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </opener>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01986.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01986.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <address>
                <addrLine>Walt Whitman Esq.</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Washington</addrLine>
                <addrLine>D C</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01986.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/> --> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>