<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01889">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">William Michael Rossetti to Walt Whitman,
    31 March [1872]</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>William Michael Rossetti</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
<persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01889</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc><bibl>
    <author>William Michael Rossetti</author>
    <title>William Michael Rossetti to Walt Whitman, 31 March [1872]</title>
    <date cert="medium" when="1872-03-31" xml:id="dat1">March 31, 1872</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Rossetti, William Michael" ref="n0522">William Michael Rossetti</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-02-01" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-18" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-09" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-05-03" who="#al">Checked and corrected.</change>
            <change when="2011-03-29" who="#kk">Transcribed, encoded.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01889.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <address><addrLine>56 Euston Sq.</addrLine><addrLine>London, N.W.</addrLine></address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1872-03-31">31 March.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Mr. Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Your very interesting &amp; valued letter of 30 Jan<add type="insertion">?</add><!--link to this letter--> ought to have been answered before now. As you
                are willing to confess in it, however, to being an irregular correspondent, I gladly
                avail myself of so tempting an opening for saying that I am the same&#8212;&amp;
                shall feel confident that my delay is pardoned.</p>
            <p>I read with much zeal the poem you kindly sent me, with its deep sonata–like
                alternations of emotion.</p>
            <p>It was a peculiar pleasure to me to get acquainted with Mr. Burroughs, <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01889.002.jpg" type="verso"/> to whom <choice>
                    <sic>w.d</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> you please remember me with great cordiality whenever the chance occurs.
                He may have told you&#8212;&amp; indeed it cannot have needed telling&#8212;that you
                were a very principal subject of our discourse, &amp; of my reiterated
                enquiries.</p>
            <p>It interests me to see in your letter that you have a habit of taking moonlight walks
                out of Washington: I used to find walks of this kind highly enjoyable, &amp; have
                frequently indulged in them years ago. In my youth I was living in habits of daily
                &amp; brotherly intimacy with various painters (Millais<!-- <ptr target="n0771"/> -->, Holman
                    Hunt<!-- <ptr target="n0317"/> -->, &amp;c); &amp; from time to time we <choice>
                    <sic>w.d</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> all sally out, 6 or 7, say towards 11 at
                night<!-- First recorded instance of "night boating." -->, &amp; pass the whole
                night, &amp; sometimes the succeeding day <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01889.003.jpg" type="recto"/> as well, tramping about, &amp; enjoying
                the varying effects of night, dawn, &amp;c&#8212;studied of course with peculiar
                interest, &amp; directness of observation &amp; purpose, by the painters: sometimes,
                instead of walking, we <choice>
                    <sic>w.d</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> row up the river from nightfall to day. There is a goodish deal of
                agreeable country round London: but, unless one lives quite out in the suburbs, it
                takes miles of walking to get even to the beginning of anything green or rural. I
                can easily imagine that to walk out of Washington at night "into Virginia or
                Maryland" is an experience of a very different sort, in point of grandeur &amp;
                impressiveness. <choice>
                    <sic>Tho'</sic>
                    <corr>Though</corr>
                </choice> indeed, from some points of view <choice>
                    <sic>wh.</sic>
                    <corr>which</corr>
                </choice> you of all men realize most intensely, nothing surely can be more
                impressive than the unmeasured size <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01889.004.jpg" type="verso"/> &amp; colossal agglomeration of life in London&#8212;none the
                less felt through the interminable streets when all are asleep, &amp; scarcely a
                passenger met athwart one's path. The interval when the streets are really deserted
                to this extent is but brief: I suppose from about 2 ¾ to 4 a.m. is the most
                vacant time.</p>
            <p>What you say about the insulting &amp; in fact ungrateful treatment <choice>
                    <sic>wh.</sic>
                    <corr>which</corr>
                </choice> your poems continue to receive in America is deeply interesting, <choice>
                    <sic>tho'</sic>
                    <corr>though</corr>
                </choice> painful. I suppose it is a very general if not universal experience that
                anything that is at once great &amp; extremely novel encounters for some
                considerable time much more hostility than acceptance, &amp; so far your experience
                is not surprising&#8212;rather indeed a testimonial, when properly considered, to
                the great intrinsic value of your writings. But certainly <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01889.005.jpg" type="recto"/> it does seem that in degree &amp;
                duration the obduracy of Americans <choice>
                    <sic>agst.</sic>
                    <corr>against</corr>
                </choice> your work is something abnormal &amp; unworthy&#8212;especially
                considering the spirit of intense patriotic love &amp; national insight <choice>
                    <sic>wh.</sic>
                    <corr>which</corr>
                </choice> pervades your book <choice>
                    <sic>thro</sic>
                    <corr>through</corr>
                </choice> &amp; <choice>
                    <sic>thro</sic>
                    <corr>through</corr>
                </choice>. That America <choice>
                    <sic>sh.d</sic>
                    <corr>should</corr>
                </choice> be so wanting (in this matter at least) in large receptiveness &amp; quick
                intuition is distressing to those who love her&#8212;among whom I may humbly but
                truly profess myself. It seems as if she were even <hi rend="underline">less</hi>
                capable than others of appreciating great work vital with the very marrow of her
                bones &amp; corpuscles of her blood: perhaps this very affinity is partly the
                reason&#8212;but at any rate a bad &amp; perverse reason. In this country there are
                of course very diverse knots of opinion, &amp; schools of thinking &amp; criticism,
                &amp; to several of these your <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01889.006.jpg" type="verso"/> works are still an exasperation &amp; an offence: but others
                accept &amp; exalt you with all readiness of love &amp; delight, &amp; I think I may
                safely say that it is these <choice>
                    <sic>wh</sic>
                    <corr>which</corr>
                </choice> have in their holding the future of English opinion on such matters for
                some years to come.&#8212;But I will say no more on this tack. For myself (with
                others) who believe in you with the certainty of full conviction, all these
                considerations are poor &amp; slight: the one thing in the work itself, &amp; the
                maker of the work, which has a destiny as assured &amp; as limitless as that of any
                other great product of the soul or of nature.</p>
            <p>I have not met Prof. Dowden since last summer (or spring perhaps): he is seldom, I
                think, out of Ireland. <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01889.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                What I saw of him I liked particularly. He seems an uncommonly young man to be a
                Professor&#8212;less than 30 to look at; &amp; is in no common degree
                good–looking, pleasant, open, &amp; sound–minded. There are few men, I <choice>
                    <sic>sh.d</sic>
                    <corr>should</corr>
                </choice> say, more likely to have their sympathies in literary matters sane and
                right&#8212;guided also by the fullest measure of lettered cultivation. Mrs.
                    Gilchrist<!-- <ptr target="n0259"/> --> I dined with not many weeks ago. She seems to
                have fairly recovered from a very exhaustive &amp; indeed dangerous illness that
                oppressed her of late (say from the early autumn of 1870 to the late summer of
                1871)&#8212;only that she is not so capable as she used to be of continuous mental
                or bodily strain. It was a pleasure to see her surrounded by her family, <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01889.008.jpg" type="verso"/> the type of a true
                mother, guiding &amp; nurturing all aright in her children, mind &amp; body. The
                eldest son bids fair to have a distinguished &amp; prosperous career as a mining
                engineer: a younger son is greatly set on being a painter. One of the daughters is
                just about grown up, the other, I suppose, 10 or 11 years of age.&#8212;Mr. J. A.
                    Symonds<!-- <ptr target="n0615"/> --> I don't know personally; but, about the time when
                my selection from your Poems came out, he wrote to me (2 or 3 letters) showing
                himself to have been for some while fast one of your very ardent admirers. Tennyson<!-- <ptr target="n0625"/> -->
                I have known for years, &amp; like much, I think him deep–hearted &amp;
                high–minded, <choice>
                    <sic>tho</sic>
                    <corr>though</corr>
                </choice> it may be true (as has often been said, &amp; sometimes not in a kindly
                    <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.01889.009.jpg" type="recto"/> spirit) that he is
                somewhat too self–centred, &amp; morbidly sensitive. He hates all the <hi rend="underline">vulgarizing</hi> aspects of fame, &amp; some people find him
                present a very obtuse exterior to their advances or approaches: for myself, I can
                truly say my experience is the direct contrary. I think you &amp; he <choice>
                    <sic>w.d</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> understand each other, &amp; feel on a very friendly footing. Tennyson (as
                I dare say you know) is a remarkably fine manly person to look at, with a noble
                mould of face, &amp; very powerful frame. He must be 6 foot 1 in height. I <choice>
                    <sic>sh.d</sic>
                    <corr>should</corr>
                </choice> suppose&#8212;but not now, so erect as in his prime.&#8212; If you do at
                any time come to England, to see Tennyson or others, I need not say what a delight
                it <choice>
                    <sic>w.d</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> be to me to know you personally&#8212;&amp; several of my friends <choice>
                    <sic>w.d</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> amply <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.01889.010.jpg" type="verso"/> share
                my feeling.</p>
            <p>My vol. of Selections from American Poets<!-- <ptr target="n0523"/> --> doesn't seem likely to
                be published yet awhile. It has been completed for <choice>
                    <sic>mo.s</sic>
                    <corr>months</corr>
                </choice> past: but, as it is one vol. of a series, &amp; others of the vols. are in
                course of printing, the printer may probably leave it over for a few <choice>
                    <sic>mo.s</sic>
                    <corr>months</corr>
                </choice> to come. I have in the briefest terms dedicated it to you (&amp; hope you
                won't object). Any other dedication&#8212;at least, if to any one on your side of
                the Atlantic&#8212;<choice>
                    <sic>wd</sic>
                    <corr>would</corr>
                </choice> be a fatuity.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Believe me <choice>
                        <orig>honoured</orig>
                        <reg>honored</reg>
                    </choice> to be called your friend,</salute>
                <signed>W. M. Rossetti<!-- <ptr target="n0522"/> --></signed>
            </closer>

            <postscript>
                <p>I have no doubt you will have felt sorrow as I did&#8212;<choice>
                        <sic>tho</sic>
                        <corr>though</corr>
                    </choice> indeed <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.01889.011.jpg" type="recto"/>sorrow is not fully the right word, nor the right emotion&#8212;at reading
                    lately of the death of Mazzini<!-- <ptr target="n0392"/> -->. I, who am ¾ Italian in
                    blood, have naturally a strong feeling on these subjects: &amp; I regard Mazzini
                    as the noblest of patriots, &amp; the man to whom more than any other single
                    person not even excepting Garibaldi, the lovers of Italian unity are beholden.
                    It is often a pleasure to me to reflect that, with all the miserable oppression
                    &amp; depression under <choice>
                        <sic>wh.</sic>
                        <corr>which</corr>
                    </choice> she has so long been <choice>
                        <orig>labouring</orig>
                        <reg>laboring</reg>
                    </choice>, Italy has after all produced the 3 greatest public men (to my
                    thinking such) of the last 100 years in England&#8212;</p>
                <p><!--are these paragraph division sufficient, or ought we to create a list?-->1.
                    Napoleon I<!-- <ptr target="n0432"/> -->, the greatest genius as a conqueror &amp; ruler
                    (I suppose any one is to be allowed to admire <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.01889.012.jpg" type="verso"/> him enormously, whether one approves
                    him or not&#8212; &amp; to call him a Frenchman, or anything save an Italian, is
                    meaningless)</p>
                <p>2. Mazzini, the greatest of ideal statesmen&#8212;patriot&#8212;</p>
                <p>3. Garibaldi, the greatest &amp; most flawless personal hero.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>