<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03651">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Sarah Avery to Walt Whitman, 20 May 1873</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Sarah Avery</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.03651</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>       
<bibl>
    <author>Sarah Avery</author>
    <title>Sarah Avery to Walt Whitman, 20 May 1873</title>  
    <date cert="high" when="1873-05-20" xml:id="dat1">May 20, 1873</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 194</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
              
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Avery, Sarah" ref="n0055">Sarah Avery</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-01">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-09-19" who="#cb">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-06-26" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-06-21" who="#js">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

          
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03651.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1873-05-20">May 20 1873</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Cousin Walt</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I presume you will be a little surprised when you open this letter&#8212;and will cast your eyes down at the end of it before you read it to see the writers <hi rend="underline">name</hi>, but I received a letter from your Mother telling me of your very severe illness in <choice><sic>wich</sic><corr>which</corr></choice> you have our Heartfelt sympathy (Barth, my Husband, and myself) your Mother asked me to write to you &amp; write about any thing she says will interest you</p>
            <p>Now Cousin I hardly know what to write&#8212;there are many things of interest I could write about&#8212;But to write to one who has so much knowledge and intellect I am afraid you will think <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word"/> but a very poor hand at it&#8212;and the trouble with cousin Sarah she writes her letters so plainly&#8212;you must excuse my simple way of writing you (now there is something that interests <hi rend="underline">me</hi> <hi rend="underline">just</hi> <hi rend="underline">now</hi> and I will tell
            
                     
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03651.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                you all about––it is to take place this month to of my <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word"/> one to be memorized one your Mother knowing Mr Olivers' daughter of Brooklyn from your old neighborhood the other lives at Binghampton Dr. Griffen's daughter you may have heard of him he had charge of one of the hospital at <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word"/> drawing the men two model wifes that can <hi rend="underline">grace</hi> <hi rend="underline">the</hi> <hi rend="underline">parlor</hi> or <hi rend="underline">grace</hi> <hi rend="underline">the</hi> kitchen (if need be) this is the kind of <hi rend="underline">wife</hi> <hi rend="underline">men</hi> in my opinion ought to look for not a doll to be looked at, I hope <hi rend="underline">cousin</hi> if you live to get well you will look about and get such a one for a <hi rend="underline">wife</hi> because you will meet just such a one in your old days I do not mean to say you are an old man <choice><sic>bye</sic><corr>by</corr></choice> any means because I do not know how old you are (now do not suppose for a moment that I am a match maker (&amp; no I am not) but I do feel sorry for old <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#cb">Bachelors</unclear>) me think I see you lay this <hi rend="underline">scribbles</hi> down with a remark: <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#cb"/> cousin Sarah must think I have a great deal of time to master
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03651.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            it in reading this paper. But I have taken your Mother advice&#8212;I said I did not know what to write&#8212;her reply was any thing would charm you. Now I am fraid I have gone too far&#8212;but you must make all due allowance for me <hi rend="underline">must</hi> you. I could have written a mans' sympathetic letter (But then my heart is so full of my own sad Afflictions) But nevertheless you have our sympathy</p>
            <p><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#js">John has</unclear> just called my attention to a paragraph in the evening <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#cb">express</unclear>, in <choice><sic>wich</sic><corr>which</corr></choice> it speaks of your improved health I can assure you we are glad to hear that if is so now cousin Walter if you feel that you have time to answer this <choice><sic>scribbleing</sic><corr>scribbling</corr></choice> I should think it a favor (can you read it I doubt if you can) you do not know perhaps I am left handed so you will please make all due allowances John wishes to be remembered to you</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>truly your cousin</salute>
                <signed>Sarah Avery</signed>
                
                <address>
                    <addrLine>152 Henry st</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>New York</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03651.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>