<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04271">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Horace Tarr to Walt Whitman, 1 December 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Horace Tarr</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04271</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Horace Tarr</author>
                    <title>Horace Tarr to Walt Whitman, 1 December 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-12-01" xml:id="dat1">December 1, 1890</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Tarr, Horace" ref="loc.00412_n3">Horace Tarr</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-12-01" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00441.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="left">fm Horace Tarr</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.00442.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00443.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>86 LIBERTY STREET,</name>
                    <name type="place">NEW YORK CITY.</name>
                    <date when="1890-12-01">Dec. 1, 1890.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/>My Dear Mr. Whitman:&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>

            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Since Jeff's<ptr target="n4995"/> death I have been
                constantly thinking that there should be some proper obituary notice of him
                published in one of the engineering journals.</p>

            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>At the time of the death of Moses Lane,<ptr
                    target="loc.00443_n3"/> I found that the notices which I wrote brought forth
                others from his friends, and withal it was very satisfactory to his family and those
                to whom he was especially dear.</p>



            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>In Jeff's case, there is no one of us that knows enough of
                his early life to write a proper notice, in fact, there is no one that can do this
                with justice to his memory among us, save possibly Worthen<ptr target="loc.00429_n1"
                />, or Joe Davis,<ptr target="n0185"/> and we cannot hope for anything from them.
                Therefore, the thought has occurred to me that if you would write a notice that
                would take up say not over half a column <handShift rend="manuscript"/>Publisher
                says you may take a whole column, <handShift rend="printed"/>(as it is very
                difficult, you know, in one of these engineering journals, to get more than this),
                if you would do this, I would attend to having it published in one of the
                engineering journals, and I know that it would be a very great satisfaction to his
                friends in the profession.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The death of Jeff has been a very great blow to me
                personally, as for a good many years I looked upon him as one of my warmest friends.
                Our association of the last four or five years has been constant, and very close,
                and I have learned to lean upon<pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00444.jpg"
                    type="verso"/><pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.00445.jpg" type="recto"/> him
                in so many ways that I feel as though a prop were taken out of my life by his
                death</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>I am sorry to have to write you a machine letter now, but
                my crippled arm makes this a necessity.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>If you agree with me, and are willing <handShift
                    rend="manuscript"/>and strong enough<handShift rend="printed"/> to furnish me
                the manuscript, I would suggest your doing it at once, as I shall be away from home
                after a few days, and besides that, it should be published as soon as possible.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/>Very truly yours,</salute>
                <signed>Horace Tarr</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.00446.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
