<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.08340"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">James W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 23 July 1891</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>James W. Wallace</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor> 
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.08340</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2022 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>James W. Wallace</author>
                    <title>James W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 23 July 1891</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1891-07-23" xml:id="dat1">July 23, 1891</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 18, Reel 11</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00402</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Wallace, James W." ref="n6121">James W. Wallace</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-02-15" who="#aja">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2021-11-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-10-15" who="#me">second check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-13" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-06-22" who="#cn">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_jm.00331.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Anderton, nr Chorley</name>
                    <name type="place">Lancashire, England</name>
                    <date when="1891-07-23">23. July. 1891</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Walt Whitman,</salute> 
            </opener>
            <p>I have to thank you for your kind postcard of July 14<hi rend="underline">th</hi>
                received this mg.<ptr target="loc.08340_n1"/> I note that you were "much the same considering, but badly
                depressed today." My heart goes out to you with yearning tenderness as I think
                of you sitting by the window, alone, weak &#38; ill. May God strengthen &#38; bless
                you &#38; fill your heart with cheer &#38; hope.</p>
            <p>I do wish to hear of your being able to get out
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_jm.00332.jpg" type="verso"/>
                again into the fresh open air, the breezes &#38; sunshine, &#38; the currents of life.
                But I, too, "hope for better things bye &#38; bye."</p>
            <p>The same mail brought me two letters from Traubel<ptr target="n4267"/> 
                &#38; his wife,<ptr target="loc.08060_n3"/> deeply touching in their wonderful kindness &#38; cordiality.
                It stirs my heart to its depths to feel&#8212;as I have had reason
                to feel lately&#8212;how warm &#38; vital is the comradeship of your friends &#38;
                lovers, aroused &#38; inspired by your example &#38; words. Supreme &#38;
                increasing love &#38; honour to you always.</p> 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_jm.00333.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/> has come &#38; gone.<ptr target="loc.08168_n2b"/>
                Last Wednesday &#38; Thursday. Johnston<ptr target="n4102"/> &#38; 
                I were "on pins" all the time, expecting a telegram from Queenstown.
                This, however, D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B. had no opportunity of sending.
                On Friday mg. Johnston rec<hi rend="underline">d</hi> a telegram from him
                saying he had arrived in Liverpool (11.45 Thursday night) &#38; would be 
                in Bolton at 11 oclock on Friday mg. Johnston &#38; I met him, recognising
                him immediately. We drove at once to Johnston's, discussing arrangements
                for the afternoon as we proceeded. It was settled that D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B. should drive
                with Johnston on one of 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_jm.00334.jpg" type="verso"/>
                his professional rounds, &#38; meet me in town for dinner. In the meantime
                I was to arrange for a drive in the afternoon &#38; beat up as many friends<ptr target="loc.04707_n3"/>
                as I could to accompany us. Seven of us met in all&#8212;Fred Wild,<ptr target="loc.04694_n2"/>
                Dixon,<ptr target="loc.02465_n4"/> Shorrock,<ptr target="loc.02448_n8"/> Hutton,<ptr target="loc.02454_n3"/> 
                Johnston, D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B &#38; self. It was a glorious
                afternoon, bright, hot &#38; slightly misty. We took what we consider
                the best &#38; most interesting drive in the district&#8212;in the hilly
                moorland country north of the town, (all <hi rend="underline">flat</hi>
                country south of Bolton) stopping eventually at the parsonage in Rivington,
                where Rev<hi rend="underline">d</hi> S. Thompson<ptr target="loc.04723_n4"/> gave us our tea.
                D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B had had no sleep during the two
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_jm.00335.jpg" type="recto"/>
                previous nights, &#38; was almost overpowered by his want of sleep &#38; by the heat.
                But he seemed to enjoy the drive. Thompson's quaint old fashioned garden
                interested him too, &#38; his quiet, simple, genuine hospitality. (Grown up son 
                &#38; daughter at home, M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi> Thompson<ptr target="loc.04723_n4b"/> away on a visit). 
                Johnston had <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#me" cert="high">brought</unclear> his camera, so took the opportunity, while we were in the garden
                to photograph the group, and D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Bucke alone.
                Then the drive to Bolton, Thompson accompanying us. Some of the friends 
                (engaged in business during the day) were awaiting us at Johnston's 
                &#38; we had a pretty full "College
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_jm.00336.jpg" type="verso"/>
                Meeting"&#8212; 3 being absent. We had no set programme, &#38; didn't attempt
                any elaborate speechifying, but had an ordinary social evening&#8212;<hi rend="underline">plus</hi> 
                two songs for the occasion by Dixon &#38; Johnston &#38; short speeches by 
                D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Bucke, Hutton &#38; self. D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B., 
                I believe, has given you an account of it all &#38; sent you a copy of W.D.'s song.<ptr target="loc.08340_n3"/></p>
            <p>Law<ptr target="loc.02511_n2"/> &#38; I stayed all night at Johnston's&#8212;Law leaving early next morning
                for business. It was agreed to come out here in the afternoon. Unfortunately 
                it proved to be the worst week end one could have chosen,&#8212;more than half 
                the friends having engagements wh. could not be postpon'd.
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_jm.00337.jpg" type="recto"/>
                So there were only 5 of us in all. We went to the bank near Rivington Lake
                (where we had our talk May 31<hi rend="underline">st</hi>,<ptr target="loc.02497_n5"/>
                &#38; of the view from which you have a picture) and there in the open air,
                D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B (seated on a camp-stool, with his back against a low stone wall, 
                the rest of us reclining on the grass round him) read us a paper on you
                wh. he intends to publish in a forthcoming book by himself &#38; Traubel,<ptr target="n4267"/> 
                &#38; which he proposes to call "Physiological Guarantees." It was an admirable paper,
                &#38; it was a great treat to us to hear it, though it contained little
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_jm.00338.jpg" type="verso"/>
                that was new. But it was a memorable &#38; never-to-be-forgotten pleasure to hear 
                D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B, your accepted "explicator," &#38; old personal friend
                give his matured conclusions about you &#38;your work. A little stammering
                talk about it after, &#38; then <hi rend="underline">here</hi> to tea. D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> J. 
                had to hurry off to catch the 6.23 train, the rest staying till 9.30. We spent the 
                interval in this room talking mainly about you, D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B. reading 
                passages from L. of G. &#38; I reading the "Song of the Universal" &#38; the "Prayer of Columbus."<ptr target="loc.08340_n4"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Sunday afternoon D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B. Johnston &#38; Dixon came out here 
                again, &#38; we spent a quiet afternoon.
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_jm.00339.jpg" type="recto"/>
                We had a short walk in the immediate neighbourhood, my father accompanying us.<ptr target="n6121b"/>
                Johnston &#38; Dixon went on to Rivington for Thompson who came here for tea.
                We had a quiet chat about different things including Mark Twain's<ptr target="ucb.00961_n2"/> "Huckleberry Finn"&#8212;
                from which I read one or two of D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B's favourite passages.</p>
            <p>On Monday morning I called at Johnston's &#38; drove with D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B 
                &#38; J. to the Town Hall, Market, Library, &#38;c&#8212;&#38; then to the Station, 
                D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B. going to London by the 11.21 train.</p>
            <p>The foregoing is a mere skeleton record of our proceedings without flesh &#38; blood, faint colors.
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_jm.00340.jpg" type="verso"/>
                But I write off hand &#38; hastily.</p>
            <p>No very special celebration, &#38; nothing of much importance said or done. 
                But a memorable &#38; deeply significant time to us all.</p>
            <p>It was a great thing to us to meet D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. Bucke, face to face, 
                to hear him talk &#38; to observe his living presence &#38; manner.</p>
            <p>It was an especial treat to hear him talk of <hi rend="underline">you</hi>,
                &#38; to observe how naturally he regards you as his exemplar in all things.</p>
            <p>He said a fine thing to me on Sunday&#8212;as we sat alone together in one of the country lanes
                here (waiting for D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. J. &#38; Dixon who had gone for Thom<supplied reason="tornaway" resp="#smb" cert="high">pson</supplied>).</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_jm.00341.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I don't remember his exact words, but they were something like these.</p>
            <p>"I put my Whitman work before everything else,&#8212;before my wife<ptr target="n4273"/> &#38; family even, 
                &#38; no one needs to wish a finer family than mine."</p>
            <p>(I) "But, of course, the two interests can't come into collision, but rather support each other."</p>
            <p>(D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B) "Well, of course. But if they <hi rend="underline">should</hi> clash,
                I should put Walt's interest before theirs, extravagant as it may seem to say so."</p>
            <p>Said quietly, simply, &#38; without special emphasis, &#38; quite incidentally,
                as of an old &#38; ever present principle of his life.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc_jm.00342.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>But far more significant &#38; interesting than anything D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> B. said or 
                did&#8212;specially&#8212;was the continual charm &#38; influence of his manner&#8212;the living 
                object lesson he afforded us of some of the results of your influence &#38; teaching.</p>
            <p>His manner of perfect &#38; easy equality with each &#38; all of us&#8212;no suspicion
                of superiority, or criticism, or ennui, but frank cheerful acceptance
                on equal terms of every one, of every thing said &#38; of every incident,
                his hearty comradeship, his instant enjoyment, frank boyish laughter, &#38; occasional 
                glimpses of the depths of affection, loyalty, &#38; reverence in him won all 
                our he<supplied reason="tornway" resp="#smb" cert="high">arts</supplied>.
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc_jm.00343.jpg" type="recto"/>
                Certainly I never met a man with whom I interchanged so soon &#38; so fully &#38; deeply.
                At our spree on Friday night I shook hands with him at the close of my little speech
                in token of his admission to our "College." I did it partly in jest,
                but it expressed a serious feeling (deepened since) that we regarded him
                as <hi rend="underline">one of us</hi>, one, that is, of the circle of our dearest friends,
                a brother beloved.</p>
            <p>When he comes to see us again, it will seem quite natural that he should do so, as natural
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc_jm.00344.jpg" type="verso"/>
                &#38; as welcome as sunshine &#38; fresh air. Sitting in this house he seemed as fitly in his place
                as a near relative might have done&#8212;&#38; as intimate &#38; close to our hearts.</p>
            <p>His very limitations (or what seem so) only endear him to us.
                For our own limitations are far greater&#8212;or narrower&#8212;&#38; it is good to feel
                that we have so great a brother to encourage us on the upward road where you stand supreme.</p>
            <p>But deeper than the pleasure, instruction, &#38; stimulus of his immediate presence,
                are the hopes &#38; aims his visit suggests for the future. It seems to me to admit us into the wide
                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc_jm.00345.jpg" type="recto"/>
                expanding brotherhood, whose glory &#38; privilege it will be, in different spheres &#38; in 
                varying degrees, to carry on your work. May God help us to indeed consecrate ourselves to the work.</p>
            <p>D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B. said on Friday night that he "only wished the old man were here." 
                But we felt that he was your representative, &#38; that, at least by proxy, you 
                <hi rend="underline">were</hi> with us. And I thank God, with all my heart, that even such a 
                connection existed between us.</p>
            <p>D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B. read portion of a letter from you aloud. I used to consider it a 
                sufficient compensation for all the obstructions &#38; troubles of my life, that I had written
                <hi rend="underline">one</hi> letter that I knew had pleased you. <hi rend="underline">Now</hi>, 
                I thank God, with a full heart, for all my privileges.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc_jm.00346.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. B. brought the canary<ptr target="loc.08056_n2c"/> safely. Johnston magnanimously brought over 
                here for <hi rend="underline">me</hi>, &#38; after D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Bucke's arbitration 
                I agreed to keep it. It is a very affecting &#38; precious souvenir of you to me. Thanks &#38; God 
                bless you.</p>
            <p>I expect two or three of the friends here tomorrow&#8212;D<hi rend="underline">r</hi>. J. 
                Fred Wild &#38; Greenhalgh.<ptr target="loc.02465_n5"/> G. is bringing some lads to a farm here 
                for an afternoon in a field.</p>
            <p>Showery weather all week usually clearing up in the afternoon or towards evening.
                Beautiful afternoon &#38; evening today&#8212;fine cloud &#38; atmospheric effects&#8212;&#38; the 
                air deliciously fresh, sweet, &#38; bracing (wind right off the sea).</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>A good night to you this night. And loving thoughts &#38; wishes for all morrows.</salute>
                <signed>J. W. Wallace</signed>  
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 
