<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.02867">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 14 July 1872</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.02867</idno></publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <!--<biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Garden City, New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1964">1918</date>
                            <biblScope unit="page">82&#8211;84</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>--> 
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 14 July 1872</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1872-07-14" xml:id="dat1">July 14, 1872</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS45443, Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms002007.mss45443.0111</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842–1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-07-28" who="#aja">updated image pointers</change>
            <change when="2022-05-05" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-10-12" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-02-18" who="#cn">checked, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2021-11-23" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-30">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-05-25" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-18" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-04-10" who="#al">checked with microfilm images</change>
            <change when="2011-08-05" who="#zk">transcribed and encoded from Harned; annotated AG and family, Strong Bird, Han, Rossetti, Stanley</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_cb.00106.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">50 Marquis Rd.</name>
                    <name type="place">Camden Sq. London.</name>
                    <date when="1872-07-14" rend="right">July 14/72</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>The 3d July was my rejoicing day, dearest Friend,—the day the packet from America reached me 
                scattering for a while the clouds of pain and humiliation &amp; filling me through &amp; through 
                with light &amp; warmth: indeed I believe I am often as happy reading as you were writing your Poems. 
                The long new one "As a Strong Bird"<ptr target="loc.02867_n1"/> of itself answers the question hinted 
                in your preface &amp; 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_cb.00112.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                nobly <choice><sic>fulfils</sic><corr>fulfills</corr></choice> the promise of its opening lines. 
                We want again &amp; again in fresh words &amp; from 
                the new impetus &amp; standpoint of new days the vision that sweeps ahead, the tones that fill us with
                faith &amp; joy in our present share of life &amp; work—prophetic of the splendid issues. It does 
                not need to be American born to believe &amp; passionately rejoice in the belief of what is preparing 
                in America. It is for humanity. And it
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_cb.00113.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                comes through England. The noblest souls the most heroic hearts of England were called to be the nucleus 
                of the race that, (enriched with the blood &amp; qualities of other races &amp; planted down in the new 
                half of the world reserved in all its fresh beauty &amp; exhaustless riches to be the arena) is to 
                <choice><sic>fulfil</sic><corr>fulfill</corr></choice> 
                justify outstrip the vision of the Poets, the quenchless aspirations of all the ardent souls that never 
                ever struggled forward upon this earth.
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_cb.00107.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                For me, the most precious page in the book is that which contains the Democratic Souvenirs.<ptr target="loc.02867_n9"/>
                I respond to that as one to whom it means the life of her Soul. It comforts me very much. You speak in the Preface 
                of the imperious &amp; resistless command from within out of which Leaves of Grass issued. This carried 
                with it no doubt the secret of a corresponding resistless power over the reader wholly unprecedented 
                unapproached in literature as I believe, &amp; to be compared
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_cb.00115.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                only with that of Christ. I speak out of my own experience when I say that no Myth, no "miracle" embodying 
                the notion of a direct communication between God &amp; a human creature, goes beyond the effect soul 
                &amp; body, of those Poems on me: &amp; that were I to put into oriental forms of speech what I experienced 
                it would read like one of those old "miracles" or "myths. Thus of many things that used to appear to me 
                incomprehensible lies, I now 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_cb.00116.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                perceive the germ of truth &amp; understand that what was called the supernatural was merely an inadequate 
                &amp; too timid way of conceiving the natural.—Had I died the following year, it would have been the 
                simple truth to say I died of joy. The doctor called it nervous exhaustion falling with tremendous violence 
                on the heart which "seemed to have been strained": &amp; was much puzzled how that could have come to pass. 
                I left him in his puzzle, but it was none to me—How could such 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_cb.00117.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                a dazzling radiance of light flooding the soul, suddenly kindling it to such an intense life, but put a 
                tremendous strain on the vital organs? how could the muscles of the heart suddenly grow adequate to such 
                new work—O the passionate tender gratitude that flooded my breast, the yearning that seemed to strain 
                the heart beyond endurance that I might repay with all my life &amp; soul &amp; body This debt—that 
                I might give joy to him who filled me with such joy, that I might make his outward life sweeter &amp; more 
                beautiful 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_cb.00114.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                who made my inner life so divinely sweet &amp; beautiful. But, dear Friend, I have learnt to see that this 
                is not to be so, now: that for me too love &amp; death are folded inseparably together: Death that will renew 
                my youth.</p>
            <p>I have had the paper from Burlington<ptr target="loc.02867_n2"/>—with the details a woman likes so to 
                have. I wish I had known for certain whether you went on to Boston &amp; were enjoying the music there. My 
                youngest boy<ptr target="n0262"/> has gone to spend his holiday with his brother<ptr target="n2000"/> in South Wales &amp; 
                he writes me such good news of Per. that he is "looking as brown as a nut &amp; 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_cb.00108.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                very jolly" &amp; his home in a "clean airy old farm house half way up a mountain in the midst of wild rough 
                grand scenery, &amp; the sea in sight near enough to hear the sound of it about as loud as the rustling of 
                "leaves"—so the boys will have a good time together, and the girls<ptr target="upa.00165_n5"/> are going with me for the holiday to 
                their grandmother at Colne. W. Rossetti<ptr target="loc.02867_n5"/> does not take his till October this year. 
                I suppose it will be long &amp; long before this letter reaches 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_cb.00109.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                you as you will be gone to California—may it be a time full of enjoyment—full to the Brim.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good-bye dearest Friend</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>What a noble achievement is Mr. Stanley's:<ptr target="loc.02867_n7"/> it fills me with pleasure that Americans
                    should thus have been the rescuer of our large hearted heroic traveller. We have just got his letters 
                    with account of the five races in Central Africa copied from N. Y. Herald, July<ptr target="loc.02867_n8"/> 29.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>