<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03968">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Harry Stafford to Walt Whitman, 21 April 1877</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Harry Stafford</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="vm">Vince Moran</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ab">Alicia Bones</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03968</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
              
                <bibl>
                    <author>Harry Stafford</author>
                    <title>Harry Stafford to Walt Whitman, 21 April 1877</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1877-04-21" xml:id="dat1">April 21, 1877</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
               
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Stafford, Harry">Harry Stafford</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-03-06" who="#ss">annotations added</change>
            <change when="2013-02-03" who="#ab">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-25" who="#ej">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-10-26" who="#vm">transcribed, encoded</change>
         </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00109.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Camden, New Jersey.</name>
                    <date when="1877-04-21">April 21, 1877.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>

            <p>Spring has at last commenced.<ptr target="n0590"/> The buds are out on the trees, the early flowers are in bloom, the days have grown to a much greater length, the fields of rye and wheat show their beautiful carpet of emerald, the farmers are busy planting their corn and potatoes, and all Nature exhibits the plainest <choice><sic>evidencs</sic><corr>evidences</corr></choice> that the delightful season for flowers, vegetables, fruits, grains, and the foliage of Summer is again commencing.</p>
           
            <p>Common as it is in the experience of every one of us, nothing is more wonderful than the annual return of spring: The dead ground awakening by some mysterious process to all the miracles of life is a spectacle, common as it is, not surpassed in all the infinite processes of the Universe.</p>
            
            <p>Amid these wonders and glories, the passions and ambitions of mankind and the objects of their pride and eagerness seem artificial and petty. There is a healthy and elevating lesson in studying the spring.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.00110.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>Saturday evening, end of the week</p> 
            
            <p>We have had a couple of rainy <choice><sic>Apriel</sic><corr>April</corr></choice>. It is now a fine evening, partially clear, with an <choice><sic>occasionals</sic><corr>occasional</corr></choice> gust of wind, it and the moon at times shining out brightly. Mr Whitman and I are sitting here in the room <choice><sic>togeather</sic><corr>together</corr></choice>; he is reading the New York Herald, and I am writing these lines for exercise for exercise. To day we received a newspaper from our friend the artist George Waters<ptr target="n0685"/> of Elmira N.Y. It contained an article on W. W. portrait, painted by Mr. Waters during our late visit to New York; also an interesting extract from the last letter <choice><sic>writen</sic><corr>written</corr></choice> by our lamented hostess, the very day before her sudden death. Of <choice><sic>corse</sic><corr>course</corr></choice> we were glad to <choice><sic>here</sic><corr>hear</corr></choice> from our friend, though the newspaper and letter brought up some very sad recollections</p>
            
            <p>On Monday next I expect to commence work <choice><sic>a gain</sic><corr>again</corr></choice> at the printing of the West Jersey Press.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours,</salute>
                <signed>Harry Stafford.</signed>
            </closer> 

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00111.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
	     <postscript><p><date when="1877-04-21" rend="right">Sunday April 22 1877.</date></p>
            
	     <p>It is a beautiful morning and you are feeling well and hearty. My friend and I, he says, have had a happy night and morning. I am bound for Kirkwood in the next train</p></postscript>
            
	     <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00112.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
	     </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>
