<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01096">
    <teiHeader>  
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Edward Bertz to Walt Whitman, 20–22 July 1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Edward Bertz</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.01096</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Edward Bertz</author>
                    <title>Edward Bertz to Walt Whitman, 20–22 July 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" notBefore="1889-07-20" notAfter="1889-07-22" xml:id="dat1">July 20–22, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 4</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                    Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>   
            <particDesc>  
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Bertz, Edward" ref="n4193">Edward Bertz</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-03-13" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2017-07-21" who="#if">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2017-01-25" who="#cb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-10-11" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01096.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>Deutscher
                            Schriftstellerverband</name><ptr target="loc.01096_n1"/>
                        <name type="place">Bezirtsverein I, Berlin. Dorstand.</name>
                        <name type="place"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>Lagow,</name>
                        <date when="1889-07-20">July 20th, <handShift rend="printed"/>18<handShift rend="manuscript"/>89.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Your card and, some days later, the gift of your Complete Works<ptr target="n4192"/>, as well as the
                    parcel of pamphlets and papers you sent me, safely reached me here in the
                    country where I am spending my summer holidays, and whence I shall return to
                    Potsdam in the beginning of August.<ptr target="loc.01096_n2"/> Your card alone would have been a great
                    treasure; but to receive, out of your own kind hands, that glorious book with
                    your personal dedication, your portraits, and those various materials which
                    confirm what had always been my impression of your character, is more to me than
                    words of gratitude could express. So I <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01096.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>will only say: Thank you
                    heartily. To think that some words of mine brought a pleased smile upon the lips
                    of a great and good man, adds something priceless to the value of my life.</p> 
                <p>My article was hastily written and, though you do acknowledge my good intentions,
                    must seem very inadequate to you. But for years it has been my aim some day to
                    write an exhaustive essay worthy, as far as it may be in my power, of your work
                    and genius. Now your personal touch, if I may say so, has given me a new
                    impulse, and I am resolved to set to work at once. If life and strength lasts,
                    this pen of mine shall help to reveal you to the German people.</p>
                <p>When I wrote that paper for the "Deutsche Presse," I did not know of the
                    translation published at Zürich, of which you speak. <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01096.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>But I got it since then and
                    brought it here with me. I came here, together with a medical man, Dr. Rehfeldt,<ptr target="loc.01096_n3"/> my faithful
                    friend since our common school days, and we are staying in a retired spot which
                    belongs to the most picturesque in Northern Germany. The house is situated high
                    in a garden from which we overlook two deep, quiet lakes, surrounded by hills
                    clad with beach and pine forests. On our island between them clusters the hamlet
                    of Lagow, at the foot of an ancient castle. My friend has his wife and children
                    with him. Every evening when these my little favourites have gone to sleep, we
                    light the lamp under an old lime tree in the garden, and then we call you to
                    keep us company. The other night I translated to my friends pp. 5 to 11 from Mr.
                        O'Connor's<ptr target="n2002"/> "Vindication", and they were deeply moved.
                    The wife whose <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01096.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>spiritual beauty would gladden your heart, instructed me to send you her love.
                    Generally my friend reads the translation while I compare the English text. So
                    Messrs. Knortz<ptr target="uva.00476_n1"/> and Rolleston<ptr target="n1027"/>
                    have found in us a rather critical public. In many places the rendering is
                    excellent, and faithfully mirrors the beauty and power of your thoughts,
                    eliciting warm praise from Rehfeldt and his lady. In not a few instances, however, we also
                    noticed mistakes which sometimes will make it hard to grasp your meaning, for
                    those who cannot read the original. No doubt you are aware that it is very
                    difficult to translate you; frequently the entire originality of your language
                    seems to defy its being moulded into different forms. I have often experienced
                    it in my own attempts at translating you; for I was never quite satisfied with
                    the result. In any case there is not, in the German translation, that grand
                    harmony by which the original <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01096.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>is distinguished, and it
                    certainly does not reach the perfection of those examples Freiligrath<ptr target="n0248"/> has given us of your work. But to translate a poet, another
                    poet is required, and I think that some day he will appear who will do justice
                    to you even in German. However, everything considered, it is a careful and
                    diligent book Messrs. Knortz and Rolleston have given us, and as pioneering work
                    it is most welcome.</p>
                <p>To avoid mistakes, I think I ought to tell you that I am living as an independant
                    literary man, and am not constantly the editor of the "Deutsche Presse," but was
                    so only temporarily, because of a severe illness of the regular editor. However,
                    since last autumn I am entrusted with the honorary office of first secretary in
                    the Society of German authors, a position the duties of which keep me very busy
                    indeed. I am also a member<pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01096.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> of the "Verein Berliner Presse," and though quietly living at
                    Potsdam, I have to go to Berlin about twice or three times every week.</p>
                <p>Perhaps you did not know of the passages characterizing your mind and work which,
                    in my article, I have translated from "Thyrza."<ptr target="loc.01096_n4"/> The author of this book, the
                    English novelist George Gissing, is one of my very best friends. I knew him from
                    my first coming to England, in 1878, and passed with him, in common studies and
                    aspirations, some rich and fruitful years of companionship and curious
                    Bohemianism, and our correspondence, since my coming back to Germany, was never
                    interrupted. I made him acquainted with your works, after my return from
                    America, and it is my own experience he has related in "Thyrza": his hero's
                    getting to know "Leaves of Grass" during his American life, and coming home a
                    new man.</p>     
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01096.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p>I spent two years in America, from 1881 to 1883, at Rugby, Tennessee, the English
                    colony of Thomas Hughes.<ptr target="loc.01096_n6"/> My health had broken down from overwork, and making the
                    personal acquaintance of the author of "Tom Brown's School Days," I was induced
                    to join his settlement, since I urgently needed a change of air. The sea voyage
                    did me much good, and when I arrived at Rugby, I was well enough to help for a
                    month or two in nursing those English young fellows who, after coming out to
                    Tennessee, were most of them attacked by typhoid fever. A number died, and when
                    the others recovered I went into the wilderness. But though I acquired a hundred
                    acres of forest land, and got a good house erected there in a solitary and
                    romantic spot, all of which is still my property, my farming came to nothing, as
                    I longed to get back to my studies, as soon as I had got well again in the rough
                    and healthy <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01096.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    forest life. Seven squatter's children came to me every morning with their
                    spelling-books, and I amused myself with teaching them the three R's, still snow
                    blocked the roads. Then I passed the winter in complete solitude, reading
                    Shakespeare and the ancient classics, with no companion save a fine collie dog I
                    had brought over with me from England. In the spring of 1882, the trustees of
                    the "Hughes Public Library" which, in honour of Tom Hughes, had been founded at
                    Rugby by the publishers of Boston, New York, and Philadelphia, offered me the
                    post of librarian, and I accepted it for a year, during which time I had to
                    arrange and to catalogue the whole library.</p> 
                <p>Your works were not among the donations; but reading about you in the "Critic"
                    paper, I believe, which was regularly sent to the library, I ordered "Leaves of
                    Grass" from Cincinnati, and from the very first I recognized your geniune
                    greatness, and loved you with all my heart. However, with a<pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.01096.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/> whole library at my disposal,
                    in which hundreds and hundreds of books were new to me and attracted my
                    curiosity, I was not then in a position to enter very deeply into anything, but
                    rather tasted of everything, and I may say the seeds that fell into my heart
                    when first reading you, have grown to maturity only after my return to Europe
                    when I found time quietly to digest what I had hastily swallowed.</p>
                <p>I did not want to stay in America, as I felt that my real work lay in Europe with
                    which I was most strongly connected by personal and intellectual ties. So in
                    June, 1883, I went back first to England, and, about a year after that, to
                    Germany. But before leaving, I spent a fortnight in New York, and there I
                    purchased "Specimen Days and Collect,"<ptr target="n4121"/> so that your complete works, as far as
                    they were then published, accompanied me to Europe.</p> 
                <p>Since then I have been leading the<pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.01096.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/> life of a literary man. In
                    1884 I wrote an English book, entitled "The French Prisoners",—the story
                    of a friendship between a German boy and a young French soldier. It was
                    published by Messrs. Macmillan &amp; Co., of London, and rather well received by
                    criticism. One of its chapters is headed by a motto from "Leaves of Grass",
                    orig.: "Beautiful thought, beautiful as the sky, that war and all its deeds of
                    carnage must in time for even be lost."<ptr target="loc.01096_n7"/> In the following year I published, at
                    Leipzig, a German translation of Montesquieu's "Lettres persanes,"<ptr target="loc.01096_n8"/> with
                    commentary and critical introduction. In the latter I have also mentioned
                    you.</p> 
                <p>But I may say I am still in the beginning of my literary career. After finishing
                    that translation, I devoted about three years to extensive studies, writing very
                    little, and it seems to me that only then I acquired what I may perhaps regard
                    as my maturity. Now during the last<pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.01096.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/> year I have written a number
                    of long articles on literary matters, for various papers, and I had the
                    satisfaction that almost every one of them brought me letters of approval and
                    gifts of books from authors. All that is very encouraging and assures me in the
                    hope that I may in time do some really good work. Having devoted much industry
                    and thought to the study of philosophy, social science, and literature, I was
                    able to form an independent opinion on many things; and as my highest aim in
                    writing is truth, I have come to believe that there is some important work to do
                    for my pen. And I trust you will find it is no unworthy advocate that is going
                    to interpret you to the Germans. You will not wonder, of course, if I tell you
                    that in many respects I am opposed to the spirit now current in the German
                    empire. I am not a fighting man by nature, but as an author I feel in <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.01096.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>duty bound to
                    defend with unflagging energy what is highest in life and literature, and I
                    would rather be silent forever than to foster anything mean and unjust.</p>  
              <p><date rend="right" when="1889-07-22">July 22nd, 1889.</date></p>
                <p>Yesterday your gift of Dr. Bucke's<ptr target="n0119"/> book arrived, as well as,
                    from Mr. Knortz of New York, his German lecture about you. Thank you from all my
                    heart for the kind and welcome help you are giving me in the work that is now
                    before me: for indeed all those materials will make my task much more easy. But,
                    besides being a help, Mr. Bucke's book contains much, very much that is new to
                    me and a key to your work and character. And, beyond all that, everything that
                    comes from you is sanctified, and words cannot express what it means to me.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.01096.013_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p>I have written this very long letter because I felt it due to you to tell you
                    something of the disciple who was so kindly received by you. Perhaps, as my work
                    progresses, it will please you to hear now and then how I am getting on. But of
                    course no answer will be needed, since it is quite sufficient to me to imagine
                    that my lines come to you like a pleasant visitor.</p>
                <p>By-the-by, there was a delay in sending you my article, because I did not know in
                    what city you are living. After some weeks only, seeing from a paragraph in the
                    London "Athenaeum" that you had been present at the celebration of your birthday
                    in Camden, New Jersey,<ptr target="loc.03027_n4"/> I concluded that you were dwelling there.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.01096.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <p>Now good-bye for this once, my dear friend and Master. I send you my sincere
                    goodwishes for the improvement of your health and strength. Some weeks ago my
                    old grandparents, after sixty years marriage, celebrated their diamond wedding.
                    My grandfather who last year had been so ill that hardly any hope remained for
                    his life, walks now about again and reads all day long, and is as ardent and
                    radical a politician as ever, though now past eighty-six: I trust you too, like
                    him, will grow quite strong again.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Ever yours reverently, gratefully, and affectionately,</salute>
                    <signed>Edward Bertz.</signed>
                </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc.01096.015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc.01096.016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc.01096.017_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc.01096.018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>