<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.02265">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Albert C. Hopkins to Walt Whitman, 14 March 1892</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Albert C. Hopkins</author> 
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor> 
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>
                    National Historical Publications and Records Commission
                </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02265</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>
                        Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Albert C. Hopkins</author>
                    <title>Albert C. Hopkins to Walt Whitman, 14 March 1892</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1892-03-14" xml:id="dat1">March 14, 1892</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName> 
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 10, Reel 6</idno> 
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00206</idno>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>  
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="unk"><persName key="Unknown">Unknown</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key= "Hopkins, Albert C." ref="loc.02265_n2">Albert C. Hopkins</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName> 
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-15" who="#smb">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2021-09-21" who="#aja">2nd check, notes</change>
            <change when="2021-07-19" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-10-07" who="#cn">transcribed, encoded</change> 
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02265.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">#42 Pine Park Chicago Ill.<ptr target="loc.02265_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1892-03-12">12. March 1892</date>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Mr. Walt Whitman</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Camden N.J.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Comrade:&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I notice that the press still reports you feeble, and I am constrained to write you, 
                thinking that a cheery hail in memory of old days from even an unknown comrade may
                comfort you.</p>
            <p>True, we are all comrades in the largish sense, and all go one road, but that
                comradeship of war and war's suffering and privations makes closer if not truer union.</p>
            <p>It may interest you to hear that we have formed a temporary society which we hope to soon
                make
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02265.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                permanent. devoted to the pansy, the children's flower for the national emblem of the United States.
                The motto is "Union, Culture and Peace."</p>
            <p> We hope to secure its adoption by Congress and its official establishment in the Union Flag
                as an outline setting setting for the stars, the centre representing the Central government
                or Capital, from which radiate in the white outlines of the leaves and dark blue pencilings 
                of the flower, "light, order, land."</p>
            <p>We mean to do this in time to make it a conspicuous feature of the world's Colmbin. Exptin.<ptr target="loc.02469_n8"/></p>
            <p>Unless we greatly overestimate the strength and fitness of our cause, we shall on July 4<hi rend="underline">th</hi>
                1893, march an all&#8211;union army of a hundred thousand children with pansy&#8211;bud caps and pansy
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.02265.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                banners, badges, gloves and belts, into the open gates of The World's Columbian Exposition, and replace the 
                present awkward and unmeaning union of The Flag, with the star&#8212;pansy union, and sing, to war's
                of Bethlehem, a new Peace Anthem of America, thus making, with the time and place, the most imposing
                and memorable pageant of Union, Culture and Peace, of universal fellowship and human progress
                in the history of the world.</p>
            <p>I shall be glad if you are able to see it with your material eyes, and, if not, why then from the other shore,
                with clearer vision, perhaps.</p>
            <p>The argument for the pansy appeared in the October number of The Kindergarten, 1890, Pan the Piper, 
                and in the 4<hi rend="underline">th</hi> July number of America 1891
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.02265.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                A Place for The Pansy. These are both Chicago publications.</p> 
            <p>The Illst'd. Home Journal is likely to have a more complete argument in a short time.</p>
            <p>The full argument for that star Pansy Flag, has been sent The Youth's Companion<ptr target="loc.04511_n2"/> and, I hope, 
                may appear soon with an illustration of it. We have just ordered what we think a very pretty zinc etching
                for letter heads and envelopes for the society, showing the flag and a spray of Pansies.</p>
            <p>Pardon me if I am making this worrisome. Of course, I'm a Crank on this particular subject.</p>
            <p>I hope you may escape serious suffering, and I presume you have no doubt, as I have none, of your assured place in 
                history and literature
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.02265.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                This is our summing up in three lines of the present and future of the world.</p>
            <lg type="poem">
                <l>"In the bright blue Pan's eye awakes:</l> 
                <l>No darkest land God's light forsakes:</l> 
                <l>O'er all the world, Christ's morning breaks."</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And still, "The man is ruler of the dark."</p>
            <p>The eye of Pan, the fairy, the All&#8211;God. "Keeps watch and ward above his own."</p>
            <p>Whatever valley of shadows you may be called upon to pass, go bravely with full trust&#8212;"the
                heights where morning shines" and safe and sure and permanent beyond.</p>
            <p>Though I have never seen you, I hail you friend and comrade well met.</p> 
            <closer>
                <signed>Albert C. Hopkins Pres. Protem.</signed> 
                <address>
                    <addrLine>The Pansy Society of America</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Comrade G.A.R. Post #132</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Nashua Ia</addrLine>
                </address>   
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02265.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02265.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>   
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.02265.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.02265.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.02265.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.02265.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.02265.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="bottom" resp="#ht">(over)</note>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ht"><p>The full argument for The Pansy is promised in The apl. number of The Illst'd. Home Journal</p> 
                <p>H.</p></note>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#unk">c 1892</note>
        </body> 
    </text>
</TEI>


