<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03828">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Logan Pearsall Smith to Walt Whitman, 29 December
                    1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Logan Pearsall Smith</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03828</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Logan Pearsall Smith</author>
                    <title>Logan Pearsall Smith to Walt Whitman, 29 December 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-12-29" xml:id="dat1">December 29, 1890</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Smith, Logan Pearsall" ref="n6122">Logan Pearsall
                        Smith</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-12-08" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_jc.00159_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>Alpenkurort</name>
                    <name type="place">GRINDELWALD</name>
                    <name type="place">Open the whole year round</name>
                    <name type="place">Ouvert toute l'ann&#233;e</name>
                    <name type="place">HOTEL ET PENSION DE L'OURS (<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Bear</hi>)</name>
                    <name type="place">J. BOSS, Propri&#233;taire</name>
                    <date when="1890-12-29"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>Dec. 29th 1890</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear W. Whitman</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>This is rather late I am afraid to wish you a Merry Christmas&#8212;or even a happy
                New Year&#8212;but I had forgotten all about Christmas till it was on me. I have
                come here to Switzerland to have a little winter, such as one gets in America, the
                winter in England is a poor affair generally, but I see in the papers that it is
                cold enough there now. My family live happily in London, though it is always fog
                there when there is frost&#8212;I should think they would choke, but they seem to
                like it. But I don't, so<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_jc.00160_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> I packed up my books and came here. In summer Grindewald is one
                of the most crowded of the Swiss places but now, in the winter there are only a few
                people, almost all English, who came here for the skating and courting. We are in a
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#ktl">hole</unclear>, surrounded
                by tremendous mountains, and the sun has not yet got high enough to shine in yet.
                The wind never blows, but we have day after day of clear cold weather, when one
                feels so well and strung. We have a very jolly party&#8212;five or six people from
                Oxford&#8212;a master from one of the great English schools with one of his boys, an
                English member of Parliament or two, and several ladies.</p>

            <p>The Costelloes have gone to Italy and Alys<ptr target="loc.05908_n1"/> with them, and
                they write that they are having a most delightful time there among the churches and
                pictures. Alys is going to stay on a month &amp; learn Italian &amp; then in
                February she is going to Sicily with my mother.</p>
            <p>The "Parnell Crisis" has been the one great topic of late. At first we feared that
                Home Rule was dead, but now, since the election at Kilkenny, things are looking<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_jc.00161_large.jpg" type="recto"/> better, and it
                may not be so bad after all. But it has been most exciting&#8212;certainly the Irish
                make politics dramatic. It always seems to be the unexpected that occurs. Mrs.
                    Costelloe<ptr target="loc.02189_n1"/> does a great deal of speaking, and is
                getting quite a name.</p>
            <p>How did you like the American elections? I was <hi rend="underline">delighted</hi> it
                seems to me that the time has come for the Republicans to go. All my American
                friends&#8212;young men who have gone in for politics&#8212;are <unclear
                    reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#ktl">washing</unclear> with the
                Democratic party.</p>
            <p>Your books were so much appreciated in Oxford, and that great one you sent my father
                is certainly a royal book. Are you writing anything else?</p>
            <p>I wish I had got this letter off in time to wish you a happy Christmans&#8212;but you
                must accept my somewhat tardy letter as if it had come earlier.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>ever yours with love</salute>
                <signed>Logan Pearsall Smith</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_jc.00162_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
