<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?> 
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.05902">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 27 February
                    1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.05902</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="tbh">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &#38; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">233&#8211;235</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 27 February 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-02-27" xml:id="dat1">February 27, 1885</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 10, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-03-10" who="#smb">final check</change>
            <change when="2015-05-26" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-02-21" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2015-01-29" who="#ss">encoded based on Harned</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body> 
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><hi rend="italic">Keats Comer</hi></name>
                    <name type="place"><hi rend="italic">Hampstead, England </hi></name>
                    <date when="1885-02-27"><hi rend="italic">Feb</hi>. 27, '85.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>How has the winter passed with you I wonder? Me it has
                imprisoned very much with bronchial &#38; asthmatic troubles&#8212;and the four
                walls of the house &#38; the ceiling seem to close in upon one's spirit as well as
                one's body, all too much. I hope you have been able to wend to and fro daily on the
                great ferry boats &#38; enjoy the beautiful broad river &#38; the sky &#38; the
                throngs of people as of old&#8212;you are in my thoughts as constantly as ever,
                though I have been so silent. Percy<ptr target="n2000"/> &#38; his wife<ptr
                    target="loc.05902_n1"/> &#38; the little son spent some weeks with us at
                Christmas &#38; now they have taken a house quite near, into which they will be
                moving in a week or two. I can't tell you what a dear, affectionate, reasonable,
                companionable little fellow Archie is&#8212;now six years old. Perhaps you will have
                seen in the American papers that Sidney Thomas, the cousin with whom Percy was
                associated in the discovery of the Basic process, is dead<ptr target="loc.05902_n2"
                />&#8212;he spent his strength too freely&#8212;wore himself out at 35&#8212;he was
                much loved by all with whom he had to do. His mother &#38; sister have been watching
                &#38; hoping against hope &#38; taking him to warm climates, he himself full of
                hope&#8212;the mind bright and active to the last&#8212;&#38; now he is
                gone&#8212;&#38; his eldest brother died only two months before him.&#8212;I cannot
                help grieving over public affairs too&#8212;never in my lifetime has old England
                been in such a bad way&#8212;no honest &#38; capable man seemingly to take the
                helm&#8212;&#38; what Carlyle<ptr target="n0139"/> was fond of describing as the
                attempt to guide the ship by the shouts of the bystanders on shore&#8212;the
                newspapers &#38;c. prospering very ill. A government that tries perpetually how to
                do it and how not to do it at the same moment! The best comfort is that I do not
                think there is any, the smallest sign, of deterioration in the English race; so we
                shall pull through somehow, after tremendous disasters. How many things should I
                like to sit and chat with you about, dear Walt&#8212;above all to see you again! I
                could not get my article into any of the magazines I most wished. I believe it is
                coming out in <hi rend="italic">To-Day</hi>. Giddy<ptr target="n0890"/> was so
                pleased at your sending her a paper&#8212;a very capital article too it is of Miss
                    Kellogg.<ptr target="n0186"/> I was interested also in a little paragraph I
                found about Pullman town, near Chicago, which confirmed my suspicion that it was not
                a thing with healthy roots&#8212;but only a benevolent despotism. I am seeing a good
                deal of your socialists just now&#8212;&#38; I confess that though they mean well, I
                think they have less sense in their heads than any people I ever saw.</p>
            <p>I am going to pay a little visit to those friends (friendliest of friends) who live
                on the lonely top of a heath-covered hill&#8212;with such an outlook, such wooded
                slopes and broad valleys&#8212;and the storms travelling up hours before they
                arrive&#8212;such sweeps of sunshine too!&#8212;&#38; they mean to drive me about
                till I am quite strong again. So the next letter I write, dear Friend, shall be more
                cheery. I am afraid to look back lest this one should read too grumbly to send. I
                don't feel grumbly however&#8212;only shut in. Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> has been
                working hard at getting up an exhibition here to help along our Public Library. It
                is so very hard to stir up anything like public spirit &#38; unity of action in
                London or its suburbs&#8212;I suppose because of its vastness&#8212;&#38; alas! also
                the social cliques &#38; gentilities &#38; snobbishnesses.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good-bye, dearest Walt, with love from all.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
