<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04300">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Sarah Tyndale to Walt Whitman, 1 July 1857</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Sarah Tyndale</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lc">Lauren Claeys</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="em">Erel Michaelis</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie M. Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04300</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Sarah Tyndale</author>
                    <title>Sarah Tyndale to Walt Whitman, 1 July 1857</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1857-07-01" xml:id="dat1">July 1, 1857</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 17; Reel 10&#8211;11</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00394</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Tyndale, Sarah" ref="duk.00424_n19b">Sarah Tyndale</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-21" who="#smb">final notes</change>
            <change when="2022-06-22" who="#kjb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-13" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-06" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-28" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-11-14" who="#lc">transcribed, encoded; SLIS:6335: Metadata Theories
                and Applications Class, Fall 2020, Micah Bateman, Lecturer, University of
                Iowa</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00695_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Germantown</name>
                    <date when="1857-07-01">7 mo 1&#8212;57</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received yours of the 29th last evening and hasten to comply with your request. a
                friend in the City will send you a check today for fifty Dollars Hector<ptr
                    target="duk.00424_n18"/> would be very glad to do it, but he left the City last
                monday.</p>
            <p>I will help to pray for the good time which you evidently think is in reserve for
                you, I am quite sure it is&#8212;we all have times of groping in the dark but there
                is always enough light to find the true way, one thing has never failed me, that is
                to do <hi rend="underline">this</hi> moment whatever my best judgment says I ought
                to do, and every succeeding hour and day it becomes easier to follow the same plan,
                in that way I have been <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.00696_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/> enabled to overcome difficulties which many many times looked to
                be quite impassable. I never put off for tomorrow what ought to be done to day.</p>
            <p>Am I writing a homily? I did not intend it. I know you will excuse me for apparently <choice>
                    <sic>medling</sic>
                    <corr>meddling</corr>
                </choice> with your business I can not help it perhaps as I feel so great an
                interest in the success of Leaves of Grass. I was thinking yesterday of the
                difficulty you must have in having the work published, it is so ultra
                the publishers and it <choice>
                    <sic>occured</sic>
                    <corr>occurred</corr>
                </choice> to me that it was quite possible that Mr Arnold<ptr target="pml.00016_n7"/> or Mr Verner<ptr target="n5001"/> (I believe they have a press) could do it. With
                this hint I leave the subject to your better judgment</p>
            <p>Mrs Walton<ptr target="n5001"/> has some means and I think would be willing to assist
                in <choice>
                    <sic>geting</sic>
                    <corr>getting</corr>
                </choice> out the work, entrenous.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00697_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I received a letter yesterday from a friend who stated that he had just received a
                letter from Worcester, in which the writer says, that Mr Alcot<ptr target="n0741"/>
                says, Walter Whitman is about to publish another edition of Leaves of Grass, leaving
                out all the <hi rend="underline">objectionable</hi> parts, my friend in reply said
                he had understood that you intended no such thing. but intended to leave out every
                thing but your own poems.</p>
            <p>He that receives the inspiration knows the best, but I with all my ultra radicalism
                would be delighted if some of the expressions were left out, the pictures are too <choice>
                    <sic>vived</sic>
                    <corr>vivid</corr>
                </choice> in some instances. where it seems to me that common instinct seeks
                privacy, at the same time the entire nakedness of the intercourse is rather
                calculated to increase libidinousness in weak minds which Heaven knows is
                frightfully rampant, I feel constrained to treat all subjects of thought equally <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00698_large.jpg" type="verso"/> free and <choice>
                    <sic>dispationately</sic><corr>dispassionately</corr></choice>, but distrust the good effect of dwelling upon the rapture <choice>
                    <sic>consiquent</sic>
                    <corr>consequent</corr>
                </choice> upon the indulgence of any of the appetites I detest drinking songs,&#38;
                poems on the delight of eating the most <choice>
                    <sic>luxurient</sic>
                    <corr>luxuriant</corr>
                </choice> food, and always consider their notaries as mean sensualists so too do I
                look upon an unnecessary expose of any personal enjoyment, whilst I would have the
                freest social intercourse, men and women associating humanly in all the true
                brotherly relations of life, insensably imparting the magnetism of humanity to each
                other, which would rectify the <choice>
                    <sic>morbed</sic>
                    <corr>morbid</corr>
                </choice> condition of society on the great subject of procreation, however this is
                ground you have gone over hundreds of times, and I ought to have taken a hint from
                your brief note, brevity is not generally a womans fort.</p>
            <p>Please write me when you receive this, kind regards to your mother</p>

            <closer>
                <salute rend="right">Yours in the brotherhood of the race</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Sarah Tyndale</signed>
                <address>
                    <addrLine rend="left">Walter Whitman</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>
