<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03335">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 12 December 1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03335</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 12 December 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-12-12" xml:id="dat1">December 12, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-07-23" who="#smb">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2018-09-25" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2018-09-18" who="#blh">Second check</change>
            <change when="2017-07-18" who="#ss">checked and correction</change>
            <change when="2017-01-18" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03335.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">11, Cowley St., Westminster, S.W.</name>
                    <name type="place">London</name>
                    <date when="1888-12-12">12th Decr. 1888.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have been in London this fortnight &#38; more now, &#38; have completely settled at
                last in this quiet, old-fashioned little street behind Westminster Abbey. From Wales
                I went to Somersetshire&#8212;to King Arthur's Vale of Avallon, for a week; then to
                Liverpool, to lecture on "The Modern Novel,"&#8212;on the whole I think the best
                lecture I have given yet. The practice I had in America, &#38; the vocal exercises
                that I used to indulge in during my mountain rambles in Wales this fall, seemed to
                have given me greater power &#38; ease of locution. &#38;c. Ten days ago another
                chance to lecture cropped up unexpectedly, in the place of a sick man, before a
                large audience of working men,&#8212;chiefly socialists; so I gave them as good an
                account of <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi> in connection with my visits to
                you &#38; to America generally as I could at an hour or two's notice. To my great
                delight, there proved to be several men there who knew L. of G. &#38; who were able
                to join with good effect in the discussion afterwards. Again last night I was asked
                to go to a society's meeting where a paper on <hi rend="underline">L. of G.</hi>
                would be read, by William Clarke,<ptr target="loc.03335_n1"/> a young lecturer &#38; journalist, &#38;
                a very able paper it proved to be. During its delivery who should come in but Mrs.
                Costelloe,<ptr target="loc.02189_n1"/> with Evelyn Nordhoff,<ptr target="loc.03335_n2"
                /> &#38; after the paper, Mrs. C. joined in the discussion, speaking with wonderful
                ease &#38; grace, &#38; in fact rather casting into the shade the efforts of the
                rest of us. Shortly<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03335.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                afterwards, Mrs. C &#38; Miss N. had to go, &#38; I saw them into a hansom, not
                expecting of course to see them again; but when an hour later or so I was sauntering
                home, red glare in the sky in the direction of Grosvenor Road, but on the opposite
                side of the river, &#38; the sound of fire-bells &#38; galloping horses in the
                distance, drew me out of my way. On reaching Lambeth Bridge, I found Doulton's great
                pottery had caught fire in one of its buildings &#38; was making a fine blaze, right
                opposite Costelloe's; &#38; I went along then, expecting to find some of them on the
                balcony watching the spectacle. They had not seen it however, &#38; were glad to
                come out to Lambeth Bridge where we stood till the fire was got under. The effect of
                the red glare on the water, with the black barges shooting by, &#38; the river
                fire-engine's steaming up, was singularly striking, especially in contrast with the
                pale, cold moon which shone on the other side. Altogether a wonderful scene!</p>

            <p>After being so long in the quiet of the mountains, you can imagine how these
                excitements of town affect one. Here in Westminster, I am in a capital situation for
                making the most of what London can give one of a healthy &#38; helpful kind. Charing
                Cross is only a short walk distant, with the Strand &#38; its theatres &#38; crowded
                pavements. The river is almost at the back-door, or at any rate only a short street
                away; so that I have the ferries close at hand, &#38; trains &#38; busses are
                equally handy. My American trip seems to have given me a new energy of assimilation
                too. Never before were all the sights &#38; sounds of London so full of suggestion;
                I think you must have unwittingly given me some of your power of co-ordinating
                imaginatively the everyday experiences of the crowd &#38; the life of the streets.
                (By the way, have you seen 'The Century' for Decr.? There's a vivid account of
                London by Hy. James,<ptr target="n2001"/> with clever sketches by Jo. Pennell,<ptr
                    target="loc.02189_n2"/> which gives a very true impression of the whole thing.) And
                now I must stop for to-day, for I have a great deal of work to get through. Don't
                forget about the promised <hi rend="underline">Novr. Boughs</hi><ptr target="n3999"/> &#38; the collected
                complete works,<ptr target="n4188"/> which I want to review immediately! </p>
            <closer> 
                <salute>with much love,</salute> 
                <signed>Ernest Rhys</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p><!--This is written vertically, from top to bottom, in the left margin of the recto.-->I
                    hear<ptr target="loc.03335_n3"/> great account of Gilchrist as Art professor! Tell him the Hobby-Horsemen
                    are so much struck by his success, that they think of following him en-masse to
                    Philadelphia.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
