<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01822">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 9 October 1868</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="em">Erel Michaelis</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01822</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 9 October 1868</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1868-10-09" xml:id="dat1">October 9, 1868</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8&#8211;9</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00295</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-21" who="#smb">final notes, updated</change>
            <change when="2023-05-09" who="#aja">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-14" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-12" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#em" when="2022-02-01" >checked</change>
            <change when="2021-11-12" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-06">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-11-29" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-07-25" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-05-02" who="#js">transcribed additional pages; reordered</change>
            <change when="2012-04-25" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2010-12-06" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
        <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01822.001_large_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <name type="place">Jamestown. R. I.</name>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <date when="1868-10-09">October 9. 1868</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I did not get your letter of September 27th<ptr target="loc.01822_n1"/> till I was leaving for New England, and
                today I have yours of October 4th,<ptr target="loc.01822_n2"/> which Nelly<ptr target="n4137"/> sends me.</p>
            
            <p>I felt so miserably unwell that I decided to try a vacation, and left Washington on
                the 30th of September for Providence, intending to come down at once here to the
                island of <choice><sic>Conauient</sic><reg>Conneaut</reg></choice>, opposite Newport, 
                where I now am. But a severe cold, and a week of unsettled and stormy weather delayed 
                me in Providence till the 6th, when 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01822.002_large_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                I arrived here. I intended to stay at the Light House on the end of the island (Beaver 
                Tail L.H.) but the Keeper could not accommodate me, so I am boarding with a private family.</p>
            
            <p>My purpose was to kill two birds with one stone&#8212;get well and fix up the
                "Carpenter",<ptr target="loc.02449_n4"/> but I fear neither are likely to be effected. I feel 
                wretchedly unwell, and can't think of composition. I never was so <hi rend="underline">tired</hi> in my
                life, and am so sleepy that I drop off in slumber if I sit a few minutes in a
                chair&#8212;a new experience for me. I slept twelve hours last night, and after
                dinner today (one o'clock) fell asleep in a rocking chair 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01822.011_large_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                and slept till six! I never felt such lethargy. I expect some day I shall fall asleep 
                like Rip Van Winkle or (more appropriately) the Sleeping Beauty, and my beard grow down 
                all over the rocks like sea-weed, and cover the sea, and my hair spread backward over the 
                island, and smother the inhabitants. Selah.</p>
            
            <p>I shall probably leave here by the first of next week. I intended to stay longer, but
                it is dull and lonely to me, not feeling able to occupy myself with writing, and the
                beauty of the sea is half-lost and indifferent to my sick eyes. My only pleasure is
                a daily delicious 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01822.012_large_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                swim in the ocean&#8212;all too-brief, for the water is too cold to stay in
                long&#8212;but oh, how good it is! It electrifies and braces me for a few minutes,
                but then I get dull and sleepy again.</p>
            
            <p>So far, thanks to not feeling well, I haven't had a good time at all.</p>
            
            <p>Dear Walt, I hope you will come to Providence. Dr. Channing<ptr target="loc.00945_n5"/> and 
                Jeannie<ptr target="loc.03003_n4"/> quite count upon it, and will be much gratified. I hope 
                you will be there while I am, and then we can go around. I shall return there about the 12th 
                or 13th, and if you fulfil your original intention, that will about bring us together at that time.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01822.007_large_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I am glad you are going to send to Freiligrath.<ptr target="n0248"/> I will do my part, eagerly, 
                though I think I had better wait a few days now, hoping to feel better, and therefore in a better 
                mood. Perhaps, I had better wait till I see you in Providence, if you decide to come on there, 
                and then we can talk it over, and arrange just what is best to say.</p>
            
            <p>Swinton's<ptr target="loc.00434_n6"/> discovery of the resemblance in form between Leaves of Grass 
                and Blake's<ptr target="loc.07918_n5"/> poetry, is in my humble opinion, a mare's nest of the first water. (Irish!!) The
                resemblance is extremely superficial&#8212;about as much as 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01822.008_large_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                between the Gregorian chant, bellowed by bull-necked priests with donkey lips, and a 
                first-class, infinitely varied, complex-melodied Italian opera, sung by voices 
                half-human, half-divine. Such assertions as Swinton's exasperate me. All that resides 
                in the matter is just this: Bishop South<ptr target="n5001"/> had translated the Hebrew prophets into 
                verse of unequal length, following the original, whose metres are interior, the accords being of 
                sense and not sound, and <hi rend="underline">this, as regards mere external form, Blake imitated undoubtedly</hi>. The 
                verse of Leaves of Grass has just so much superficial resemblance to Bishop South's translations, 
                and the imitations of 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01822.009_large_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                Blake, as results from their all being <hi rend="underline">unequal in length</hi>, and no more. 
                For my part, I should as soon think of the form of Leaves of Grass in 
                <choice><orig>connexion</orig><reg>connection</reg></choice> with that of 
                Southey's<ptr target="n3050"/> Thalaba, as with anything of the South-Blake pattern. It differs radically and 
                palpably to the eye, to the ear, and above all to the mind, from anything before it.</p>
            <p>Swinton's item in the Times was good. Nelly sends it to me copied into the <hi rend="underline">Star</hi>. 
                By the way, I put the item into the <hi rend="underline">Star</hi> about the price paid for 
                "Whispers of Heavenly Death":<ptr target="n0695"/> It made a great sensation in Washington, and your stock went 
                up enormously. The 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01822.010_large_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <hi rend="underline">Chronicle</hi> copied it next day, or rather <choice><sic>transmographied</sic><corr>transmografied</corr></choice> 
                it into an item of its own, making the amount twenty five <hi rend="underline">guineas</hi> a page,
                or two hundred and fifty dollars, in which pleasing form it is going the rounds, to your great honor, 
                and glory, nothing appealing to the <choice><orig>esthetic</orig><reg>aesthetic</reg></choice> 
                American mind so much as a success in dollars.</p>
            <p>I meant to have sent you the item, but forgot. I have saved it for you to see.</p>
            <p>That indescribable serpent, George Alfred Townsend,<ptr target="n0643"/> has published an abominably
                flippant and insulting article about you, 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.01822.003_large_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                which I brought with me, in case we met, for you to see. My indignation was intense when I read it, 
                and I don't understand how a man can write such things at all, much less about a person with whom 
                he pretends to be on friendly terms. I think you must spear him with a look when you next meet him, 
                as you did Tilton.<ptr target="n5001"/> He needs reducing to his lowest denomination.</p>
            <p>I left in such a hurry of preparation, that I did not see John Burroughs,<ptr target="n0129"/> so must
                keep your messages for him till I return.</p>
            <p>I am glad your dear mamma<ptr target="n0705"/> is in better quarters than before. It is a great thing, 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.01822.004_large_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                though many might not think so, to be comfortably housed. Especially must it be so to 
                one advanced in years, as she is. Give her my best love.</p>
            <p>It was so long before I heard from you, after I had written, that I thought you must be out 
                of town, and thought of commencing another letter to you with "My dear Romeo"!!! If you 
                wonder "why Romeo?," I can only answer, demurely, because you may have been roaming.</p>
            <p>This is most beautiful!</p>
            <p>&#8212;Ashton<ptr target="loc.01818_n2"/> was running the office when I left. I had a long 
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.01822.005_large_mflm.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                and free talk with him about that Pleasants<ptr target="loc.01822_n3"/> and Evarts,<ptr target="n0223"/>
                in <choice><orig>connexion</orig><reg>connection</reg></choice> with you, which I must tell you
                about when we meet. It made me feel quite
                anxious, but I guess all's right, while Ashton is there. Pleasants is a miserable
                devil. I wish I had power in that office for a little while. I'd put a spoke in the
                wheel of his vendetta, which would carry it and him to a safe distance.</p>
            <p>Your letters were sent by young Rowland.<ptr target="n0530"/> I attempted to attend to it, 
                but found that you had left him full directions, (so he said) which I guess you forgot.
                Nevertheless, I supervised him 
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.01822.006_large_mflm.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                as long as I was there.</p>
            <p>Charley<ptr target="n0642"/> thought his letter to you must have miscarried. He waited for you 
                an hour at the Fifth Avenue Hotel.</p>
            <p>I feel awfully sleepy, and am going to bed, a prospect which renders me disconsolate,
                but nature will have her way.</p>
            <p>I hope to see you in Providence.</p>
            <p>I heard that Higginson<ptr target="n7030"/> did not like my "Good Gray Poet."<ptr target="n0272"/> 
                This is sad. He also had over the story about his reading Leaves of Grass when he was 
                sea-sick, &#38;c. A good thing, which he evidently thinks bears repeating. O ass of
                hell! I thank thee, Gurowski,<ptr target="loc.03046_n3"/> for teaching me that word!</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye</salute>
                <salute>Your affectionate</salute>
                <signed>W.D.O'C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>If you should write, direct to me at Dr. Channing's, 67 Congdon Street, Providence, R. I.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>  
    </text>  
</TEI> 