<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01317">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Moncure D. Conway to Walt Whitman, 12 October 1867</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Moncure D. Conway</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.01317</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Moncure D. Conway</author>
                    <title>Moncure D. Conway to Walt Whitman, 12 October 1867</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1867-10-12" xml:id="dat1">October 12, 1867</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8, Reel 5</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00140 </idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Conway, Moncure D." ref="n0170">Moncure D. Conway</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-06-26" who="#aja">final corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-04-18" who="#smb">final checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-14" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-07-26" who="#kjb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-01-27" who="#cn">checked, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2021-11-10" who="#aja">checked, added DOI, added notes</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-29">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-06-18" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-05-08" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-02-15" who="#al">Checked</change>
            <change when="2011-02-07" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01317.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right">
                    <name type="place">14 Milborne Grove,</name>
                    <name type="place">Brompton W.</name>
                    <name type="place">London, England.</name>                    
                    <date when="1867-10-12">Oct. 12.</date></dateline>
                <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
            </opener> 
            <p>I regret to say that our hopes of getting out the complete and arranged edition of
                your Poems with O'Connor's<ptr target="n2002"/> Introduction is at present remote.
                Just as I was beginning to consult about the matter I found that John Camden
                Hotten<ptr target="n0311"/> had already contracted with W. M. Rossetti<ptr target="n0522"/> 
                to prepare and edit a volume of selections from your Poems.<ptr target="prc.00016_n1"/> 
                I found that Hotten is not yet ready to bring out the whole work as we would wish. My
                first feeling at hearing of this arrangement was one of regret. On thinking the
                whole matter over however I came to think that such an arrangement as that was not
                without some advantages. In the first place <choice>
                    <sic>its</sic>
                    <corr>it's</corr>
                </choice> a thing which cannot be prevented. Americans have not granted the English
                any protection for their works or choice about bringing them out, and in the absence
                of a just law on the subject no one can claim property in his work over here. I may
                say in passing, however, that in reply to a letter from me to Mr. Hotten he 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01317.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01317.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                told me that he meant to share with you the pecuniary profits of the venture, 
                and spoke in an honorable tone.</p>
            <p>Now the advantages I see in the plan of having Rossetti edit the selected volume are
                these: I believe that it is the best means of paving the way for a public demand for
                the entire work. The English people are the very ones to desire that which is
                reserved. Until there is such a popular demand no publisher can be found to print
                the poems which are now quite extensive. In the next place it is far better, in my
                opinion and that of your real friends here, that the introduction of you to the
                general public will come much more gracefully from an English literary man than from
                any American. No introduction could easily surpass in simple breadth that which
                O'Connor has written; and some day it must appear; but his reputation here is
                confined to the few who have read his noble pamphlet,<ptr target="n0272"/> and,
                which is still more important, it can never have so much effect here for an American
                to praise American work. It says more for your work that it has kindled enthusiasm
                in the mind of one of another nation, 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01317.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01317.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                and one whose good judgments cannot be ascribed to personal friendship more than to national
                pride. These facts together with the assured social and literary position of
                Rossetti make him of all persons of my acquaintance the fittest I could name to
                undertake the work. It at once secures the <hi rend="underline">position</hi> of
                your work. The criticism which he wrote in the <hi rend="underline">Chronicle</hi><ptr target="loc.01317_n3"/>
                will show you the spirit in which his work will be done, and I know that he is
                putting a great deal of very careful work upon his introductory essay. 
                I have passed an evening with him. He tells me that his plan
                will be to divide up the Poems according to their subjects; e.g. "Poems of
                Democracy," "Personal Poems," "Poems of Friendship," etc. He does not intend to
                alter any of the Poems he publishes. His volume will I should judge include about
                one half you have written. There will be footnotes explaining "phebe–bird" and other
                things not known in England so far as he can.</p>
            <p>Now for some questions he wishes me to ask you: What is <hi rend="underline">Calamus</hi>?<ptr target="loc.01317_n1"/> 
                I could not tell him, satisfactorily, either the exact thing you meant or its metaphorical meaning to you. 
                Again, Rossetti admires very much indeed your introduction to 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01317.006_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01317.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                the first edition of the "Leaves of Grass," and wishes to publish it; but he is deterred by a
                few words. He wishes to know whether you will not send him a word instead of
                "father–stuff" (p. 7, 17th line from bottom) and if on p. 10, bottom lines, you will
                allow him to alter "venereal sores or discolorations," "onanist" and "any depravity
                of young men." These are the only words he anywhere wishes to modify. The essay is a
                great one &amp; would have a great effect; but if you do not permit the alterations
                he will not print it—as he goes on the honorable principle that he has not the
                right to change an author's language.<ptr target="n0526"/></p>
            <p>Now, my dear friend, I hope that on reflection you and O'Connor will think as I do
                (who am on the ground) that on the whole we had best feel good naturedly toward this
                plan of Hotten's and Rossetti's. We are not here up to the point yet, but are
                rising, &amp; this book will help us I am quite sure. The other day the Saturday
                Review<ptr target="loc.01317_n2"/> which once ridiculed Leaves of Grass began a
                review of some American's poems by saying that nothing related to America had
                appeared in its literature with the simple exception of Walt Whitman's works. The
                word had its effect. And now goodbye. Let me hear from you as soon as you can, and
                believe me ever cordially your friend.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>M. D. Conway</signed>
            </closer> 
            <postscript>
                <p>Observe my change of address<ptr target="duk.00555_n3"/></p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01317.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>