<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.03385">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 31 August 1891</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="adk">Andy King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03385</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2022 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                    <title>Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 31 August 1891</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1891-08-31" xml:id="dat1">August 31, 1891</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8&#8211;9</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00297</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Dowd, Bernard" ref="loc.08456_n8">Bernard O'Dowd</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-07-13" who="#aja">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2022-03-17" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-06-15" who="#adk">second check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2019-07-02" who="#if">First check</change>
            <change when="2018-06-20" who="#bjo">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03385.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1891-08-31" rend="right"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>August 31st /91</date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>Supreme Court Library<lb/>Melbourne</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Master</salute>
            </opener> 
            <p>
                I have received and heartily thank you for the papers you have sent and the welcome copy of "Good bye! My Fancy."<ptr target="loc.07894_n2"/>
                I have not wanted to bother you during your severe illness, hence my silence. But we have followed with interest any information 
                about you especially the facsimile letter which Dr. Johnston<ptr target="n4102"/> of Bolton was kind enough to send me and the article in a late
                "Review of Reviews"<ptr target="loc.07336_n6"/> with a sketch of your house and a little chit chat on your political opinions (I have much the same opinions
                myself of late years, but that is not surprising for they are simple deductions from the spiritual principle
                of the spirit of "Leaves of Grass.") I gave a lecture on "Walt Whitman, the Poet of Democracy" to an audience of 3 or 400 people at a 
                Sunday night meeting of the Australasian Secular Association<ptr target="loc.03385_n7"/> and was very well received. The subject was evidently 
                unfamliar but its reception gave me great hopes that it will not be so long in that quarter anyway. I made the acquaintance of
                another Whitman enthusiast at the meeting, Mr John Sutherland M.A.,<ptr target="loc.03385_n3"/> and I can assure you we have had some glorious evenings together
                since talking of you and with you. He tells me that he has only read L. of G. once, but wants to read it no more.
                He doesn't remember
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03385.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                the words particularly, but the
                new mental attitude to things he believes he has thoroughly absorbed, and the world is different and life different to him since.
                "Tom Touchstone"<ptr target="loc.03385_n2"/> sent another disciple, Mr Carr,<ptr target="n5001"/> to me and he is quite devoted. He was greatly pleased at
                a portrait I was able to give him. Mr Sutherland &#38; Jim Hartigan<ptr target="loc.03385_n4"/> want a copy of "Good bye my Fancy." Could
                you send price, please. Fred Woods<ptr target="loc.03385_n5"/> would like one of those portraits where you appear with (as it were) storm tossed beard,
                your hat on, and a hearty, sea-captain-like look on you. And, if it would not be too much trouble, with your name on it.
                He's a grand fellow Fred, and tossed as he was on seas of doubt &#38; deserts of the barrenest materialism,
                you have become a virtual religion to him as you have to more than him. Mr Sutherland has translated Freiligrath's<ptr target="loc.03385_n8"/>
                article on you (from Dr. Bucke's<ptr target="n0119"/> book<ptr target="loc.03385_n6"/>). It is wonderful what misunderstandings are about concerning your poems of sex.
            </p> 
            <p>
                I do not fear, as you seem to do, that we shall separate from Britain.<ptr target="med.00938_n1b"/> I advocated it once, nay started a society to
                bring it about, which I am glad to say soon died. For this change as for many others, I must thank you. I like to hear
                your ideas on Australians and would say much myself but that I don't want to bother you too much. We want a Walt Whitman here:
                ours is a democracy too with ever more hopeful prospects than yours but with great dangers ahead (especially social) and here 
                too the song of material interests drowns the other pieces in the chorus.
            </p>
            <p> 
                We love you all, and greet you with sympathy in your illnesses and with growing hopes for your speedy recognition by all 
                men as being as much their Walt as you are ours.
            </p>
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">B. O'Dowd</signed>
                <signed rend="left">Bernard O'Dowd</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
