<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.02884">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 16&#8211;30 November 1875</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02884</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <!--<biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Garden City, New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1964">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">133&#8211;136</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>-->
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 16&#8211;30 November 1875</title>
                    <date cert="high" notBefore="1875-11-16" notAfter="1875-11-30" xml:id="dat1">November 16&#8211;30, 1875</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS45443, Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms002007.mss45443.0111</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-10" who="#smb">updated notes</change>
            <change when="2023-03-27" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-01" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-15" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-06-05" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-05-21" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-04-23" who="#al">Checked with microfilm images</change>
            <change when="2011-08-09" who="#zk">transcribed and encoded from Harned; annotated AG and family, WMR, MDC, Hillard</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter"> 
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_cb.00321.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>1 Torriano Gardens</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Camden Rd.</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>London.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    <date when="1875-11-16" rend="right">Nov. 16 1875</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener> 

            <p>I have been wanting the comfort, of a talk with you dearest Friend, for weeks &amp; weeks, without being able to 
                get leisure &amp; tranquillity enough to do it to my <choice><sic>hearts</sic><corr>heart's</corr></choice> content, 
                indeed <choice><sic>hearts</sic><corr>heart's</corr></choice> content is not for me at present; but restless, 
                eager longing to come&#8212;&amp; the struggle to do patiently &amp; completely &amp; wisely what remains for me here 
                before I am free to obey the deep faith and love which govern me&#8212;So let me sit close beside you my Darling&#8212;&amp; 
                feel your presence &amp; take comfort &amp; strength &amp; serenity from it, as I do, as I can when with all my heart 
                &amp; soul I draw close 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_cb.00324.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                
                to you realizing your living presence with all my might.&#8212;First, about Percy<ptr target="n2000"/>&#8212;things 
                are beginning to look a little brighter for him. He is just entering upon a new engagement with some very large &amp; 
                successful works&#8212;the Blenavon Iron Co.&#8212;where, though his salary will not be 
                higher at first, his opportunities of improvement will be better &amp; he is also to be allowed to take private 
                practice (in assaying &amp; analyzing). The manager there believes in Science &amp; is friendly to Percy &amp; 
                will give him every facility for showing what he can do, so that he hopes to prove to the
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_cb.00325.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                Directors before long that he is worth a good salary. The parents of Norah<ptr target="loc.02882_n6"/> (whom he loves) have 
                released from their unfriendly attitude since my Beatrice<ptr target="n0260"/> has been staying with him, the 
                two girls have attached themselves to one another &amp; <choice><abbr>Per.</abbr><expan>Percy</expan></choice> has had 
                delightful opportunities of being with Norah, &amp; best of all she is to return <hi rend="underline">here</hi> with 
                Beatrice (they are coming tomorrow) &amp; <choice><abbr>Per.</abbr><expan>Percy</expan></choice> is to have a 
                <choice><sic>weeks</sic><corr>week's</corr></choice> holiday &amp; come up, so that he &amp; Norah will be wholly together 
                &amp; have I suspect, the happiest week they have yet had in their lives. Then I have stored away for them the furniture 
                of the dear old home at Colne &amp; I really think that by the time 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_cb.00322.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
                /76 is out they will be able to marry. I see, and indeed I have known ever since he formed this attachment, that I must 
                not look for him to come to America with me. But what I build upon dearest Friend is that when I have been a little while 
                in America &amp; have made friends &amp; had time to look about me I might hear of a good certainty for him&#8212;his 
                excellent training at the <choice><abbr>Lond.</abbr><expan>London</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>Sch.</abbr><expan>School</expan></choice> 
                of Mines, large experience at Blenavon energy ability &amp; sturdy uprightness will make him a first rate manager of works 
                by &amp; bye. 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_cb.00328.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                
                But the leaving him so happy with his young wife will make it easier for us to part&#8212;Nov. 26&#8212;Beatrice has 
                begun to work at anatomy at the School of Medicine for Women lately founded, &amp; seems to delight in her work. She 
                will not enter on the full course all at once&#8212;I am for taking things gently. Women have plenty of strength but it 
                is of a different kind from <choice><sic>mens</sic><corr>men's</corr></choice> &amp; must work by gentler &amp; slower 
                means&#8212;Above all I do not like what pushes violently aside domestic duties &amp; pleasures. The special work must 
                combine itself with these; I am sure it can. Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> is getting on very nicely, never did 
                student love his work better. He is eager, &amp; by making the best use of present opportunities &amp; advantages
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_cb.00330.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                
                yet looking towards America full of cheerful hopes &amp; sympathy. Grace<ptr target="n0261"/> is less developed 
                in intellect but not less in character than the others. I can't describe her but send you her photograph. There is a 
                freshness &amp; independence of character about her&#8212;yet withal a certain waywardness &amp; reserve. She is a good 
                instinctive judge of character&#8212;more influenced by it than by books&#8212;yet with a growing taste for them too. 
                She comes to America with a gay and buoyant curiosity, declining to make up her mind about anything till she gets there. 
                We want as far as possible 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_cb.00331.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
                to transplant our home bodily&#8212;to bring as much as we can of our own furniture because we have beautiful old things 
                precious in Herby's eyes &amp; that we are all fond of. And coming straight to Philadelphia &amp; taking a house somewhere 
                on the outskirts of it or Camden immediately we fancy this might be practicable, but have not yet launched into the matter&#8212;I 
                have just heard from Mr. Rossetti,<ptr target="n0522"/> &amp; also from Mrs. Conway<ptr target="loc.02871_n6"/> 
                of her <choice><sic>husbands</sic><corr>husband's</corr></choice><ptr target="n0170"/> having seen you, &amp; if
                his report be not too sanguine it is a cheering one &amp; would comfort me much dearest Friend. 
                But what he says is so favourable I am afraid to believe it 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_cb.00327.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                
                altogether, knowing that you would make the very best of yourself &amp; indeed be probably at your best with the pleasure 
                of seeing an old friend fresh from England &amp; also that he is sanguine.</p>
            <p>Nov. 30. And now, dear Friend, I have had a very great pleasure indeed, thanks to you&#8212;a visit from Mr. 
                Marvin<ptr target="n0830"/>&#8212;&amp; hope to have another when he returns from Paris. And the account he gives 
                of you is so cheerful&#8212;so vivid&#8212;it seems to part assunder a gloomy cloud that was brooding in my mind. 
                And though I know that for the short hours that you feel bright &amp; well are many long hours when you are far 
                otherwise, still I feel sure those short hours are the earnest of perfect recovery&#8212;with a fine 
                patience&#8212;boundless patience. And now I can picture you sitting in your favourite 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_cb.00332.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                
                window, having a friendly word with passers by&#8212;&amp; feel quite sure that you are happy &amp; comfortable in 
                your surroundings. And a great deal else full of interest Mr. Marvin told me. I was loth for him to go, but one
                hour is so small we have noticed for a friend I am sorry to say. </p>
            <p>William Rossetti has a little girl which is a great delight to him. Miss Hillard<ptr target="n0302"/> of Brooklyn 
                has also paid me a visit &amp; spoken to me of you. She charmed me much&#8212;only I felt a little cross with her 
                for giving Herby such a dismal account of his chances as an artist in America&#8212;<pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_cb.00333.jpg" type="verso"/>However 
                we both refused to be discouraged, for after all he can send his pictures to England to be established &amp;c. having 
                plenty of friends who would see to it; &amp; we are both firm in the faith that if you can only paint the really good pictures 
                the rest will take care of itself somehow or other&#8212;&amp; that can be done as well in America as in England&#8212;but of 
                course he must finish his training here&#8212; </p>

            <closer>
                <salute>With best love from us all, good bye my dearest Friend.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>