<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00673">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Hannah Whitman Heyde to Walt Whitman, 4
    March [1873]</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Hannah Whitman Heyde</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
<persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
<persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska–Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.00673</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc><bibl>
    <author>Hannah Whitman Heyde</author>
    <title>Hannah Whitman Heyde to Walt Whitman, 4 March [1873]</title>
    <date cert="medium" when="1873-03-04" xml:id="dat1">March 4, 1873</date>
                <orgName xml:id="loc">Hannah Louisa Whitman Heyde Papers, 1853&#8211;1892, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Heyde, Hannah Whitman" ref="n0285">Hannah Whitman Heyde</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#nhg" when="2015-04-07">corrected orgName</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-06-14" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-26" who="#al">Checked</change>
            <change when="2011-12-14" who="#kk">Checked</change>
            <change when="2011-08-14" who="#zk">Transcribed and encoded from manuscript</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.00673.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <address><addrLine>Burlington</addrLine><addrLine>Tuesday morning</addrLine></address>
                    <date when="1873-03-04" rend="right">March 4 <ptr target="loc.00673_"/></date>
                    
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>How are you this morning.&#8212;I wish I was where I could come in and see you and do something for you&#8212;that has been a trouble to us. that we <choice>
                    <orig>cant</orig>
                    <reg>can't</reg>
                </choice> be of the least benefit to you now when you are ill. </p>

            <p>You <choice>
                    <orig>dont</orig>
                    <reg>don't</reg>
                </choice> know anything about how bad and sorry I felt about your illness</p>

            <p>You have been exceedingly kind and thoughtful dear brother to write to me, that first letter was very welcome I was wonderfully glad to get it, a little afraid you was
                    <del type="strikethrough" cert="high" resp="#zk">not</del> hardly yet strong
                enough <!--The closing/signature is on the top of this page, but we have transcribed/encoded it in reading order at the end of the letter-->

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.00673.002.jpg" type="verso"/>

            to write.&#8212;Dear Mother too has been kind about writing I expect a line every day
                I am anxious to hear.</p>

            <p>I have not heard for eleven days&#8212;I do so hope to hear the good news that you
                are better, and are able to go out a little</p>

            <p>I feel glad when <choice>
                    <orig>its</orig>
                    <reg>it's</reg>
                </choice> bright pleasant weather I think maybe you will gain faster,&#8212;I know my dear brother you have a good deal of patience and that you do not easily get discouraged and that too is in your favour,&#8212;You have a good many friends I know, and have every attention, every little thing

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.00673.003.jpg" type="recto"/>

           done for your comfort that can be done, do you not Walt,&#8212;Still it would seem better, to us, if some of us was near you.</p>

            <p>Has George been to see you I suppose he has though</p>

            <p>And dear brother Jeffy too I know as soon as he can think of anything he will go to see you. I should like to hear from him and the dear little girls</p>

            <p>Do you remember Walt some years ago, what a bad time I had with my back (I think it was neuralgie of the spine) anyway I was well only my back I could not walk three steps for many weeks &amp; could sit up all day, &amp; when I could walk about &amp; even go up &amp; down stairs I was a good deal more than half bent over, &amp; I was bent over so nearly as bad for more than a year,&#8212;I only speak of it so you will know how much time will do, my back is now as strong as it ever was in the world</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.00673.004.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>I do so want you to get well Walt, I shall be so happy when you are strong as ever
                again, and persons tell me you will be, a good many inquire about you.&#8212;</p>

            <p>You know your room here is always ready. I do hope when it warm weather, in June you will come, I remember you liked the mountain air here and I know it will be good for you And I have been thinking if dear Mother too could bear the journey. for it would seem just like home to you then, and I do not think it safe to stay in Washington like you did last summer, &amp; Charlie has a great wish to go away to the Adirondacks &amp; other places, &amp; <choice>
                    <orig>its</orig>
                    <reg>it's</reg>
                </choice> a great bother to leave the house alone with me, &amp; I would do every
                thing in my power for you, dear brother</p>

            <p>I <choice>
                    <orig>dont</orig>
                    <reg>don't</reg>
                </choice> know why I have not written to you before, I wish I had <choice>
                    <orig>somethin</orig>
                    <reg>something</reg>
                </choice> cheerful to tell you, things are just the same here I only want you to be well again I do like that young fellow that is so kind to you, Peter Doyle, I shall always remember him</p>
             <pb sameAs="#leaf001r" facs="loc.00673.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <closer><salute>Good bye my dear brother, I send you a great
                deal of love, Charlie also sends love</salute>
                <signed>Han</signed>
            </closer>
           
                

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>