<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02871">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 12 August 1873</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02871</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any 
                        medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital 
                        Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners 
                        of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               <!-- <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Garden City, New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1964">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">91&#8211;93</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>-->
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 12 August 1873</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1873-08-12" xml:id="dat1">August 12, 1873</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS45443, Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms002007.mss45443.0111</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-10" who="#smb">ran image script, updated notes</change>
            <change when="2023-07-28" who="#aja">updated image pointers</change>
            <change when="2023-03-04" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-03-03" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-10-20" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-04-10" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#cn" when="2021-11-29">checked, corrected, added notes and DOI</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-30">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-05-29" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-20" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-04-12" who="#al">Checked from microfilm images.</change>
            <change when="2011-08-05" who="#zk">transcribed and encoded from Harned; annotated AG, WMR, MDC</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_cb.00143.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Earls Colne</name>
                    <name type="place">Halstead</name>
                    <date when="1873-08-12" rend="right">August 12, 1873</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dearest Friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The paper has just been forwarded here which tells me you are still suffering,<ptr target="loc.01969_n4"/> 
                and not, as I was fondly believing, already quite emerged from the cloud of sickness. 
                My Darling&#8212;let me use that tender caressing word once more, for how can I help 
                it, with heart so full &amp; no outlet but words? 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_cb.00146.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                My darling. I say it over &amp; over to myself with voice with eyes so full of 
                love&#8212;of tender yearning sorrowful longing love. I would give all the world if 
                I might come (but am held here yet awhile inexorably by a duty nothing may supersede) 
                &amp; soothe &amp; tend &amp; wait on you &amp; with such cheerful loving companionship 
                lift off some of the weight of the long hours &amp; days &amp; perhaps months that 
                must still go over while nature is slowly, imper<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_cb.00147.jpg" type="recto"/>ceptibly 
                but still so surely repairing the mischief within, result of the tremendous ordeal 
                to your frame of those great overbrimming years of life spent in the Army Hospitals.<ptr target="n0044b"/> 
                You see dear Friend a woman who is a mother has thenceforth something of that feeling 
                toward all men who are dear to her&#8212;a cherishing fostering instinct that makes 
                her rejoice so in all personal service to them. O I should be so happy it needs must 
                diffuse a reviving 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_cb.00144.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                comforting vivifying warmth around you. Might but these words breathed out of the inmost 
                heart of a woman who loves you with her whole soul &amp; life &amp; strength fulfil their 
                errand &amp; comfort the sorrowful heart, if ever so little&#8212;and through that help 
                to revive the drooping frame! This love that has grown up far away over here, unhelped by 
                the sweet influences of personal intercourse, penetrating the whole substance of a 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_cb.00150.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                woman's life, swallowing up into itself all her aspirations, hopes, longings, regardless 
                of Death, looking earnestly confidently beyond that for fruition blending more or less 
                with every thought &amp; act of her life a guiding star that her feet cannot choose but 
                follow resolutely&#8212;what can be more real than this dear Friend. What can have deeper 
                roots, or a more immortal growing power within it? But I do not 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_cb.00152.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                ask any longer whether this love is believed in &amp; welcome &amp; precious to you: 
                For I know that what has real roots cannot fail to bear real flowers and fruits that 
                will in the end be sweet and joygiving to you; and that if I am indeed capable of being 
                your eternal comrade, climbing whereon you climb, daring all that you dare, learning 
                all that you learn, suffering all that you suffer (pressing 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_cb.00153.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                closest then) enjoying all that you enjoy, you will want me, will not be able to help 
                stretching out your hand &amp; drawing me to you. I have written this mostly out in the 
                fields as I am so fond of doing&#8212;the serene beautiful harvest landscape spread around, 
                returns once more, as I have every summer for five &amp; twenty years, to this old village 
                where my mother's family have lived in unbroken succession three hundred years, ever since 
                in fact, the old Priory they 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_cb.00149.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                have inhabited ceased to be a Priory at the dissolution of monasteries&#8212;My Mother's<ptr target="loc.02871_n4"/> 
                health is still good&#8212;wonderful, indeed, for 88 though she has been 30 years crippled 
                by rheumatism. Still she enjoys getting out in the Sunshine in her Bath chair &amp; is able 
                to take pleasure in seeing her friends &amp; in having us all with her. Her father was a hale 
                man at 90.<ptr target="loc.02871_n8"/>&#8212;These eastern counties are flat &amp; tame but yet under this soft smiling 
                summer sky lovely enough too&#8212;with 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_cb.00156.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                their rich delicious green meadows abundant golden corn crops now being well got in &amp; 
                thickly scattered old homesteads each with gay garden, &amp; picturesque villages shaded by 
                tall elms. Even the sluggish little river Colne one cannot find 
                fault with, it nourishes such a luxuriant border of wild flowers as it creeps along, &amp; 
                turns &amp; twists about from sunshine into shade &amp; shade into sunshine so as to make 
                the very best &amp; most 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_cb.00158.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                of itself. But as to the human growth here, I think that perhaps more than anywhere else 
                in England it struggles along choked &amp; poisoned by dead things of the past still holding 
                their place above ground.</p>
            <p>I did not see William Rossetti<ptr target="n0522"/> before I came down but heard that he had 
                had a very happy time in Italy &amp; splendid weather all the while. Mr. Conway<ptr target="n0170"/> 
                &amp; his wife<ptr target="loc.02871_n6"/> &amp; three children 
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_cb.00159.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                are gone to Brittany for their holiday.</p>
            <p>My boys &amp; girls are well&#8212;except indeed that I am afraid Percy<ptr target="n2000"/> 
                finds his health somewhat affected by the constant inhaling of unwholesome gases analyzing 
                ores all day long, but he is going to have better appliances in his laboratory which will 
                I hope remove or lessen very much the evil. In other respects he likes his work &amp; is 
                getting good experience</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc_cb.00155.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>May this find you by the sea shore&#8212;getting on so fast,&#8212;the friend you love best 
                with you, comforted, refreshed soul and body&#8212;perfect harmony between these two restored 
                once more so that you step forth with strong &amp; buoyant step to complete your great purpose.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye beloved friend</salute>
                <signed>Annie Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>
