<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.04408">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">James W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 18&#8211;19 August 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>James W. Wallace</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor> 
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="adk">Andrew David King</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04408</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2021 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be 
                     shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication 
                     on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification 
                     of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic 
                     images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>James W. Wallace</author>
                    <title>James W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 18&#8211;19 August 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" notBefore="1890-08-18" notAfter="1890-08-19" xml:id="dat1">August 18&#8211;19, 1890</date> 
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 18, Reel 11</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00401</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, 
                        Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName> 
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Wallace, James W." ref="n6121">James W. Wallace</persName> 
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName> 
                </person>
            </particDesc> 
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2021-07-29" who="#smb">completed director's corrections</change>
            <change when="2020-10-20" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2020-07-13" who="#adk">second check, minor corrections, added notes</change>
            <change when="2020-06-02" who="#cn">first check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-03-15" who="#adk">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.01045_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener rend="center">
                <dateline>
                <name type="place">Anderton</name>
                <name type="place">Chorley</name>
                <name type="place">England.</name>
                <date when="1890-08-18">18 Aug.' 1890.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Dr Johnston<ptr target="n4102"/> arrived at home on Friday the 8<hi rend="underline">th</hi>
                inst, as he will have told you. On Monday, the 11<hi rend="underline">th</hi>, (my birthday) he came to see me and gave me
                the&#8212;presents you sent me: <hi rend="underline">viz</hi> the two books&#8212;("Passage
                to India" &#38; "As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free")<ptr target="loc.04408_n1"/> and the magnificent photograph
                of yourself&#8212;(Since borrowed
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.01046_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                by him for a copy, as arranged with you).</p>
            <p>I cannot tell you how much I prize them&#8212;especially the latter. Carlyle's<ptr target="n4301"/>
                heart was not stirred more deeply by the friendship and gifts of Go&#235;the<ptr target="n0270"/> than 
                mine is by yours&#8212;nor, indeed, I think, nearly so much</p>
            <p>I have thought it a sufficient, and, indeed, a great and sacred privilege to write to you
                at all, and
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.01047_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> you some slight beginnings, even here, of the immense influence 
                your work is destined to
                have, and of the deep personal love and reverence towards yourself, which must always accompany it,
                and which millions will yet share. And I have felt it a duty, as well as a privilege, to show my
                gratitude to you and to cheer you (so far as might be) by some expression of all this.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.01048_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>But I never dreamed of receiving such returns!</p>
            <p>Fitly, indeed!, and with a full heart,
                may I "hang up your picture as that of the tenderest lover, the friend the lover's portrait, of
                whom his friend his lover is fondest"<ptr target="loc.04408_n2"/>&#8212;It shall adorn my room as long as I live,&#8212;reminding
                me daily of you, of your work and life, of your great&#8212;benefactions to me personally through
                your books&#8212;and
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.01049_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                to how many besides!&#8212;and (not least) of the consecrating friendship with which you have crowned
                them, and of the tender, thoughtful courtesy and noble kindness which you have <choice><orig>shewn</orig><reg>shown</reg></choice> 
                me. I trust it may also prove a daily incentive to emulation of your great qualities.</p>
            <p>For your goodness to me&#8212;like all the good gifts of life&#8212;carries with it its own deep
                obligations. And these I feel to be&#8212;to live as one worthy of
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.01050_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
               your friendship, and to help on, so far as I can, your influence and work.</p>
            <p>It awakens in me an old purpose, which circumstances have for the last few years thwarted and 
            almost crushed.</p>
            <p>Five years ago (last January) my mother died. (You, too, know well what that means!&#8212;though I
                doubt if even you can have sounded so deeply&#8212;as many exceptionally harmful
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_vm.01051_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                circumstances led me to sound&#8212;the unfathomable depths of a mothers tender, self-sacrificing
                love.&#8212;And the circumstances of her death, beautiful &#38; sacred, affected me infinitely more,
                and were a far deeper revelation to my soul than any literature&#8212;even yours.) In the revision
                of my purposes and aims that followed, one fixed project with me was to contribute to current literature
                an account of your work that should include one or two things that have not yet been said&#8212;at
                any rate, not with sufficient
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_vm.01052_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
               clearness and emphasis. But many untoward circumstances (partly resulting in &#38; including
               mental and nervous break down &#38; exhaustion) have prevented me from attempting this, and I see
               no prospect now of carrying out my plan for a long time to come.&#8212;But I trust that the time
               <hi rend="underline">will</hi> come,&#8212;when, perhaps, I shall be all the better fitted for it
               by the long delay.&#8212;At any rate "my purpose holds," and as the old painter (quoted by
               Emerson<ptr target="n0218"/>) once said, not
           <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_vm.01053_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
               irreverently&#8212;"By God, it is in me, and shall out of me!"<ptr target="loc.04408_n5"/> 
            </p>
            <p>In the meantime I have led some of my friends to know you and to love you.&#8212;Dr. Johnston
                being one of the first. And it is <hi rend="underline">your</hi> influence mainly that has made
                our little society of friends<ptr target="loc.04707_n3"/> what it was lately described as being&#8212;"the truest band
                of brothers" the speaker had "ever met with."</p>
            <p>(It has been very pleasant to me to note how one or two of my friends&#8212;one especially&#8212;who
                are not "literary" in their
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_vm.01054_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                tastes, and who care little for any authors except <choice><orig>Shakspere</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> 
                and Burns,<ptr target="loc.07725_n6"/> but who love
                manly and heroic qualities, outdoor life, boating, sailing, engineering &#38;c, and who have
                a deep inarticulate sense (deeper than usually goes with "culture" and
                <choice><sic>esthecism</sic><corr>estheticism</corr></choice>) of what is good
                and true&#8212;are attracted by <hi rend="underline">you</hi>. It is very clear to me
                that your ultimate absorption by this class (the class you have loved best of all) is only
                a matter of time and will be deep and affectionate.).
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_vm.02158_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                It has been a very great pleasure to me to learn from D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Johnston,
                particulars of his interviews with you and of your great kindness to him. He is still
                noticeably affected by it, and by your personal presence &#38; conversation.&#8212;and he
                looks&#8212;as I told him the other day&#8212;"like one who has been awed &#38; exalted
                by a supernatural visitation."</p> 
            <p>I rejoice especially to hear of your good health ("considering") and of the wonderful
                extent to which you
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc_vm.02159_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                have recovered from your condition two years ago. May you long enjoy health, happiness,
                "halcyon days,"<ptr target="loc.04408_n3"/> and the devotion of increasing numbers of loving friends.&#8212;
            </p>
            <p>Dr. Johnston's friends are all very much pleased, too, to hear of the hospitable kindness
                of M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi> Davis<ptr target="n6113"/> and of "Warren"<ptr target="loc.07319_n6"/>
                towards him, and indeed, I think I will write to them direct, next mail,
                (per M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi> Davis) to say so.&#8212;
            </p>
            <p>I asked D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Johnston about the canary you once celebrated
            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc_vm.02160_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                but he could tell me nothing of it (though he told me about your "robin") and we concluded
                that it must be dead. I am sorry to think that its cheering &#38; "joyous warbles"<ptr target="loc.04408_n4"/> are ended
                for you in this way.</p>
            <p>I was deeply sorry to hear of W. D. O'Connor's death,<ptr target="n2002"/>, of which we had
                seen no notice. The last thing I saw about him (some time ago) was that he was ill (in
                California, I believe). And now I learn that he is dead! Only the week before
                D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Johnston's return
            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc_vm.02161_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                I had been re-reading his letters (in Dr Bucke's<ptr target="n0119"/> book) with
                renewed pleasure in his brilliant and perfervid championships of your cause, and I almost
                feel now as though I, too, had lost a friend.</p>
            <p>But I have written too long, &#38; perhaps tired you. Again thanks to you,
                loved benefactor and friend, from my heart, and love to you always from self &#38; friends.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">J.W. Wallace</hi></signed> 
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc_vm.02162_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <postscript>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">P.S.</hi> <date when="1890-08-19">Aug' 19<hi rend="underline">th</hi></date>
                    D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Johnston brought me a copy of "Camden's Compliments"<ptr target="loc.03027_n3"/> and
                    I am very pleased to see, from an advertisement at the end, that a small pocket book edition of
                    L. of G. <hi rend="underline">complete</hi><ptr target="med.00869_n3"/> is in existence and it is to be had from
                    <hi rend="underline">you</hi>. It appears to be just what I want&#8212;a copy that I can carry
                    conveniently in my pocket in my country rambles &#38; holidays.&#8212;The ordinary edition is too
                    large&#8212;though I have often carried it about&#8212;and the handy volume published
                <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc_vm.02163_large.jpg" type="verso"/>  
                    by W Scott,<ptr target="n4147"/> which I usually carry, is much too incomplete. I don't know what the carriage will
                    be, but I will enclose money order for 22s/-
                    which I trust will cover it, and shall be glad if you will kindly send me a copy at your
                    convenience. The fact that it comes direct 
                    from <hi rend="underline">you</hi> will give it additional interest.
                    <note type="editorial" resp="#ww">book sent</note>
                </p>
            </postscript>  
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>