<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02203">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 16 June
                    1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02203</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Herbert Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Herbert Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 16 June 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-06-16" xml:id="dat1">June 16, 1888</date>
                   <!-- <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>-->
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Herbet" ref="n0262">Herbert Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2017-03-14" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2017-01-09" who="#cb">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-09-01" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-08-26" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
 
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02203.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">12 Well Rd<lb/>Hampstead, London<lb/>England</name>
                    <date when="1888-06-16">1888<lb/>June<lb/>16th</date>
                </dateline>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-left"/>
            </opener>

            <p>I feel very sad about dear old <choice>
                <orig>Walts</orig>
                <reg>Walt's</reg>
            </choice> illness.</p>

            <p>The two telegrams in the London "Daily News" are so alarming&#8212;I fear I shall
                never see him again; I've half a mind to start off now to Philadelphia.</p>
            <p>If you see Walt again in this world after receiving this letter, give him my
                love.</p>
            <p>Write to me as soon as you get this if it's only a few lines.</p>
            <p>Tell me about your own health, how much work are you doing every day. Can I be of
                use? I wish I could be of more comfort to you.</p>
            <p>I am coming to America about the <hi rend="underline">middle</hi> of August.</p>
            <p>I hope that you are not working just the same as you did last summer. You <hi
                    rend="underline">must</hi> remember what the doctors told you.</p>
            <p>It will not do for you to be ill again. I feel horribly anxious about your
                health!</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02203.002.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>Let me know if you require anything. I hope it will not be very hot in America in
                August. What I recollect of it last year, was that it began to "let up" in August cool nights,
                and that sort of thing.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Pearsall<ptr target="n4979"/> has told me of a nice little studio
                in Chestnut street high up that is only about &#36;75 a year, which would just suit me. My idea is to hire
                a studio &#38; one other room in Chestnut street, &#38; to get my meals out at different cheap
                restaurants I, dare say, I could get a meal for 25 cents, and in the colder weather I
                could cook my own breakfast or at any rate my tea on my studio stove? So I shall
                bring a few cooking utensils &#38; a few other things. I want to make drawings of street
                scenes in Philadelphia and during the <hi rend="underline">election</hi> in November&#8212;and
                maybe, also, that I shall travel to other cities a little during the elections. It
                is possible, also, that I may get work to do in connection with <unclear
                    reason="illegible" resp="#ktl" cert="medium">in</unclear>:&#8212;Cherry street Academy
                of Fine Arts, but of that I am not certain.</p>
            <p>I am getting on with my portrait of Mrs. Costelloe<ptr target="loc.02189_n1"/>; I reckon to finish it before I
                leave England, and to leave it behind all ready for next year's Govenor of Royal Academy.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02203.003.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>She is a light hearted fine lady, talks to me in a lively strain during the sitting, but she is so
                superficial, every time one dips the oar of conversation in, I seem to scrape the sandy bottom!!
                And would you believe, that Westminster is five good miles from our house and at 2
                O.C. she leaves me to get home as best I can, &#38; to get a lunch where I can; there is no <hi rend="underline">in</hi>hospitality like that
                of a fine lady from Germantown, however, no one will know when they look at her blooming cheeks
                on my canvas that the artist painted it on an empty stomach; at least so my sister
                laughs, and says.</p>
            <p>The Smiths, who have just arrived from Philadelphia tell
                me that Dr. Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/> procured Walt a man nurse; which was just
                what the dear old fellow wanted, I was so glad to hear it.</p>
            <p>Of my two friends across the pond no one knows how much I think and feel &#38; how little
                I say. I haven't written to Walt yet since his illness for I thought he might be too
                ill to open my letter. I have just received your second letter dated June 14th<ptr
                    target="loc.02203_n1"/> as well as the former in wch you spoke of your great loss. I received the
                    former a week or
                2 weeks ago.<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02203.004.jpg" type="recto"/> My dear
                friend, are you going through this hot summer without a servant?&#8212;and doing all the
                work yourself? Tell me; and tell me have you a return of any of your old ailments
                because the doctors will shake their heads if you have&#8212;you <hi
                    rend="underline">must</hi> be careful.</p>
            <p>I hope that I shall be able to be some comfort to my friends during my visit to the
                States.</p>
            <p>I can't very well manage to write a <gap reason="illegible" quantity="5" unit="char"
                    resp="#ktl"/> family letter this time as I want this to catch this afternoon's mail. Mrs.
                Costelloe's portrait is coming on, and I think that it will do me credit &#38; do think that I may see
                Walt yet in the flesh. I do rejoice in his recovery; Debbie gives very hopeful account of him, at wch I am so pleased.</p>
            <p>Answer my question Madam, do you want anything?</p>
            <p>It has been quit hot here: so hot that I lay awake all last night. I am so glad to
                hear that <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#ktl" cert="medium">Mr. S's</unclear><ptr
                        target="n0817"/> strawberries promise so well. We have had lots of rain.
                Where has Van gone?</p>
            <p>Grace<ptr target="n0890"/> is going to give a large party 75 people here
                next Saturday&#8212;week probably the day that you will receive this, between 8:30 and
                12:30 in the evening.</p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-left"/>

            <closer>
                <signed>Herb.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>Tell me more about your health and spirits? I can't think how Ed<ptr
                        target="n0589c"/> &#38; Mr S can work out in the blazing sun?</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
