<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02455">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Johnston to Walt Whitman, 3 January 1891</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Johnston</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02455</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>John Johnston</author>
                    <title>John Johnston to Walt Whitman, 3 January 1891</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1891-01-03" xml:id="dat1">January 3, 1891</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Johnston, John" ref="n4102">John Johnston</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-12-08" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02455.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02455.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02455.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">54 Manchester Road</name>
                    <name type="place">Bolton</name>
                    <name type="place">Lancashire, England</name>
                    <date when="1891-01-03">January 3rd 1891</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Old Friend,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I must thank you very cordially for your great kindness in sending me the p.c. of
                Decr 19<hi rend="underline">th</hi> 1890 which I received on New Year's Day.</p>

            <p>I cannot tell you how heart-strong I am to learn that at the time of writing it you
                were so poorly, + I sincerely hope that by this time you are feeling better, + are
                freer from the pain + distress of those internal complications which trouble you.<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02455.004.jpg" type="verso"/> While I was saddened
                by the knowledge that you were suffering physical pain I was deeply touched by the
                fact that in the midst of it all you should kindly think of me + write me such a
                tender + loving note, and I thank you from the bottom of my heart for this act of
                self-denying thoughtful friendliness which I regard as a signal proof of your
                affection for me. God bless you for this + for everything else I owe to you!</p>



            <p>The other day I received a letter from Mrs Harrison of Bideford to whom I sent a copy
                of my "Notes"&#8212;she is a daughter of the late Charles Kingsley<ptr
                    target="n0137"/> + writes under the <hi rend="underline">nom de plume</hi> of
                "Lucas Malet"&#8212;in which she says:<pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.02455.005.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> "It is most interesting to get fresh, first-hand impressions of a
                man whom one so deeply admires as I admire Walt Whitman. He is too big, too
                unconventional, ever to become popular, I fancy, either here or in the United
                States. But his thought, filtered through the minds of those few who admire + love
                him, may help to 'leaven the lump,' I hope, as time goes on. I read him with
                increasing sympathy +, I think, profit. But he writes in a language of his own +
                must be understood in a sense <hi rend="underline">of</hi> his own;"</p>
            <p>I sent a traced copy of your p.c. to Mr. Wallace<ptr target="n6121"/> + he will
                probably write to you</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.02455.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>By the way it may amuse you to know that in consequence of the extent of my "Whitman
                correspondence" he has jokingly dubbed me "Organising Secretary of the International
                Whitman Society!"</p>
            <p>We had a pleasant New Year's Day here&#8212;a hard frost with crisp, clean
                atmosphere. There is a great Carnival on New Year's Eve among the Bolton people who
                assemble in thousands on the <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="9"/>
                Square&#8212;the great central open space in the town&#8212;to listen to the band
                which plays on the Town Hall steps from 11-15pm until after midnight + upon the last
                stroke of 12 everybody wishes<pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.02455.007.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> everybody else a "Happy New Year," the band then playing "Hail,
                Smiling morn!" + afterwards "Auld Lang Syne," the "Hallelujah Chorus" + "God Save
                the Queen." Then the "fair" begins and the Saturnalia last three days</p>
            <p>I hope you all received the Christmas papers I sent + that they afforded you a little
                amusement.</p>
            <p>I notice a paragraph in this week's <hi rend="underline">Academy</hi>(London)
                announcing that you are now engaged in the preparation of your new volume, <hi
                    rend="underline">Farewell, My Fancy!</hi></p>
            <p>There is a loan collection of pictures on exhibition at<pb xml:id="leaf004v"
                    facs="loc.02455.008.jpg" type="verso"/> a newly opened museum here + this
                afternoon our Librarian suggested that I should send <choice>
                    <sic>Sydney</sic>
                    <corr>Sidney</corr>
                </choice> Morse's<ptr target="n0862"/> large portrait of <hi rend="underline"
                    >you</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>In the syllabus of the "Bolton Internation Club" I notice that Mr Duncan is put down
                to give a paper on "Walt Whitman" in April next.</p>
            <p>Mr Wallace<ptr target="n6121"/> has just been here for half an hour's chat after
                posting his letter to you. He tells me that he has also sent you a copy of the <hi
                    rend="underline">Manchester Weekly Times</hi> containing an<pb xml:id="leaf005r"
                    facs="loc.02455.009.jpg" type="recto"/> article on Bolton which I intended
                sending to you.</p>
            <p>And now as it is close upon mail time I must bring this letter to an end by again
                expressing the hope that you are keeping better + sending you my heartiest sympathy
                + good wishes + wishing you all a "Happy New Year"</p>
            <p>With best regards to all your household + with heart-love to yourself</p>


            <closer>
                <salute>remain</salute>
                <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
                <signed>J Johnston</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.02455.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
