<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04958">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">J.W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 19 September 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>J. W. Wallace</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04958</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>J. W. Wallace</author>
                    <title>J.W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 19 September 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-09-19" xml:id="dat1">September 19, 1890</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Wallace, J. W." ref="n6121">J. W. Wallace</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-11-17" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.02178.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Anderton, near Chorley.</name>
                    <name type="place">Lancashire, England</name>
                    <date when="1890-09-19">19. Sept. 1890.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Your kind post card of the 8<hi rend="underline">th</hi> inst. and papers just to
                hand. My cordial thanks to you.&#8212;</p>

            <p>D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Johnston<ptr target="n4102"/> has already told you of
                the open air meeting held by our friends last Saturday-afternoon&#8212;the 13<hi
                    rend="underline">th</hi> inst&#8212;4 miles from Bolton&#8212;<pb
                    xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.02179.jpg" type="verso"/> to hear his account of
                his visit to you and to West Hills.&#8212;It was a perfect September
                day,&#8212;warm, calm and bright, with a slight, pensive autumnal haze veiling the
                distance. We gathered together under the shade of a tree in the fields and listened
                for over an hour and a half to the D<hi rend="underline">r's</hi> story and examined
                the photos he handed round as he proceeded.<pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="loc_vm.02180.jpg" type="recto"/> It brought you very near to us all and
                every heart was stirred as the D<hi rend="underline">r</hi> told us of your great
                kindness to him, and of your kind messages to us all&#8212;since repeated, again +
                again, in your post cards to me. In the talk which followed a general feeling was
                expressed that our united gratitude, thanks + affection should be conveyed to you,
                and I was commissioned to write to you.&#8212;<pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc_vm.02181.jpg" type="verso"/> It gives me great pleasure to do so for
                our little society owes its very existence, indirectly, to you, and we are all, in
                greater or less degree, your admirers + lovers.</p>



            <p>One of the friends (Thomas Shonock) has since asked me to procure a copy of the
                pocket book edition of L. of G. for him. So I will enclose a money order for
                $22/&#8212;, I shall be glad if you will send one at your convenience.<pb
                    xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.02182.jpg" type="recto"/> I am just beginning my
                holidays (long needed) + your book accompanies me in all my rambles. I am spending
                the first few days at home and taking solitary walks in the lonely country lanes and
                on the moors near here. With you for company I have all I wish and spend blessed
                hours of sacred, vital communion with the wordless divine Spirit that informs all
                    things<pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.02183.jpg" type="verso"/> and with my
                own soul. How near and dear <hi rend="underline">you</hi> are to me I cannot tell
                you. But I am sure that no author before ever appealed to such depths of a man's
                nature, or aroused such tender, personal love. Very sure am I that your now despised
                poems will yet rank with the Hebrew Scriptures (to which alone I can compare them)
                as sacred and priceless&#8212;<pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_vm.02184.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>springing from divine depths&#8212;the latest modern revelation of
                the same Spirit.</p>
            <p>I will enclose a cutting from last weeks paper giving another instance (at a place a
                few miles from here) of the latent heroism of the roughest classes.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>With love to you always</salute>
                <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">J. W. Wallace</hi></signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
