<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01987">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Benton H. Wilson to Walt Whitman, 27
    January 1867</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Benton H. Wilson</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn
        Kruger</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska–Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01987</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc><bibl>
    <author>Benton H. Wilson</author>
    <title>Benton H. Wilson to Walt Whitman, 27 January 1867</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1867-01-27" xml:id="dat1">January 27, 1867</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 19</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Wilson, Benton H." ref="n0810">Benton H. Wilson</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-03-15" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-15" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-09-28" who="#kk">transcribed; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01987.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <body>
            <opener>
                <address><addrLine><name type="place" rend="right">Syracuse</name></addrLine></address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1867-01-27" rend="right">Jan 27<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi>/1867</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>your letter of the 10<hi rend="underline">th</hi> of
                January<!--no longer extant?--> was received more than a week ago and should have
                been answered before this time but I have not been in the humor of writing and have
                kept putting it off till some more convenient season but I will try to be more
                punctual in the future.</p>
            <p>Father is staying with me again and he borrowed "Leaves of Grass,"<!--annotation-->
                for me of Dr. Hawley<!-- <ptr target="n0295"/> --> for a few days and was very much
                interested in it, but I <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01987.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> will be candid with you. I think on the start I was more
                interested in it because it was your work than for the good sentiments it contained,
                but as I got more acquainted with it I liked it for its own value, although I <choice>
                    <orig>can not</orig>
                    <reg>cannot</reg>
                </choice> understand all of it I <choice>
                    <orig>can not</orig>
                    <reg>cannot</reg>
                </choice> find anything indecent about it. But my kind Old Friend you must not think
                that because I wrote to you and mentioned it, that I wish you to send me the Book
                for that is not what I intended for you to think.</p>
            <p>Drum Taps<!--annotation--> I have not seen yet nor is it to be found at any of the
                stores in <name>Syracuse</name>. Dr. Hawley has been trying to get a
                copy of it for about a <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01987.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> month but all that was here <choice>
                    <sic>were</sic>
                    <corr>was</corr>
                </choice> taken as soon as they arrived.</p>
            <p>We have splended sleighing here now, and have had for about, two or three weeks or
                more.</p>
            <p>You say you wish me to write how I am situated what I am doing &amp;c. I wrote to you
                a year and more ago that I was married but did not receive any reply so I did not
                know but you <choice>
                    <sic>was</sic>
                    <corr>were</corr>
                </choice> displeased with it.</p>
            <p>I was married to a <name>New York</name> Lady, Daughter of the late P.L.
                Gage of the firm of Gage, Sloans &amp; Dater
                    <!--drygoods store per Trow's NYC Directory, Vol. 71--><name>No 83
                    Chamber St and 65 <choice>
                        <sic>Reed</sic>
                        <corr>Reade</corr>
                    </choice> St</name> but like many others they went down in the crisis of 1857<!--annotation-->
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01987.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> I went into
                Business with a partner at manufacturing Parlor Brackets a little over a year ago
                and continued it about six or Seven months and lost about one thousand dollars and
                found myself in debt six hundred dollars and finally came to the conclusion that it
                was time I closed up my business, so I did so about the first of July
                last<!--1865, presumably-->, and am now at work at my trade in a Piano Forte &amp;
                Melodeon<!-- <ptr target="n0406"/> --> Manufactory and find that it pays me better than business
                on my own book. Now I think I have given you a good statement of my situation and
                hope it will be to your satisfaction</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01987.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <p>If you come to <name>New York</name> next summer on a visit I shall
                expect you to take a short trip up here to see me (if I am here) and I will pay your
                fare and take as good care of you as we possibly can. Now if you come to <name>New York</name>, you must not fail to let me know it.</p>
            <p>Hamilton<!--annotation--> has returned from the west. his Brother is gaining slowly,
                he sends his love to you and says he will write to you.</p>
            <p>Father<!-- <ptr target="n0811"/> --> is living with me now, he says he wrote to you a few days
                ago<!--Letter from Henry Wilson to Walt Whitman, January 17, 1867 (loc.02000)--></p>
            <p>My Wife wants me to send her love to you for she says she loves <choice>
                    <orig>any body</orig>
                    <reg>any body</reg>
                </choice> that I love <pb xml:id="leaf003v" type="verso"/><!--missing image from Feinberg microfilm <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01987.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>--><supplied reason="missing image" source="shively"> I devote some of my leisure to reading
                    and writing but I have not had any History except what we have got in the house
                    because I have not had access to the Libraries, but if you will write what
                    history I shall get, I will get a library ticket and try to get them. History is
                    my favorite reading. I do not know as this letter will be very interesting to
                    you so I will close for this time hoping to hear from you again
                soon.</supplied></p>


            <closer><salute>I remain as ever Your Boy Friend with
                Love</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01987.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="left" rend="underline">Atty Genls</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">B.H. Wilson, Jan 27,</note>
            <note type="authorial" place="left">ans. Jan 31, '67</note>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01987.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>