<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"
?>
<?oxygen
SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03376">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 6 September 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>O'Dowd, Bernard</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>
                    National Historical Publications and Records Commission
                </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03376</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>
                        Copyright &#169; 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                    <title>Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 6 September 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-09-06" xml:id="dat1">September 6, 1890</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8&#8211;9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">
                        The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
                    </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Dowd, Bernard." ref="n5000">Bernard O'Dowd</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03376.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline><handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                    <name type="place">
                        Supreme Court Library<lb/>
                        Melbourne
                    </name>
                    <date when="1890-09-06">
                        <handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                        9 / 6 / 90
                    </date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear master</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                If the thought of having illuminated dull lives with a burst of heaven can give you pleasure, you cannot regret having replied to my letter. I cannot reply properly; we have been treading air since.
                The occasion is so great that we must have a long space of time between us &#38; it to see, to appreciate it truly. Heartfelt thanks, Walt, from me for your letter newspapers, proof-slips and portraits.
                They shall be treasured by those who love you dearly, until they become too valuable for any private person to hold them. I wish I could waft to you the looks of Fred Woods, Jim Hartigain and Ada as they heard you
                sending them greetings (I had concelaed it till I got them together). My wife knew it was you when I came to the words "&#38; others unnamed, if any." Jim, (a most devoted admirer of you, and one who seems to have
                an intuitive perception of your meaning, an idea strikes him now &#38; then as we read &#38; although he can't get words to clothe it I see what he means <del rend="overstrike">in</del><add place="supralinear">after
                </add> a little, and can see that he had sounded deeper than we.) seemed thunderstruck at first and then his vivacity became thrilling. Fred, in grand spirits previously, became silent, almost sad, all evening.
                "His overladen heart" almost "withered itself in tears". Ada's intellectual face glowed as I have never seen it before. The sight of it would have done you good. But when we read how sadly shattered you were
                physically, our joy was damped. I could not help reechoing in my heart the wish of Mrs. Fryer,<del rend="overstrike">as she heard</del>"O the poor<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03376.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                dear old gentleman! How I wish I was near him to nurse him!" We are all a little envious of your "nurse-man" in fact, I think. Poor Ted was not here to get your greeting to him. He has gone to the stations of
                the interior, shearing. A strange life, station-life; a strange almost unique race, the station race. Wild and hot as the northwind that scorches their plains, their lives are like those plains in their
                humdrum monotony &#38; barrenness of result. A bush fire is the plains only gala day and a hearly "burst" the stockrider's. Would that a fresh manhood rose from the blasted wrecks and "lambed down" cheques of 
                the one as the young green blades hide the black of the other! They have a favourite poet, Gordon, whose strange scenery and the vacuums (I was going to say 'raging vacuums') of their solitary world-weary
                hearts. Gordon had been a stockrider himself, a gold-digger, bush policeman, member of parliament, steeplechaser and&#8212;suicide. I generally visit his grave on my birthday. Sad minor key! excuse me, Walt,
                thinking of Ted has led me into it.
            </p>
            <p>
                I don't want to tire you or I would try to tell you the story of my own life as to my "confessor." I shall only give a few fragments. Parents, Irish, catholics, father policeman. In youth, in moderate
                circumstance, but a rather lonely child. Studious never knew how to play "alleys" etc, was always "down" at "fly the garter," enjoyed reading &#38; questioning re origin of ancient Irish etc, read Paradise Lost
                at 8 Hume at nine, Virgil at 10, passed exam for a teacher at 11. Wasted time at school for a couple of years but read omnivorously. Shadows darkened meanwhile <del rend="overstrike">it</del> over family
                happiness. Do not remember a period of three <del rend="overstike">moths</del> months of home happiness since I was 9. Shifted from country into a mining city. Got on well at school, not so at home. Passed
                metric got exhibition for 6 years, held it for 2 or 3, passed <add place="supralinear" rend="marked">at</add> exam. for degree. Father died (I 15) Thought I knew what was best to do, taught Catholic school for
                3 months &#38; then thrown on my own resources. Hadn't any, I suppose. loafed about thinking I was trying to get something to do for 3 or 4 months. could only teach. no one else would have me because I was a
                Catholic, they wouldn't have me because I was a Free thinker &#38; so I fared badly.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03376.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>
                Love episode of a strange nature; as usual, with bad luck to me, "Shouldered bluey" with Ted &#38; went through 5 months strange experiences in austrailian wilds. Hard times, starvation, annihilation of soul
                almost, depradation everywhere, I touched with it as much as any I suppose. Staunch mates almost to death. I wrote a book as we wandered about, I thought it good at 18. I wrote it under the gum trees in 
                early morning as my mates lay asleep. The somnolent whiffs from the wattle seemed to inspire me at times. I sent it afterwards to a school mistress whom I loved wildly to have her opinion of it. But as she
                thought fit to forget all about it when she set her school on fire to get a paltry insurance and it perished so, I haven't tried that kind of thing since, nor am likely to. Wild joys &#38; woes of 19-21,
                I would need the pen of Sappho, Rousseau &#38; Goethe (in Werter) to describe. What I thought a marble statue became very clay &#38; woeful were its last days blasted was my life by it I fear, but O Walt, I cling to it,
                in duty's bounds to the last. I am now married to a dear, loving, pure, good firl, descended from French Huguenots, Dutch Van Tromps and Saxon Fryers. and am pretty happy. I look over the past &#38; see 
                a desert with a soul wandering aimlessly. I fear I have lost the soul for ever. Your words at times make me pulse responsive but I know it is the human "I" not the fitful, aerial marsh-fire-like "I" of the past.
                I am optimistic now, before, I was the reverse. I had a good school in a country town once &#38; gave a lecture on Spiritualism &#38; Free thought, trod honestly on the corns of the orthodox &#38; lost all my 
                pupils. Now, I can be more diplomatic, and gain the orthodox to my views with profit. I was foolish enough to start a movement for the separation of Australia from England We held two meetings &#38; I am 
                not altogether sorry now that very few heard of it. Now I can get disciples for Marx at my will.
            </p>
            <p>
                Look over the rubbish of this letter, I give you a few shreds of a failure. I believe Fame once intended to give birth to a child. Some accident happened &#38; I was the abortion. Dear Walt, I love you "with all my heart and
                all my mind" and must unburden myself a little. Much that I have said, not even my wife knows. Read it &#38; then<pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03376.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>blot it out. I am again in the midst
                of my friends conveying their good wishes and greetings to you. My word, we did keep up your birthday jollily here! It shall be a yearly affair now <add place="supralinear" rend="marked">here</add> Fred &#38;
                jim &#38; others "unnamed" before, as you guessed, the dear family whose tenderness and companionship has made my life a heaven, Mr &#38; Mrs Fryer and Ada &#38; Louise and Eve my wife all greet you,
                would, if we could, pray for you. "Tom Touchstone" (Mr. Bury) is on his way to England and America and will, I am certain, try to see you. i am forwarding him your greeting. I owe him much, for I owe him you.
            </p>
            <p>
                I believe <del rend="overstrike">your</del> the "Canterbury" edition of Leaves of Grass sells well here. The <del rend="overstrike">others are</del> large edition is hard to get. I managed to get one (McKay, Philadelphia, /84)
                after great trouble. Jim has a later one. I have also "November Boughs" &#38; the two small "Specimen Days" &#38; "Democratic Vistas". We have been trying to get Dr. Bucke's work, but haven't as yet.
                Whenever there is an essay on your works we go &#38; by rousing up a little enthusiasm manage to get <del rend="overstrike">a</del> many to read &#38; a few to like you. Occasional letters &#38; articles
                to the press we don't forget, although our power is small in that way. I compiled a kind of service book for the Secularists &#38; took the liberty of taking a verse of your "Pioneers" for a motto &#38;
                a quotation here &#38; there throughout the book. I have a book "chants of Labour" with two of your pieces to music in it. We have tried them occasionally from it. We have great difficulty with your Adam pieces,
                but since what our purest and holiest <del rend="overstrike">ones</del><add place="supralinear" rend="unmarked">friends</add> can see nothing but what is pure in them, we grow more sanguine, although these
                pieces will retard you longer than any others. Never mind, Walt, we will fight tooth &#38; nail for you as long as we live &#38; shall try to shape our lives so as to be worthy of being your soldiers.
            </p>
            <p>
                Dear Walt, I hope I haven't tired you too much, I wish I could describe myself to you, but I find that I don't know what I am. I say materialist &#38; my spiritual thirst drives me to wells of the soul, I say spiritualist
                and my logics chop me into atoms &#38; molecules and forces. I am retiring, yet vanity makes me proclaim myself, foolish, yet I hold myself wise; wise, yet I know how foolish. I am an enigma to myself. Your "To You" has
                roused me a little &#38; I can put my foot down solid sometimes small.
            </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03376.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>
                There is a sublimity in your personal character that affects me as more than has ever done, not even Christ's. Had Carlyle added another chapter to his "Hero Worship" the "Hero as Nurse" with Walt Whitman as subject would have worthily capped his 
                dome. The seeker does not always find, you, it is, not Gawaine, who have found the San Graal. May the holy chalice of comradeship ever flow with blessings to man and commemorate thy nobleness!
            </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03376.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>
                Jim &#38; I like the full length portrait best (the <del rend="overstrike">last one</del><add place="supralinear" rend="unmarked">latter one</add> especially? Ada likes the head with the hat on and Mrs. Fryer the one
                where you look so "very old." If it is a good likeness, my favourite is the frontispiece to "November Boughs"
            </p>
            <p>
                I think your influence will be powerful in Australia. One of our most characteristic, perhaps our most powerful poet, is Francis Adams, and he has been called "Whitman and Water." <del rend="overstrike">Often show your influence in the magazines.</del>
                There are some fine things in his "Songs of the Army at Night". Others show your influence too.
            </p>
            <p>
                Your word or two about our country was especially welcome, the external Federation etc movement being, I hope, the counterpart of an internal brotherhood movement. there are mighty problems awaiting solution here, in fact Democracy herself
                anxiously awaits our verdict as well as yours. I would wish to say more on this subject but have been too verbose already. 
            </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>With best love to you, Walt, and thanks for your kindness to us poor unknowns I remain your</salute>
                <signed>bernard O'Dowd</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>
                    Address&#8212;Supreme Court library Melbourne Victoria
                </p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
