<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01462">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 7 June
    1876</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Thomas Dixon</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
<persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2010</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01462</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc><bibl>
    <author>Thomas Dixon</author>
    <title>Thomas Dixon to Walt Whitman, 7 June 1876</title>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 8 Reel 5</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Dixon, Thomas" ref="n0196">Thomas Dixon</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-11-06" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-16" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-02-27" who="#al">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2011-11-11" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01462.001.jpg" type="recto"/>


            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1876-06-07">7 June: 76</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I<ptr target="n0196"/> have now received a series of papers &amp; post cards, yet
                have never once ventured to reply, &amp; I am in <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">sort</unclear> afraid you will deem me growing cold in
                my sympathy for you with my long silence. It is not so and I hope it never will be:
                I have been waiting all this time in the hopes that I might have a cheery letter to
                write you of how all goes on here in your <hi rend="underline">matters</hi>, but I
                learn from Rosetti<ptr target="n0520"/> that he is keeping you well up with news up to date, so that on
                that score I find I have no <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01462.002.jpg" type="verso"/> news to write you that you <choice>
                    <sic>wont</sic>
                    <corr>won't</corr>
                </choice> already know. so far I learn all goes on pretty well with the kind aid of
                all our English folk that care and love you they seem all to be doing their best to
                get subscribers to your <hi rend="underline">noble testimonial to</hi> your <hi rend="underline"><choice>
                        <sic>countries</sic>
                        <corr>country's</corr>
                    </choice> 100 years</hi> To me it seems a fitting and truly beautiful offering,
                and <hi rend="underline">one</hi> that I hope to see your people yet—warmly
                and tenderly appreciate at its worth. one item I deem they will never forget, I mean
                your noble services to the gallant souls who fought and eved died for the Union of
                their Land—</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01462.004.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>The reading of their memorandums made me almost weep and faint I saw you in the midst
                of them. <unclear reason="illegbile" cert="low" resp="#km">Aye</unclear> mentally I
                was near you. I heard you speak to them: I saw them look on you, grasp your hand,
                embrace you, Kiss you: the eyes of them I saw that glistened upon you. Oh man, how I
                wished while I read I was near you, to tell you how I felt for you, how I loved you,
                and even begrudged the love and sympathy you realized from these <hi rend="underline"><choice>
                        <sic>Hero's</sic>
                        <corr>Heroes</corr>
                    </choice></hi>. I fain would have been you. I feel like Ruskin when I read such
                actions of <hi rend="underline">love</hi>, that I fain would be the actor oh brave
                kind generous soul</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01462.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>in them memories of thine, why need thou care for us poor puny souls. men nursed in
                luxery's lap one may say: men who know <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#km">scant</unclear> anything <choice>
                    <sic>then</sic>
                    <corr>than</corr>
                </choice> one's petty duties from day to day, even <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">several</unclear> of them shirked too? While thou has
                been a father, mother, nurse, doctor, priest, and who can tell all, to thousands.
                Well. Well, let them rail thou and thy <hi rend="underline">work</hi>, will live in
                the hearts of these men, and in the memories of them who are in the other region:
                fear not the storm will pass by—</p>

            <!-- Missing page perhaps? There is no closing or salutation, but it skips instead to a post-script -->

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01462.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>P.S.</p>
            <p>I cannot close this note without stating that I have now placed copies of your Poems
                in all our towns' libraries, in Shields, Manchester, Newcastle, Warrington,
                Birkenhead, Liverpool, <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">London</unclear>, Plymouth, Morpeth, Tynemouth.. and other places in all I find
                I have circulated some 80 copies of <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#km">including</unclear> the English one, and American ones. so you see the
                little hand's been a working one.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01462.006.jpg" type="verso"/>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>