<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03341">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 7 December 1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="as">Ashlyn Stewart</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03341</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 7 December 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-12-07" xml:id="dat1">December 7, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MS18630, Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-01-08" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2018-09-27" who="#blh">Second check</change>
            <change when="2018-09-25" who="#as">First check</change>
            <change when="2016-10-27" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03341.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">24 Warwick Lane,</name>
                    <name type="place">E.C.</name>
                    <name type="place">London.</name>
                    <date when="1889-12-07">7<hi rend="underline">th</hi> Dec. '89.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I was glad to have the Birthday<ptr target="loc.03027_n4"/> book<ptr target="loc.03027_n3"/> the other day, with its record of so many
                friendly voices. Traubel<ptr target="n4267"/> was very good to let mine be heard so
                prominently in the throng. I believe I even blushed a little to find my lines so
                bravely in evidence.</p>
            <p>As I write, the snow is falling, &amp; the sky is leaden overhead. A regular English
                winter's day! I wonder if it is the same at Camden whose streets and ferries I
                remember best under wintry aspects. At present I am quartered at
                Hampstead,&#8212;not far away from Gilchrist's<ptr target="n0262"/> house in Well
                Road, tell him!</p> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03341.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>Hampstead is by far the highest part of London, &amp; this cottage is very near the top
                of the Heath, approaching 500 feet above the sea. I find it much healthier than the
                low-lying parts near the river. After the Welsh mountain winds, the regular London
                air is rather trying,&#8212;no oxygen, no stimulus, in it!</p>
            <p>There is much at Hampstead that you would like. The high road that runs along the top
                of the Heath, (called the Spaniards Road, &amp; passing an old inn where Skittles are
                still played, called "The Spaniards"), has a fine view down to London on the south &amp;
                the open country on the north. It is a fine walk either on a bright morning, or at
                night when the glamour in the sky &amp; the glitter of Camps below &amp; the hum of the city
                    tell<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03341.003.jpg" type="recto"/> that the
                monster, London, lies there, hydra-like, with pains untold &amp; pleasures extreme in
                his various heads.</p> 
            <p>Edith<ptr target="loc.03341_n2"/> &amp; I went to call on Miss Gilchrist<ptr target="n0890"/> on Sunday last, &amp; found
                her very well. She said that her brother would probably be home in February. Some of
                his friends were beginning to think he meant to settle oversea for good. I suppose
                he is waiting to astonish us with a <hi rend="underline">magnum opus</hi>.</p>
            <p>We have a young American novelist over here at present with his wife,&#8212;Henry
                Harland<ptr target="loc.03341_n1"/> ("Sidney Luska.") They are very bright &amp; interesting, more rapid &amp; restless
                than we slow Englischers. He however in his turn seems to be astonished at the
                immense amount of hard writing that English men of letters get through.<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03341.004.jpg" type="verso"/> "It is your sedative
                climate which makes the difference," he says in discussing it. There's no doubt that
                the English climate does tend to concentrate one's energies.</p>
            <p>For my own part, I feel now that concentration is the one thing that I lack. Too many
                distractions in this hydra-headed London. It would be good to retire for seven years
                to some mountain solitude, &amp; there, hermit-like, work out the purposes of one's
                destiny,&#8212;as Carlyle did. Meanwhile this probation in a world's city is helpful
                &amp; good, fortunately, in other ways.</p>
            <p>I suppose you had copies of the 'Illustrated London News' with your portrait. It
                figured well in the shop-windows here.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>With hearty regards to all friends.</salute>
                <signed>Earnest Rhys</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
