<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03263">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Edmund Mercer to Walt Whitman, 28 November 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Edmund Mercer</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03263</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Edmund Mercer</author>
                    <title>Edmund Mercer to Walt Whitman, 28 November 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-11-28" xml:id="dat1">November 28, 1890</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Mercer, Edmund" ref="n5000">Edmund Mercer</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-12-01" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03263.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">373 Oxford Road</name>
                    <name type="place">Manchester. England.</name>
                    <date when="1890-11-28">Nov<hi rend="underline">r</hi> 28. 1890.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear friend</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>For so you seem to me just like a grandfather whom I once knew years ago, but who
                lives in my memory as a childish recollection. No, I have never seen you with my
                physical eyes, but I feel as though I had, and it is my love for your work, and
                through that for yourself that prompt me to write you and declare it. I long thought
                of stretching out my hands across the water in greeting to you, but that diffidence
                I had lest I might be intruding unwarrantably upon your quiet has hitherto prevented
                me. This has now passed away through the kindness of a new-found friend&#8212;Dr.
                    Johnston<ptr target="n4102"/> of Bolton&#8212;who tells me he has sent you a
                copy of "Great Thoughts" containing my small addition to the literature <unclear
                    reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#ktl">appreciation</unclear> of your
                prophetic messages and high-<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03263.002.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>souled songs. May this be my excuse for thrusting my small
                personality into the path of your Kingly one.</p>

            <p>It is now about five years ago, (when I was 21, and looked something like the
                photograph I enclosed) since I first remember reading any of your poems, and that
                was in a small anthology. From that time I wished to read more of them, and, making
                discoveries for myself, I at last found "Leaves of Grass"&#8212;one of the late
                editions&#8212;and rejoiced as over a discovery of hid treasure. Needless to tell
                you, I read it through, and lost no time in buying "Specimen Days."</p>



            <p>It does not need an Indian to find my trail through the "Leaves of Grass." It is
                broad and thick. Thumb marks, ink scratches, pencil notes, and dear old
                stains&#8212;each one has its history, and is looked upon as an old friend. Even my
                Bible is not so bemarked.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03263.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>Your volume holds a princely place in my ranks of 600; for to it I owe so much of
                what is now mine, and a never-ceasing interest in all that appertains to life. My
                eyes have been opened to a truer view of the Bible, of Shakespeare&#812;yea, of all
                the great minds that have enriched mankind. And for all this&#8212;this that makes
                life so truly happy, I thank <hi rend="underline">you</hi>.</p>
            <p>I need hardly say how gratified I should be if it pleased you to write to me, if only
                a line.</p>
            <p>We may never meet on this earth, and I would like to be as near to you as possible in
                the next way&#8212;by a personal letter. In the after-days we shall surely
                meet&#8212;somehow, somewhere; and then we shall see, and know, and understand.</p>
            <p>To you&#8212;of all of the best that even God has divined here and
                hereafter&#8212;love, honour, glory and<pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.03263.004.jpg" type="verso"/> power.</p>
            <p>Good bye my master and my friend!</p>
            <p>Think that I grasp your hand as long as all may or even so little longer.</p>
            <p>Good bye, and again my thanks&#8212;as yours, "a soldier's, traveller's thanks."</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Au revoir! et &#224; Dieu</salute>
                <salute>Ever sincerely</salute>
                <signed>Edmund Mercer.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03263.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03263.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <!--There doesn't seem to be any reason to believe that loc.03264 is related to this item (see notes in tracking database) ktl-->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
