<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.04299">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Sarah Tyndale to Walt Whitman, 24 June 1857</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Sarah Tyndale</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lc">Lauren Claeys</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="em">Erel Michaelis</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt> 
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.04299</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Sarah Tyndale</author>
                    <title>Sarah Tyndale to Walt Whitman, 24 June 1857</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1857-06-24" xml:id="dat1">June 24, 1857</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 17; Reel 10–11</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00394</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Tyndale, Sarah" ref="duk.00424_n19b">Sarah Tyndale</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-14" who="#smb">final checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-12" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-06-25" who="#kjb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-13" who="#em">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-06" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-07-27" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-11-14" who="#lc">transcribed, encoded; SLIS:6335: Metadata Theories
                and Applications Class, Fall 2020, Micah Bateman, Lecturer, University of
                Iowa</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00691_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Germantown</name>
                    <date when="1857-06-24">6 mo 24.57</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener> 

            <p>Being a professed Associationist I am allowed the liberty of following my
                attractions, when they are, what all the world will say, harmless, even in despite
                of common etiquette which would demand a longer delay before answering your good
                letter of the 20th. Hector<ptr target="duk.00424_n18"/> wished me to leave it with
                him for a few days and so 'tis not before me or I might take up the several points
                of interest in order, but no matter I feel like writing to you, and the order may
                come some other time, I cannot help feeling a little gratified at finding that I am
                not so different from other thinking people, in that I am disposed to think some bad
                things of myself, we ought not to be partial to ourselves, ought we? in your case
                however I must say that I think your judgment of yourself is rather severe, I have
                not changed my opinion, which I gave you when speaking of the false report of
                    Emmersons<ptr target="n1044"/> fastidiousness <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.00692_large.jpg" type="verso"/> that if he or any one else expected
                    <hi rend="underline">common</hi> etiquette from you, after having read Leaves of
                Grass they were sadly mistaken in your character where etiquette, or what is <hi rend="underline">called</hi> refined and exquisite taste <hi rend="underline">predominate</hi>. I never expect to find much originality of character, however
                this is rather an implication where I did not intend it I will have none of it, but
                try to be myself</p>
            <p>I entirely coincide with you in what will be the result of greater experience on the
                part of the exponents of the two views of matter &amp; spirit as to the priority of
                either. I find them always coexisting, and do not intend to trouble myself for any
                other solution, I only ask to use in <choice>
                    <sic>refference</sic>
                    <corr>reference</corr>
                </choice> to each, the terms that will convey my ideas to the minds of others as
                truely as I am capable of conveying them. I do think that the greater part of the
                difficulties that exist among men on <choice>
                    <sic>all most</sic>
                    <corr>almost</corr>
                </choice> all theological and <choice>
                    <sic>phylosophical</sic>
                    <corr>philosophical</corr>
                </choice> subjects arise from the different modes of expressing the same ideas.</p>
            <p>I am glad you have been to see Mrs W. I felt the same sympathy for her, her life
                is not exactly in accordance with her highest views of humanity <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00693_large.jpg" type="recto"/> hence the <choice><sic>unhappyness</sic><corr>unhappiness</corr></choice>, but 
                she will ultimately be the better woman for the experience, do any of
                us live up to our highest sense of human privileges? I <choice>
                    <sic>supose</sic>
                    <corr>suppose</corr>
                </choice> you come nearer to it, than anyone I know but I doubt the propriety of
                entire <sic>disenthralment</sic> blind instinct must govern where it is the
                governing faculty, but in man reason predominates &amp; must govern, no matter what
                mere instinct proposes as a means of happiness. if the great family is not ready to
                go with the idea, we must yield to their needs, we can not, ought not, live
                alone.</p>
            <p>You have made my heart rejoice by telling me of the breadth of the Revd Mr Porter,<ptr target="hun.00046_n10"/> is it? (I have not the letter here) verily us, would be
                progretionists are put on the back ground by some who have been by them pronounces
                pharasees and hypocrates, Were you not pleased with Mr Bellows'<ptr target="n0499d"/> views of the Drama? I find in myself a propensity to
                feel and to say, (and why should I not say it?) Thank God for the great influx of
                light, love, joy, and beauty which is every where manifest. I can not help comparing
                the present with past <choice>
                    <sic>earas</sic>
                    <corr>eras</corr>
                </choice> of cruelty and carnage. When men dare not express a thought outside the
                Church inclosure. I am not blaming the good people who inflicted the tortures, if
                they thought they were sending a brother to Heaven thereby— <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00694_large.jpg" type="verso"/> I am only
                rejoicing that the race is so expanded that each now (in this glorious land of the <choice>
                    <sic>seting</sic>
                    <corr>setting</corr>
                </choice> sun at least) dare to speak for himself taking only for his bound, the
                best interests of Man as he is, and not the dogmas of any set of men only see how I
                am running on, as if I were writing to school boy who had never thought all these
                childish things. but you will forgive me since 'tis myself, and I will try to do
                better</p>
            <p>There was one expression in your letter, which I hope you will allow me to refer too,
                in good faith. You say that Fowler &amp; Wells<ptr target="loc.02340_n3"/> are not
                the right men to publish Leaves of Grass. I am sure they are not, I can tell you
                more of their malpractice about it, when you come. You say also that they are <hi rend="underline">willing</hi> to give up the plates, now it occured to me that
                it was quite possible that some <choice>
                    <sic>trifeling</sic>
                    <corr>trifling</corr>
                </choice> money consideration prevented you from obtaining them, and although I have
                now but little money at my command I thought I would take the liberty of saying to
                you that if the small sum of Fifty Dollars would be of any use to you for the
                purpose I should be most happy to send that amount to you. I feel that I shall be
                understood and therefore make no apology.</p>
            <p>A young friend of mine Miss Matty Griffith<ptr target="loc.04299_n1"/> a native of
                Kentucky author of Autobiography of a Female Slave, and an excellent &amp; lovely
                woman had her book published by I think Redfield<ptr target="n0499c"/> &amp; he also
                has I understand treated her very meanly although he knows she is poor, and is
                suffering</p>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>