<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.02978">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 3 July 1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ellen M. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02978</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ellen M. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>Ellen M. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 3 July 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-07-03" xml:id="dat1">July 3, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 13, Reel 8</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, 
                    Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, Ellen M." ref="n4137">Ellen M. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-06-26" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2017-07-21" who="#if">checked</change>
            <change when="2017-04-27" who="#cb">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-10-06" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02978.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">1015 O St. N. W.</name>
                    <name type="place">Washington D. C.</name>
                    <date when="1889-07-03">July 3<hi rend="underline">d</hi> 1889.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt,</salute> 
            </opener>
            <p>I was on the point of writing you when this minute 8.30 A. M. the postman just gave
                me your card. Yes, I am in the same place, the little house where we have lived
                almost 21 years &#38; paid rent enough to buy it twice over. How long I shall be here,
                or what I am to do in the future is all a problem. I am sorry to tell you that after
                all my careful economy &#38; saving, the various things into which William<ptr
                    target="n2002"/> had put <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02978.002.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>money are mostly worthless, <hi rend="underline">inventions</hi>
                that are good for nothing but to swallow up good money. Then in these last years
                since this illness began in 1884 his expenses have been enormous, &#38; the bills of
                doctors, &#38;c. very heavy. He has also
                been most lavish &#38; generous to the poor &#38; needy, &#38; to the <hi rend="underline"
                    >causes</hi> in which he believed, &#38; the result is almost nothing left for me.
                Mr. Kimball<ptr target="loc.03298_n11"/> who knew more of all this probably than I,
                (I mean the bad investments) came to see me soon after William's death<ptr target="loc.02978_n1"/><pb
                    xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02978.003.jpg" type="recto"/> to say that if things
                were as they used to be, he could make a place for me in the office &#38; take me right
                in there, but that under the Civil Service rules, even if I should pass a good
                examination, one must wait till there is a vacancy in the State to which one is
                accredited, &#38; that might be <hi rend="underline">five</hi> years! But he said that
                he would try very hard to get me into the Census bureau which is soon to be
                organized! I hoped then that I should not need it, but the revelations from<pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02978.004.jpg" type="verso"/> day to day seem to
                make the outlook worse &#38; worse financially, &#38; I have just sent him a note, &#38; shall
                tell him that if I can fill any position, shall be grateful for it.</p>
            <p>But first I must go away &#38; rest. I have had no manner of rest since William had the first attack a
                year ago last January, &#38; I am really broken, &#38; these late revelations have helped to
                make me ill; <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#ktl">tho'</unclear> I
                did make a solemn &#38; holy vow that I would <hi rend="underline">not</hi> worry about
                what has been &#38; can't<pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.02978.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                be helped. But I am, or have been ill, so ill as to alarm the neighbors, but not
                myself. Then, too, I am alone, since Harold Channing<ptr target="loc.02978_n2"/> went home, &#38; I find that is not good for
                me.</p>
            <p>I go to New England, &#38; then in the autumn, return here, whether to break up &#38;
                vacate forever this little house, I know not. Indeed the way now looks very dark,
                but I try to trust &#38; hope &#38; confide in the loving care that always guides us.</p>
            <p>I did so plead with William, always, to try with me to buy a <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="loc.02978.006.jpg" type="verso"/>little, little house, so that we might
                have a home; but it was not to be, &#38; so it must be right.</p>

            <p>Yes, I have from day to day, rec'd. the papers, &#38; all the many reminders of your
               thought to me, thanks for <hi rend="underline">all</hi>, &#38; the copy of "Passage to
                India," &#38; the account of birth-day celebration, &#38;c. From day to day I wanted to
                write, but have had such discouraging &#38; disheartening work to do, &#38; so much of it, &#38;
                so many the papers &#38; letters to go over, &#38; the work is only <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="loc.02978.007.jpg" type="recto"/>begun; for in the last four or five years
                William has not kept his affairs in the order that he used to, his illness has told
                upon him in many ways. But I have been trying my best to put into order; but must
                soon drop all &#38; go for a time, or I shall not be able to get away. When I go, will
                send you my address, so that if you are disposed you can still keep me in mind by
                papers &#38; whatever you please to send.</p>

            <p>You are mistaken,<pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.02978.008.jpg" type="verso"/> dear
                Walt, in saying that I have not written you since dear William's death. The <hi
                    rend="underline">first</hi> letter that I wrote was to you, on the very day, May
                    9<hi rend="underline">th</hi> I have had several most <hi rend="underline"
                    >vivid</hi> dreams of you. So distinct that all the next day I felt as if I had
                been with you; &#38; I wonder whether my "astral body" went to you, or yours came to me.</p>
                <p>A day or two before William passed away he awoke from a nap &#38; asked me "if Walt
                    had<pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.02978.009.jpg" type="recto"/> gone?" I said
                you had not been here, but he repeated the question, &#38; then I said yes, you had
                gone.</p>
            <p>I can't, I can't possibly believe that he is gone, I find myself looking for
                him daily,&#8212;&#38; the only time I have seen him since he departed this life was the
                day that I was so ill; &#38; he then looked perfectly well &#38; young, &#38; as he he did in
                the <hi rend="underline">L</hi> St. house.<pb xml:id="leaf005v"
                    facs="loc.02978.010.jpg" type="verso"/> I hope you get a copy of his last
                literary work, "Mr. Donnelly's Reviewers," I asked to have one sent you. If you see
                any notice of it, shall be very glad if you will send me.</p>
            <p>If ever the people that owe money to William would pay me, I should not be so worried
                about my daily expenses, for one can't break up in a minute, &#38; if I can keep on by
                having some one with me to<pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.02978.011.jpg" type="recto"/> help share the
                expenses when I come back, till I can see <hi rend="underline">what</hi> to do. It
                is like taking my life to have to give up a <hi rend="underline">home</hi> with no
                prospect of ever having one again. It is the only <hi rend="underline">earthly</hi>
                possession that I ever longed for.</p> 
            <p>So I said, I will keep you informed of my whereabouts.</p> 
            <closer> 
                <salute>&#38; with love always&#8212;</salute>
                <signed>Nelly O'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.02978.012.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
