<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.03183">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Sidney H. Morse to Walt Whitman, 14 March 1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Sidney H. Morse</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="es">Jeannette Schollaert</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.03183</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Sidney H. Morse</author>
                    <title>Sidney H. Morse to Walt Whitman, 14 March 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-03-14" xml:id="dat1">March 14, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 13</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Morse, Sidney H." ref="n0862">Sidney H. Morse</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-08-17" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-06-01" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-11-04" who="#es">transcribed, encoded</change> 
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03183.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/> 
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Richmond Ind.</name>
                    <date when="1888-03-14" rend="right">March 14th. 88</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt;</salute>  
            </opener>
            <p>The Hicks bust<ptr target="loc.03183_n1"/> has probably reached you by this time, or, is in Phila. It was sent first of the week. I used it at my talk last week. Think I shall put up another for my own use. I have taken a studio
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03183.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            here, and am busy getting up an entertainment to come off in the <hi rend="underline">Grand Opera House</hi> two weeks from Monday next—"A Day's life in a Sculptor's Studio." 3 parts—or acts— Morning, afternoon &amp; evening. Assisted by the Y.M.C.A. Senate. This Senate is a debating society of the Y.M.C.A &amp; all the fellows are <hi rend="underline">enthusiastic</hi> over my enterprise. I give
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03183.003_large.jpg" type="rectp"/>
            half the proceeds to the Y.M.C.A. a part of which the <hi rend="underline">Senate</hi> is to have for a library. They are all bright fellows &amp; full of vim, <choice><sic>fredom</sic><corr>freedom</corr></choice>, &amp; fun. The awful burden of New England orthodoxy does not bear heavily upon their souls—not even the Elders are <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#es">grim</unclear> with the idea of salvation. I find I can co-operate with them &amp; do my work
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03183.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                on common ground. They have sent for <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#smb">fotos</unclear> of the <hi rend="underline">founder</hi> of the Y.M.C.A who lives in London "Exeter Hall,"<ptr target="loc.03183_n2"/> they say, "is the result of a little prayer meeting that took place in his room over forty years ago." I am to make a bust of him, with the idea of selling copies to the "Y.M.C." associations 
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03183.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            throughout the country. When you consider that they are thicker than plums in a pudding, the prospect seems good for a sale of many copies—especially if it starts with the approbation of leading "associations" in Phila &amp; New York. I am really glad to do this work—If it puts "boodle" in my purse, it will also impart a
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03183.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            certain new life to the rising swarm of human "critters" these associations gather together.</p>         
            <p>My exhibition will include a variety of things. On the stage in rear I shall have my assistants as a modeling class, dressed in grey tunics. I shall be in regalia myself—long gown &amp; appropriate head piece. The fellows will furnish glee club, &amp; grand &amp; lofty trebling.
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03183.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            During the noon interruption between 1st 2nd parts, they will (draped in white with powdered faces &amp; hands) form a pyramid climbing upon one another as high as the ceiling, to be ready the moment the curtain rises, as I enter upon the stage, to tumble to the ground or floor—so much fallen statuary. They do this thing to perfection &amp; it creates an uproar. I am to have busts &amp; all things I can obtain
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03183.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            pertaining to studio well <choice><sic>equiped</sic><corr>equipped</corr></choice>. The modeling room will be rear of stage, so it can be shut off with curtains on occasion. I shall have visitors, women &amp; <hi rend="underline">art patron</hi> and children, boys &amp; girls come in for instruction—sort of <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#if" cert="medium"><choice><orig>Kindergarden</orig><reg>Kindergarten</reg></choice></unclear>. And much more, but all finally so arranged &amp; compacted that it will run smooth &amp; occupy 2½ hours.</p>                    
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03183.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>There are certain reasons why I desire to make a short address before the curtain at the start. Some things to say that will awaken the <hi rend="underline">religiousness</hi> of art in America democratically considered. Ten minutes will suffice. Between acts then will be music &amp; stereoptican views on curtains. I will send you perfected program. I will put my best work into the business, &amp; if it
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03183.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                is a <hi rend="underline">hit</hi>, the way may open for all we have talked about. I am going to send for my Cleveland statue &amp; your bust.<ptr target="loc.03183_n3"/></p>
            <p>I had an invite to go to Indianapolis for a lecture to the Y.M.C.A there, last night. Shall probably drift that way in due season.</p> 
            <p>I have an idea it doesn't matter <hi rend="underline">where</hi> one starts. So he starts, even in a small way. The continuation, if he has got anything worth c, will follow—You 
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03183.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>know the scripture—faithful over a few things first, &amp; then rules over many.<ptr target="loc.03183_n4"/>—</p>
            <p>To change the subject—what a storm your way! Are you also snowed in? Is the back yard filled with snow up to your sitting room window? The window where the little <choice><sic>bantums</sic><corr>bantams</corr></choice> enter for their roost in the cellar. No snow here, but cold, cold, cold.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03183.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>Mother begins to feel wearied by it all, and longs for the green grass &amp; birds, so she can get out, &amp; stir up her rheumatic limbs. Every time there is the first approach to warmishness outdoors—&amp; we have had several spring suggesting days—she starts out on her pilgrimage about the yard, &amp; to the shop where she sits &amp; chats with the store workers. I wish you could see her. I think (<choice><orig>tho</orig><reg>though</reg></choice> she is my mother) she is a fine specimen of an old lady: so calm &amp; broad; large &amp; cheerful. 
            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03183.013_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                And I find she is one of the very best of readers. Her voice is still clear &amp; strong—musical and persuasive. She weighs now not far from 190 lbs; but is not what you would call fat. Her cheeks are plump &amp; solid. She takes the liveliest interest in the daily papers, &amp; the illustrations. Says "I read advertisements as much as anything, for there I find out what's going on about as much as anywhere." If she were not quite so old, I think
            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03183.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            I would start out with her on a <hi rend="underline">starring</hi> tour. I'd like to introduce the <hi rend="underline">Queen</hi> to her.—</p>
            <p>I often think of you and Mrs. Davis<ptr target="n6113"/> there with your daily round of "so, so" and "all the same." Your simple good dinners, beef &amp; rice fritters, &amp; the tea pot, and the visitors, all welcome without ado—except when they come to <hi rend="underline">convert</hi> you.</p>
            <p>Please show Mrs. D. this letter, &amp; ask her if she knows Brown's address. I wrote him &amp; the letter comes back. He thinks
            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc.03183.015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            I am sure I have treated him badly; but I am not at fault—I gave the old address—at least.</p>
            <p>Do you hear from Herbert?<ptr target="n0262"/> I do not hear from Harned;<ptr target="loc.03745_n1"/> but I suppose he must be all right again. Isn't about the time Dr. Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/> was with you? What about O'Connor?<ptr target="n2002"/> Do you hear from him? I got no paper or letter from Kennedy<ptr target="n3039"/> of late.</p>
            <p>Well, the sun shines brightly, but the air is cold. I am very comfortable &amp; quiet though, in my new studio, and 
            <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc.03183.016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                in excellent health. Last Saturday one of the fellows drove me out four miles &amp; we got a barrel of nice clay—dug it right out of a side hill—not a mite of dirt or gravel in it. Fine as satin. I felt like doffing my hat to old Dame nature. I went on a <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#if">piece</unclear> to one of his "farmer friends" to  dinner, &amp; had a good ride on a horse's back, the first for 20 years. You must understand this is no "pent up Utica,"<ptr target="loc.03183_n5"/> but spreads out infinitely. Next time I must tell you something of Earlham (Quaker) College — a mile out. I took
            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc.03183.017_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            tea out there with the Scholars some 150 in all one evening last week. Had some talk with the president. He is evidentaly touched with the new spring tide in modern world. Quite a senisible, good man.</p>
            <p>Well, it will tire you out to read this <choice><sic>lenthy</sic><corr>lengthy</corr></choice> epistle. I am most ashamed to send it, so <hi rend="underline">garrulous</hi> it will seem. But, you've been through so much, it may not overwhelm you.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Kind regards.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Sidney.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>If Horace should drop in, &amp; he <gap reason="illegible" quantity="2" unit="words"/> to objection, let him see this letter. I haven't time to write him just now.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
        <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc.03183.018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
    </text>
</TEI>