<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.07545"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 5 January 1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.07545</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Horace Traubel</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ht">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Mitchell Kennerley</publisher>
                            <date notBefore="1914" notAfter="1914">1914</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">440&#8211;441</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr> 
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 5 January 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-01-05" xml:id="dat1">January 5, 1889</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-04-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-02-11" who="#bjo">second check</change>
            <change when="2018-12-07" who="#blh">first check</change>
            <change when="2016-11-12" who="#aa">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">London,</name>
                    <date when="1889-01-05">5th Jany, 1888<ptr target="loc.07545_n1"/></date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman</hi>.</p>
            <p>Your card of the 24th came two days ago,<ptr target="loc.07545_n2"/> not a little to
                my relief. I was beginning to fear lest you were not so well again. This year ought
                to treat you well, and give you the wind and weather and everything that you love,
                seeing that in it you attain three score and ten. If good wishes of friends were of
                any direct use, physically, I mean, as well as in other ways, it would be the
                happiest year of your life. It seems very right and fit that in it you should
                publish the <hi rend="italic">edition definitive</hi> in this vol. of your "complete
                works,"<ptr target="n4151"/> which we all so eagerly expect.</p>
            <p>The last few weeks have brought nothing perhaps that is very remarkable to the
                surface here. I have been jogging along quietly enough,&#8212;but absorbing always a
                great deal humanly from the endlessly wonderful life of this great London. One of
                the most striking episodes I have lately had any share in was the midnight meeting
                of the unemployed of London on Christmas eve. It was held at the foot of Cleopatra's
                Needle, round the base of which the various speakers were grouped, faced by the
                motley throng of men, who cheered hoarsely with hungry throats as the speechifying
                went on. Through the day it had been wet and foggy in turn, but now the sky was of
                an American clearness, the half moon shining bright behind the shaft of Cleopatra's
                Needle, contrasting strangely with the red torches held to light the orators.
                Altogether an impressive scene; and when the Christmas bells rang out, and one of
                the speakers called out&#8212;"Peace on earth, good will towards men! If Jesus were
                in London today would he be in those churches?"&#8212;and the crowd shouted back,
                "No! he'd be here!&#8212;here with us!"&#8212;the effect was dramatic in the
                extreme.</p> 
            <p>When I had been standing in the crowd for some time, I discovered Jo Pennell,<ptr target="n4322"/> the
                artist, standing near me, and we presently went home together. He lives in the next
                street to Cowley Street, from which, by the way, I may have to move shortly, as a
                sister (whom you know) is coming up to town to study music at the Academy.</p>
            <p>I am writing this at the reading room of the British Museum. I must end it rather
                hurriedly. Don't let me forget to tell you that last night I saw Edward
                    Carpenter<ptr target="n0141b"/>&#8212;the first time in three years&#8212;at a
                meeting of the Fabian Society,<ptr target="loc.07545_n4"/> where he lectured. He looks older than he
                did&#8212;more nervous lines in his face. As he is staying in town we shall probably
                meet again.</p>
            <p>The Scottish Art Review wants me to write an article on The Portraits of Walt
                Whitman,<ptr target="loc.07545_n5"/> with portrait reproductions. Can you send any new pictures of yourself? For
                the present time, so long!</p> 
            <closer> 
                <signed>Ernest Rhys</signed> 
            </closer>
        </body>  
    </text>
</TEI>
