<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01231">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 12 July 1874</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Edward Carpenter</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
<persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
<persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01231</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>    
        
<bibl>
    <author>Edward Carpenter</author>
    <title>Edward Carpenter to Walt Whitman, 12 July 1874</title>    
    <date cert="high" when="1874-07-12" xml:id="dat1">July 12, 1874</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
            
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Carpenter, Edward" ref="n0141b">Edward Carpenter</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-10-19" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-02" who="#js">proofed, added envelope encoding</change>
            <change when="2012-02-23" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-10-26" who="#ej">Transcribe/Encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01231.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <address><addrLine>Trinity Hall,</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cambride, England</name>.</addrLine><addrLine/></address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1874-07-12">12. July 1874</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear friend</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>It is just dawn, but there is light enough to write by, and the birds in their old sweet fashion are chiping in the little College Garden outside. My first knowledge of you is all entangled with that little garden. But that was six years ago; so you must not mind me writing to you now because you understand, as I understand, that I am not drunk with <hi rend="underline">new</hi> wine.</p>
            
            <p>My chief reason for writing (so I put it to myself) is that I can't help wishing you should know that there are many here in England to whom your writings have been as the waking
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01231.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                up to a new day. I daresay you do not care, particularly, how your writings, as such, are accepted; but I know that you do care that those thoughts you weary not to proclaim should be seized upon by others over the world and become the central point of their lives, and that something even transcending all thought should knit together us in England &amp; you in America by ties closer than thought &amp; life itself. When I say 'many', of course I do not mean a multitude (I wish I did) but many individuals&#8212;each, himself (or herself, for they are mostly women&#8212;fluid, courageous &amp; tender) the centre of a new influence. All that you have said, the thoughts that you have given us, are vital&#8212;they will grow&#8212; that is certain. You cannot know
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01231.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                anything better than that you have spoken the word which is on the lips of God today.</p>
            
            <p>And here, though dimly, I think I see the new, open, life which is to come: the spirit moving backwards &amp; forwards beneath the old forms<!-- I could also see "focus" here, but I agree that "forms" seems more likely. -JS -->&#8212;strengthening &amp; re-shaping the foundations <hi rend="underline">before</hi> it alters the superstructure: the growth is organic too here I believe, but the flower is very very far and we do not dare to think even what it will be like.<space dim="horizontal" extent="8 letters"/>There is no hope, almost none, from English respectability. Money eats into it, to the core. The Church is effete. At school the sin which cannot be Forgiven is a false quantity. The men are blindly material; low-to the most intellectual&#8212;Art &amp; the desire for something like religion are only known as a continual sense of pain. Yet the women will
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01231.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                save us. I wish I could tell you what is being done by them&#8212;everywhere&#8212;in private &amp; in public. The artisans too are shaping themselves. While society is capering &amp; grimacing over their heads they are slowly coming to know their minds; and exactly as they come to know their minds they come to the sense of power to fulfil them: and sweet will the day be when the tongs are wrested from the hands of the children and they too <hi rend="underline">have</hi> to become men.<space dim="horizontal" extent="14 letters"/>You hardly know, I think, in America (where the life, though as yet material, is so intense) what the relief is here to turn from the languid inanity of the well fed, to the clear hard lines of the workman's face.<space dim="horizontal" extent="7 letters"/>Yesterday there came (to mend my door) a young workman with the old divine light in his eyes&#8212;even <hi rend="underline">I</hi> call it old though
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01231.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                I am not 30&#8212;and perhaps, more than all, he has made me write to you.∥ Because you have, as it were, given me a ground for the love of men I thank you continually in my heart. (&#8212;and others thank you, though they do not say so.) For you have made men to be not ashamed of the noblest instinct of their nature. Women are beautiful; but, to some, there is that <choice><abbr>wh-</abbr><expan>which</expan></choice> passes the love of women.</p>
            
            <p>It is enough to live wherever the divine beauty of love may flash on men; but indeed its real &amp; enduring light seems infinitely far from us in this our day. Between the splendid dawn of Greek civilization and the high universal noon of Democracy there is a strange horror of darkness on us. We look face to face upon each other, but we do not know.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01231.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>At the last, it is enough to know that the longed for realisation is possible&#8212;will be, has been, <hi rend="underline">is</hi> even now somewhere&#8212;even though we find it not. The pain of disappointment is, somewhere, the joy of friction<!-- Eder/Kevin saw fiction; I also saw fruition. All of which make sense in the context. I believe friction best matches the appearance of the word on the page. -JS -->.<space dim="horizontal" extent="14 letters"/>Perhaps it will be, in time, with you in the New or with us in the Old world.<space dim="horizontal" extent="5 letters"/>Slowly&#8212;I think&#8212;the fetters are falling from men's feet, the <hi rend="underline">cramps</hi> &amp; crazes of the old superstitions are relaxing, the idiotic ignorance of class contempt is dissipating. If men shall learn to accept one another simply &amp; without constraint, if they shall cease to regard themselves because the emptiness of vanity is filled up with love, and yet shall honour the free immeasurable gift of their own personality, delight in it &amp; bark in it without false shames &amp; affectations&#8212;then your work will be accomplished: and men
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.01231.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                for the first time will know of what happiness they are capable.</p>
            
            <p>Dear friend, you are older &amp; wiser than me &amp; can accept all that I have said, with a smile perhaps, but without any ill will. It is a pleasure to me to write to you, for there are many things which I find hard to say to any one here. And for my sake you must not mind reading what I have written.<space dim="horizontal" extent="11 letters"/>As to myself, I was in order; but I have given that up&#8212;utterly. It was no good. Nor does the university <hi rend="underline">do</hi>: there is nothing vital in it. Now I am going away to lecture to working men &amp; women in the North. They at least desire to lay hold of something with a real grasp. And I can give something of mathematics &amp; science. It may be no use, but I shall see.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.01231.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>You I suppose I shall not see. Yet if any one should come from your side to England&#8212;this address will always find me. There are many who, if their pens were here, would send greetings to you across the sea.</p>
            
            <p>Farewell: wherever the most common desires &amp; dreams of daily life are&#8212;wherever the beloved opposition is, of hand to hand or of soul to soul&#8212;I sometimes think to meet you.</p>
            <p>I have finished this at night. All is silent again:</p>
           
            <closer>
                <salute> and as at first I am yours</salute>
                <signed>Edward Carpenter.</signed>
                
           
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.01231.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
               
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.01231.0010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
              
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>