<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.03337">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 22–24 April 1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>      
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>   
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588–4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2020 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.03337</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 22–24 April 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" notBefore="1889-04-22" notAfter="1889-04-24" xml:id="dat1">April 22–24, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 15, Reel 9</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00325</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="n4152">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-12-10" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-05-30" who="#if">Second check</change>
            <change when="2019-03-29" who="#blh">First check</change>
            <change when="2017-04-14" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03337.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Westminster,</name>
                    <name type="place">London, S.W.<ptr target="loc.03337_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1889-04-22">22<hi rend="underline">d</hi> April 1889.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This letter was to have been written five days ago; but, like many other things that
                I project, it had to be put off a while. Lately there have been many small events to
                break through the usual run of things, &amp;, as you know, I have not a genius for
                despatch at any time. So letters &amp; other writings have gone to the wall.</p>
            <p>Last week my brother, Percy, who is an actor, came up to town with the news that he
                was going off to South Africa on a six-months'
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03337.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                tour. He sails to-morrow afternoon by the "Norham Castle" from Blackwall, &amp;
                to-day my Father &amp; Mother, anxious to see the last of their boy, have arrived to
                bid him farewell. With them came also two old friends of mine,—Will Dircks,<ptr target="n7039"/> who
                is now Walter Scotts' right-hand man in the literary part of the publishing, and
                Joseph Skipsey,<ptr target="loc.03310_n4"/> poet of north-country mining life, typical in rugged personal
                strength &amp; general appearance of the Northumbrian coal-fields. It was a striking
                sight to see the crowds of holiday-makers who poured out of the excursion &amp;
                other trains, when my brother &amp; I
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03337.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                went to meet these travellers early this morning. Easter Monday is a great day with
                both the Londoners, who go off into the country, and the country-folk, who come to
                London, to spend a holiday. Fortunately too, the sun is shining in a way to remind me
                of New York &amp; Washington, &amp; the Spring is making great progress in park
                &amp; garden. If this sunshine lasts, the trees will soon be in full leaf, &amp;
                then—Hey, for the life of the fields. Already—feeling somewhat pent up
                here in town—I think of a jaunt to North Wales, there to climb mountains and
                make friends with sun &amp; wind &amp; rain!  
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03337.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                Before that, however, there is Paris &amp; the Exhibition to tempt one over the
                Channel. It is absurd that I have never yet found my way to France. One feels that
                over there one should have plenty of money to spend, and failing this I have waited
                &amp; waited. But now there is little excuse for waiting longer, as excursions are
                being run at such low rates. So possibly the next letter you have from me will be
                dated Paris. In America I became infected somewhat with the itch for travel, &amp;
                suppose I shall not rest now till I have wandered all over the globe.</p>
            <p><date when="1889-04-24"><hi rend="underline">24th April</hi></date>
             I take up the thread of this rough and
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03337.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
               ready scribble again, after two days' interval. Yesterday I went down to Blackwall to
                see my brother stowed safely on board the "Norham Castle." She is a fine, large
                boat, comfortably fitted, &amp; well officered; &amp; there was an interesting lot
                of passengers—including the actors &amp; actresses of the Corp. which my brother has
                joined: I felt quite inclined to go off too. There is a great rush to South Africa
                at present—owing to the contagion of the gold &amp; diamond mining fever.
                Several fine young fellows of my acquaintance—engineers &amp;c. have gone out
                to Kimberley within the past year.</p>     
            <p>This morning I have been visiting various studios with Joseph Skipsey. This afternoon
                he has gone to see Oscar Wilde.<ptr target="loc.03337_n2"/> It is good fun going about
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03337.006.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                town with an outsider, a north-countryman like Skipsey, for he sees everything with
                such original eyes,—going into raptures over the flowers in Covent Garden
                Market, or the gleaming fish on the fish stalls. It is surely a great thing to have
                that fresh &amp; poetic sense of these everyday details—that the over-cultured
                London man takes no interest in.</p> 
            <p>In the same way, it was pleasant to hear Alys Smith<ptr target="n7014"/> a few days back, when she had
                just returned from Italy &amp; the Riviera, talking about London with as much
                enthusiasm as ever. She called the other afternoon, greatly to my sister Edith's
                delight, &amp; gave us a characteristic account of her adventures. Logan<ptr target="n6122"/> often comes
                in too. The other day
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03337.007.jpg" type="recto"/>
                he &amp; his father drove round here, &amp; in my absence carried off Edith, who had
                never seen them before, for a long drive in the park. I have not seen Mrs. Costelloe<ptr target="loc.02189_n1"/>
                of late. She has been rather unwell, ever since the baby's birth, &amp; now she
                &amp; her husband<ptr target="n3133"/> are staying down in Surrey.</p>
            <p>I hear by the House of Parliament clock that is nearly post-time, so I must bring my
                gossip to an end. Next letter I must try &amp; send you a more solid kind of
                writing,—but one cannot always be solid.</p>
            <p>Logan Smith said that his sister had had a card from you lately. I hope that this
                means you are getting stronger &amp; easier with the incoming of the Spring.
                Remembrances to Mrs. Davis,<ptr target="n6113"/> Gilchrist<ptr target="n0262"/> &amp; all other friends</p>
            <closer> 
                <salute>with love, yours</salute>
                <signed>Ernest Rhys</signed>  
            </closer> 
            <postscript> 
                <p><date when="1889-04-24"><hi rend="underline">24th<ptr target="loc.03337_n3"/></hi></date> General Boulanger<ptr target="loc.03337_n4"/> arrived in London this
                    afternoon,—another note in the Cosmopolitan symphony. London will get some
                    fun out of him—if nothing else. He seems somewhat doubtfully heroic.</p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03337.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>