<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.00453">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 25 March 1869</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
            <editor>Dennis Berthold</editor>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
               <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>

               <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
               <persName xml:id="al">April Lambert</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2008</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.00453</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2008 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson Whitman</author>
               <title>Thomas Jefferson Whitman  to Walt Whitman, 25 March 1869</title>
               <date when="1869-03-25">March 25, 1869</date>
               <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
               <persName key="Whitman, Thomas Jefferson" ref="n4995">Thomas Jefferson Whitman</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
               <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#ak" when="2015-02-09">corrected orgName, added pbs, added choice tags</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2013-11-22">converted to P5</change>
         <change who="#el" when="2008-07-21">updated TEI header</change>
         <change who="#kk" when="2008-04-01">checked and proofed</change>
         <change who="#al" when="2006-10-03">Transcribed, Encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_ad.00497.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <name type="place">St. Louis,</name>
                  <date when="1869-03-25">March 25th 1869</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We have just had a letter from Mother telling us <choice><abbr>abt</abbr><expan>about</expan></choice> George's troubles in getting money for the house and how you stepped in and helped him out.<ptr target="loc.00453_n1"/> I am mighty glad that you was able to do it for I feared that George might have the blues and Mother get downhearted</p>
         <p>Mat and I and the cubs have had a high old time for the last week or two. I wrote you <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_ad.00498.jpg" type="verso"/>when we left the hotel to go to a sort of hotel where they sent meals to the room "Hotel Garni"<ptr target="loc.00453_n2"/> they called it  we lived quite comfortably for awhile but it got rather dirty&#8212;and Mat concluded that she would leave&#8212;so she got a place in a boarding house in Pine street&#8212;I <choice><sic>had'nt</sic><corr>hadn't</corr></choice> been there more than an hour before I saw we were awfully taken in&#8212;and told Mat to give the week's notice that we agreed to give before leaving&#8212;our week was up last Tuesday so we told the woman to give us our bill  she wanted pay for a month first then concluded she would take two weeks and last got down <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_ad.00499.jpg" type="recto"/>to within <choice><abbr>abt</abbr><expan>about</expan></choice> $6 of right&#8212;but even this Mat <choice><sic>would'nt</sic><corr>wouldn't</corr></choice> consent to pay&#8212;so we had some high old talk and concluded to leave the <choice><sic>shantie</sic><corr>shanty</corr></choice> at once  This was <choice><abbr>abt</abbr><expan>about</expan></choice> 8<hi rend="italic"><choice><abbr>oclk</abbr><expan>o'clock</expan></choice></hi> on Monday evening&#8212;we moved next door and have (seemingly) a very excellent place&#8212;Yankee people, and clean&#8212;we are looking for a house and hope to find one to suit us soon</p>
         <p>Matters are going <choice><abbr>abt</abbr><expan>about</expan></choice> as usual with me&#8212;Lately I have been taken up in time a good deal by the attacks of a lot of Dutch <choice><sic>Enginers</sic><corr>Engineers</corr></choice><ptr target="loc.00453_n3"/> here who have assailed our works&#8212;say they are failing &amp;c particularly in regard to the foundations of the settling Res and by the way there is a report published by the Light <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_ad.00500.jpg" type="recto"/>House Board called "Memoirs on Foundations in Compressible Soils by Rich. Delafild"<ptr target="loc.00453_n4"/> that would be of great use to me in this connection  Can you get O'Conner<ptr target="loc.00453_n5"/> to send me a couple of copies (one for Davis)<ptr target="loc.00453_n6"/>  I enclose a letter<ptr target="loc.00453_n7"/> to him to ask him to send them to me with any other reports that he may have&#8212;out here these reports, particularly those made by U.S. Engineers are just of the greatest use and I do wish Walt when you ever have an opportunity to send or get any of such things you would do so. Send two when you can as Davis is as anxious to collect them as I am  <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_ad.00501.jpg" type="recto"/>They are really of a great deal more worth to us than the expensive publications, for they tell of what has really been done and how it was done  <choice><sic>Dont</sic><corr>Don't</corr></choice> fail Walt to give this note to O'Conner and if he can get him to send 'em</p>
            <p>Mattie is about the same  To-day has been a miserable day for her and she is not as well as usual on account of it. The children are first rate with the exception of a little cold. they go to school and are learning quite well not very fast but steadily</p>
         <p>We <choice><sic>hav'nt</sic><corr>haven't</corr></choice> commenced active <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_ad.00502.jpg" type="verso"/>work yet on our works&#8212;but I hope to be able to in a few weeks&#8212;we shall be pretty busy this summer&#8212;twill mostly be out-door work tho and not so tasking as last seasons work. I wish you might get an opportunity to come out and see us and see what we have done and are doing, cant you?</p>
         <p>How do you get along under the new administration<ptr target="loc.00453_n8"/>  Will you remain fixed in your old place as usual  I suppose there is to be or has been considerable change as to employers. I hope that you will be able to hold on to the bit you have 'till better comes  <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_ad.00503.jpg" type="recto"/>I suppose Gra[n]t has found out before this that the country <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> astonish worth a cuss and that he had better settle down and be like other Presidents.<ptr target="loc.00453_n9"/>
            </p>
         <p>I often wonder how you are getting along and think I will write you oftener, but to tell the truth something is coming up all the time that keeps me busy&#8212;I was nearly a whole week in writing a report<ptr target="loc.00453_n10"/> to the City Council in answer to a Resolution passed at the instance of them same <choice><orig>d&#8212;md</orig><reg>damned</reg></choice> Dutch engineers&#8212;but I think I gave them a full 20" gun&#8212;anyway I <choice><sic>hav'nt</sic><corr>haven't</corr></choice> heard from them since&#8212;still I <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> know where they will come at me next</p>
         <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_ad.00504.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>When have you heard from Han&#8212;sometimes Mother speaks of having heard from Heyde&#8212;but she hardly ever says anything <choice><abbr>abt</abbr><expan>about</expan></choice> Hannah&#8212;I wish she was happier in her situation in life&#8212;tis a shame that her whole life should be made miserable by that puppy</p>
            <p>Cant you come [on] that Pacific R. R. excursion dodge,<ptr target="loc.00453_n11"/> and get out here to see us&#8212;try if you  have a chance</p>
            <p>Walt, <choice><sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr></choice> fail to look around for any report by U.S. Engineers on works and if you can get them send them on&#8212;I get great aid from them&#8212;Love to all friends and as ever affectionately yours</p>
            <closer rend="right">
               <signed>Jeff</signed>
            </closer>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
