<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.02862">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 3 June 1872</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.02862</idno></publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Garden City, New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1964">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">79&#8211;81</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct> -->
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 3 June 1872</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1872-06-03" xml:id="dat1">June 3, 1872</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS45443, Box 3, Reel 2</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms002007.mss45443.0111</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1842–1937, 
                        Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc> 
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-10" who="#smb">ran image script, updated notes</change>
            <change when="2023-07-28" who="#aja">updated image pointers</change>
            <change when="2023-05-05" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-25" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-24" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-10-04" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-02-18" who="#cn">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-23" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-30">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-05-25" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-04-18" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-04-10" who="#al">Checked using microfilm images</change>
            <change when="2011-08-05" who="#zk">annotated Greeley</change>
            <change when="2011-08-04" who="#zk">transcribed and encoded from Harned; annotated AG, Strong Bird, Burroughs and O'Connor</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_cb.00097.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">50 Marquis Rd.</name>
                    <name type="place">Camden Sqre.</name>
                    <name type="place">London—</name>
                    <date when="1872-06-03" rend="right">June 3<hi rend="underline">d</hi> 1872.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The newspapers have both come to hand &amp; been gladly welcomed. I shall realize you
                on the 26th sending living impulses into those young men, with results not to cease—their 
                kindled hearts sending back response through glowing eyes that will be warmer to you 
                than the June sunshine. Perhaps too, you will have pleasant talks with the eminent 
                astronomers there. Prof. Young<ptr target="loc.02862_n1"/> who is so skillful 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_cb.00100.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                a worker with that most subtle fetcher of tidings from the Stars, the Spectroscope—always, 
                it seems hitherto bringing word of the "vast similitude that interlocks all"<ptr target="loc.02862_n9"/>
                nay of the absolute identity of the stuff they are made of with the stuff we are made of."—The 
                news from Denmark,<ptr target="n0793"/> that too, is a great pleasure.</p>
            <p>I have been what seems to me a very long while since last writing, because it has been 
                a troubled time within &amp; what I wrote I tore up again, believing it was best wisest 
                so—You said in 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_cb.00099.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                your first letter that if you had leisure you could write one that "would do me good 
                &amp; you too"; write that letter dear Friend after you have been to Dartmouth,<ptr target="loc.02862_n2"/> 
                for I sorely need it. Perhaps the letters that I have sent you since that first, have 
                given you a feeling of constraint towards me because you cannot respond to them. I will 
                not write any more such letters; or, if I write them because my heart is so full it 
                cannot bear it, they shall not find their way to the Post. 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_cb.00098.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                But do not, because I give you more than friendship, think that it would not be a very 
                dear &amp; happy thing to me to have friendship only from you—I do not want you 
                to write what it is any effort to write—do not ask for deep thoughts, deep feelings—know 
                well those must choose their our own time &amp; mode—but for the simplest current 
                details—for any thing that helps my eyes to pierce the distance &amp; see you as 
                you live &amp; move today. I dearly like to hear about your Mother<ptr target="n0705"/>—want to 
                know if all 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_cb.00101.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                your sisters are married, &amp; if you have plenty of little nephews &amp; nieces—I 
                like to hear anything about Mr. O'Connor<ptr target="n2002"/> &amp; Mr. Burroughs,<ptr target="n0129"/> 
                towards both of whom I feel as toward friends. (Has Mr. O'Connor succeeded in getting 
                practically adopted his new method of making cast steel? Percy<ptr target="n2000"/> 
                being a worker in the field of Metallurgy make me specially glad to hear about this). Then, 
                I need not tell you how deep an interest I feel in American politics &amp; want to know if 
                you are satisfied with the result of the Cincinnati Convention<ptr target="loc.02862_n8"/>
                &amp; what of Mr. Greely?<ptr target="med.00972_n1"/> 
                &amp; what you augur as to his success—I am sure dear friend if 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_cb.00104.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                you realized the joy it is to me to receive a few words from you—about anything that 
                is passing in your thoughts &amp; around—how beaming bright &amp; happy the day a letter 
                comes &amp; many days after—how light hearted &amp; alert I set about my daily tasks, it 
                would not seem irksome to you to write. And if you say, "Read my books, &amp; be content—you 
                have me in them"—I say, it is because I read them so that I am not content. It is an 
                effort to me to turn to any other reading; as to highest literature what I felt three years 
                ago is more than 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_cb.00103.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                ever true now, with all their precious augmentations—I want nothing else—am 
                fully fed &amp; satisfied there. I sit alone many hours busy with my needle; this used to 
                be tedious; but it is not so now—for always close at hand lie the books that are so 
                dear so dear I brooding over the poems sunning myself in them, pondering the Vistas—all 
                the experience of my past life &amp; all its aspirations corroborating them—all my 
                future &amp; so far as in me lies the future of my children to be shaped modified vitalized 
                by &amp; through these—outwardly &amp; inwardly. How then can I be content to live 
                wholly isolated from you? I 
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_cb.00102.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                am sure it is not possible for any one,—man or woman, it does not matter which, to 
                receive these books, not merely with the intellect critically admiring their power &amp; 
                beauty: but with an understanding responsive heart, without feeling it drawn out of their 
                breasts so that they must leave all &amp; come to be with you sometimes—without a 
                resistless yearning for personal intercourse that will take no denial. When we come to America, 
                I shall not want you to talk to me; shall not be any way importunate. To settle down where 
                there are some that love you &amp; understand your poems, some 
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_cb.00046.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                where that you would be sure to come pretty often—to have you sit with me while I worked, you 
                silent, or reading to your self, I don't mind how: to let my children grow fond of you—to 
                take food with us; if my music pleased you, to let me play &amp; sing to you of an evening; do 
                your needlework for you—talk freely of all that occupied my thoughts concerning the 
                <choice><sic>childrens</sic><corr>children's</corr></choice> 
                welfare &amp;c—I could be very happy so. But silence with the living presence &amp;
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc_cb.00047.jpg" type="verso"/>
                silence with all the Ocean in between are two different things. Therefore, these years stretch 
                out your hand cordially trustfully that I may feel its warm grasp.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye my dearest friend.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist</signed> 
            </closer> 
        </body> 
    </text> 
</TEI>