<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"
?>
<?oxygen
SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03382">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">
                    Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 23 December 1890
                </title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03382</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>
                        Copyright 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                    <title>
                        Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 23 December 1890
                    </title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-12-23" xml:id="dat1">December 23, 1890</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8&#8211;9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Dowd, Bernard" ref="n5000">Bernard O'Dowd</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-06-20" who="#bjo">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03382.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1890-12-23" rend="right">
                        <handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                        Dec 23rd 1890
                    </date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">
                        <handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                        Supreme Court Library
                        <lb/>
                        Melbourne
                    </name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Master</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                Your letter of Nov. 3rd, enclosing two  "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/periodical/poems/per.00139.html">Sunset Breeze</ref>"
                &#38; "Shakespeare" from <hi rend="underline">Poet Lore</hi>, slip of relpy at ingersoll's lecture<ptr target="n0839"/>, "Old Poets", 
                two Philadelphia newspapers with reports of lecture &#38; two "Truthseekers," have all arrived safely and increased our debt of gratitude to 
                our bard and our friend (we have the hope that your influence will tend to make all bards and all friends. When every pick stroke 
                in the heart of a labour-metre &#38; every through-train an epic in the eyes of the workers, and when the old spirit of 
                <hi rend="underline">camaraderie</hi>, fitfully shown now &#38; then by the way men stick together &#38; starve for each other
                in the strikes etc, tints men's lives like the Javan volcano tinted our Australian afterglow during the last few years, that will be
                "the good time coming." in mathematical formula of man = friend = bard, then happiness = &#8734;.)
            </p>
            <p>
                That lecture of Ingersoll's must have been a rare one, as it comes to us, its mere shadow, is grand. Ingersoll has an illustration
                in his lecture on Humboldt which fits himself here. He refers to Chimborazo with Humboldt at its feet. Here was another intrepid explorer
                and lover of truth, clearing away prejudice from another America, and here in this lecture, sitting nobly and ennobled at the feet of literature's
                Chimborazo. If this should sound high-falutin kindly remember an Irish enthusiasm pens it, and an Irish earnestness warms it.
            </p>
            <p>
                Jim &#38; Fred &#38; "Tom Touchstone," and all of us at home, send you our love and a hearty Australian new year's greeting, and wish we could
                personally thank Ingersoll for his kindness to you (You seemed so much better this letter than last, that we kind o' feel inclined to give Ingersoll 
                a bit of the credit and the thanks heartfelt I can tell you.)
            </p>
            <p>
                I am busy studying philosophy for a<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03382.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> university exam, and the result is that I haven't 
                a decent thought to tell you. My word, the general run of it <hi rend="underline">does</hi>
                want your test of the "open air" consideration, and a pruning according, that same "open air" would blow most of it
                to oblivion, like a hot wind a heat of frea-chaff. The stuff gives you an intellectual dry-rot &#38; how you sift for days when you can say
                as out poet Jordan said</p> 
                <lg>
                    <l>"Twas merry mid the blackwoods, to spy the station roofs</l>
                    <l>&#38; wheel the wild scrub-cattle at the yard,</l>
                    <l>With running fire of stockwhips &#38; a fiery rim of hoofs&#8212;</l>
                    <l>O the hardest day was never then too hard!"</l>
                </lg>
            <p>
                We're going to have a grand day on Christmas, about 80 children are coming to our place &#38;
                we are going to do all kinds of wonderful comical &#38; enjoyable things to please them.
            </p>
            <p>
                I tried to get some of Ingersoll's lecture in the leading papers here, but they are a little too bigoted &#38;
                so no result as yet
            </p>
            <p>
                You <hi rend="underline">did</hi> interest us by referring to your Japanese correspondent. We have been studying that country, its
                literature &#38; national character, and are pleased greatly that your "Leaves" have a prospect of being able to wreathe the brows of the
                "Daughter of the Sun." By the way, how do you think "Leaves of Grass" will translate into languages? "We have discussed the question and vary much.
            </p>
            <p>
                Thanks again for your great kindness to us and our need of thanks for that greater kindness to man your publication of Leaves of Grass has been.
            </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Our master: our prophet: our Elder Brother</salute>
                <salute>au revoir! So long!</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Bernard O'Dowd</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>