<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03379">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 9 January 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2017</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03379</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                    <title>Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 9 January 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-01-09" xml:id="dat1">January 9, 1890</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8-9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="O'Dowd, Bernard" ref="n5000">Bernard O'Dowd</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2017-08-24" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03379.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Supreme Court Library</name>
                    <name type="place">Melbourne</name>
                    <date when="1890-01-09">1/9/90<ptr target="loc.03379_n1"/></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Master</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Your letter<ptr target="loc.03379_n2"/> has made more vivid still the thrills of gratitude your former one gave
                us, and if personal attachment is part of the true poet's need, you assuredly have
                reward. I thank you sincerely for you kindness in forwarding the papers and
                criticisms, they help so much to give us clearer ideas of you and to see our Walt
                from other points of view. How we would have liked to have been present at that
                birthday "party" when Ingersoll (here to all of us once, to some of us still. It
                would do his heart good, much praised as he is &#38; much reviled too at times to
                hear some of his Australian admirers "sticking up" for him, their paladin of
                sham-slayers.) eulogized you as the papers say. We are anxiously watching the papers
                to see the drift of his speech. While out in the cathedral-like gloom of an
                Australian "bush", the sameness of the green of the gum leaves only broken at times
                with the gold of the wattle bloom, the silence only varied by the eloquent warbling
                of our mocking bird (the lyre bird) or the faint, imbodied, tinkle of the shy
                bell-bird, or the screech, as of lost souls, of the white cockatoos, I have often,
                with or without my mates, thought some of Ingersoll's sculptured sentences worthy
                of being uttered in those sacred glades, and if so on other subjects, how much more
                so would we think so when treating of you who have made those great gum trees array
                themselves in such new meanings for us. Our amygdaline (Eucalyptus Amygdalina) once
                was your redwood's rival, now each, towering over its native forest wafts
                comrade-greetings to the other, joining in free-fashion "hands across the sea."
                Those who have felt the awful meaning of our "bush", &#38; our desert with
                its mirages and its rivers swallowed up in sand, and have been self-conscious of
                that "forming, intestinal agitation" in our town-life, have whirred with flywheels,
                and mingled with miners in drives &#38; on mulloch heaps, have been "droving" sheep
                to the Plains of Promise or the weird "Never Never" land, and have wandered from
                station</p>


            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03379.002.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>to station with "sundowner" or hawker, have given a hand to the wharf-laborer bumping
                and helped him or resisted him in his "strikes" for justice or his violence (we have
                a great strike on here now, the greatest that has ever taken place here: the whole
                community are involved. In spite of logic and political economy, my whole sympathies
                are with the workmen. It shows what fellowship can do, when it unites the
                "rouseabout" on the Tropic of Capricorn with the "sails" on an Invercargill trader,
                and stimulates the London "docker" to send his subscriptions &#38; his sympathy),
                have been among children at school, among business people and professional, and
                scholars, those who have experienced such, are those who are alone competent <hi
                    rend="underline">here</hi>, to pronounce against you, and I have never met one
                such, who has been able to do so: most such, who read at all, find in you their
                natural poet. Jim agrees with me in this, &#38; says furthermore that every action
                he does and every set of circumstances he finds himself in, call up some line of
                yours. Certainly, to me at least, you are a commentary on, and a unifier of the
                disjointed (to me previously) history of the world. I can best illustrate Ada's<ptr target="n5000"/>
                experience of you by saying that to her you appeared as a vast mist, which however
                gradually developed a nucleus, and that again a nucleolus, which last contained all
                worth containing in the world. Fred's<ptr target="n5000"/> opinion is best symbolised by the rush of the
                iron to the magnet without knowing why, exactly. You would like his way of liking
                you, I think. Eve<ptr target="n5000"/> is an uncompromising evemy of shams, and if I may use the
                expression a slave to Liberty, and as she finds the same in you (as indeed everyone
                finds everything he wants in you), you are her inspired Book. To all of us indeed
                you are our "guide, philosopher &#38; friend." I hope you won't think I am trying to
                flatter, I can't help telling you what we think of you, to anyone else it might be
                flattery, but it is no high-falutin, nothing but the honest downright truth when I
                say that you are the greatest who has ever lived, to us all. The tension of an
                ecstasy, such as a Mohammedan would feel, if privileged to write to &#38; to receive
                letters from his Prophet, is on me while I write and therefore I can't write as I
                would wish to&#8212;I can hardly think it is not a dream that I am writing to Walt
                Whitman. Take our love, we have little more to give you, we can only try to spread
                to others the same great book you have given to us.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03379.003.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <p>We have great difficulty in following the movements of "Your Touchstone,"<ptr target="n5000"/> but I think
                you will see him before he will get your greetings to him here. He was busy with
                John Burns<ptr target="n5000"/> and others in London, the last I heard of him. I am very sorry that Dr.
                Bucke's<ptr target="n0119"/> book has gone astray: we are prosecuting every enquiry we can in Australia,
                &#38; so I hope we shall get it all right.</p>

            <p>After a long "try," we have managed to get "Leaves of Grass" into our Public Library
                (a magnificent insitution "November Boughs" is already there): this will do it good
                I think for the reviewers &#38; critics (your midwives) will be able to get it, and
                the general reader too.</p>

            <p>We will do our best to try &#38; get an order or two for you and think we can do it.
                It seems a pity that you should be getting no benefit of the numerous copies sold
                here.</p>

            <p>I am trying to get an essay read before the Australian Church Library Society, I
                spoke for you there two or three years ago and managed to rouse a good deal of
                interest at the time in "Leaves of Grass." We are rather a quiet lot and haven't a
                great deal of influence, but as <hi rend="underline">it</hi> spreads, you shall
                spread too, I warrant you.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03379.004.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p>I have a whole lot of questions to ask you about your poems but deem it better not
                to, you must be grown up to and are all the better appreciated when that is the
                case.</p>

            <p>We had an important event at our place on the 13th ult.&#8212;our first little one.
                We are going to call him Eric Whitman. His mother<ptr target="n5000"/> and he are quite well and she looks
                so happy.</p>

            <p>We all send our love and sincerely hope that you are as comfortable as your sad
                misfortunes will allow you. It is so sad to think that your services to human beings
                and to nature should have brought such return from both as yours have. The joy with
                which we receive your letters is flecked with great pangs for your sufferings. And
                you hear it all like the hero you are. Again, with love</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>I remain, my dear, dear master,</salute>
                <salute>he whom you have called "comrade"</salute>
                <signed>Bernard O'Dowd</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03378.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03378.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
