<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.03159">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt> 
                <title level="m" type="main">Sidney H. Morse to Walt Whitman, 31 January
                    1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Sidney H. Morse</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="es">Jeannette Schollaert</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schöberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.03159</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Sidney H. Morse</author>
                    <title>Sidney H. Morse to Walt Whitman, 31 January 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-01-31" xml:id="dat1">January 31, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 13</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc> 
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Morse, Sidney H." ref="n0862">Sidney H. Morse</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc> 
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-07-08" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-05-27" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2016-03-16" who="#es">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-11-02" who="#es">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03159.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1888-01-31" rend="right">Jan 31, 1888</date>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Richmond.</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The month Ends today—I have been here five weeks. How time <hi rend="underline">fugits</hi>! I begin to feel restless to begin another seige of work. But
                mother is plotting ways to keep me here. I should like to stay with her. She has so
                much to say, &amp; remembers everything of our family life so clearly. And
                then, she is lonesome. My sister has gone home. My brother 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03159.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                is busy in the shop; &amp; the children in school. I hate to leave her with her uncertain step,
                &amp; to the necessity of sitting alone to brood over the past. She dont exactly
                see why I can not do my work here. I explain; she understands for the moment; &amp;
                then returns to <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#if" cert="medium">the</unclear> charge next
                day or two. Still, finally, she accepts the inevitable, and as the old hymn
                says—"Puts a cheerful courage on–."</p> 
            <p>I am modeling a small bust of her. I tell her she has eyebrows like yours; cheeks
                like <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#es">Shillales</unclear>; and a
                double wallop under chin like Dr. Holmes.<ptr target="n3024"/> Her eyes have sort of grown together at
                the sides, so <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03159.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                only a round black spot appears. I shall bring on my bust of her when I come. My
                sister has a great amount of executive ability, and though moral &amp; liberal in all religious matters, almost
                to the verge of non-believing, she has the bump of discipline &amp; order big enough
                to serve the German Empire. Mother &amp; the rest of us are inclined to be lax in all
                such matters. So you see what's the matter when she (sister) is here. But, <hi rend="underline">More's</hi> the matter now she's gone, and <hi rend="underline">I</hi> assume charge. My brother's wife died some years ago, leaving 3
                children. The boy, Henry, 16 years old, spends much of his time since I have been 
                here, "drawing Walter Whitman." I often look in upon you silently, &amp; see you and
                the room: The sitting room with Mrs. Davis,<ptr target="n6113"/> the cat &amp; dog; robin &amp;
                <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="high">bantams</unclear>. And out beyond, the "hens and things"—minus one thing! <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03159.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> And so, how is Aunt
                    <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">Mary</unclear>. Somehow with her <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">
                    croneing</unclear> and her stealthy, flat footed tread, I can't avoid seeing her among
                the immortals— "her back yard when I was a housekeeper and my cellar floor,
                was always clean enough to eat your dinner on." Yes yes; how well she'd
                    keep these golden
                stairs &amp; pavements of opal &amp; pearl in Paradise! Tell her when she comes
                around that I enquire about her, &amp; wish her good health &amp; happy days for
                many years yet—</p>
               <p>And Mrs. Mapes<ptr target="n4149"/>, &amp;
                little Johnie, is it? I presume they, (&amp; Johnie's sister) still drop in &amp;
                sometimes "take a bite." And the other lady &amp; her children—is it <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">Mrs</unclear> 
                <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">Cady</unclear> ?
                No; I never quite got her name.</p>
            <p>And of course Mrs D. keeps everything in <hi rend="underline">apple pie</hi> order.
                Ah! the blessed old—<ptr target="loc.03159_n1"/>. Long may it
                wave!— Long may <hi rend="underline">you</hi> wave it!</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03159.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>I suppose friend Harned<ptr target="loc.03745_n1"/> puts in an appearance often. He is quite a remarkable man, I
                think. As the old puritan preacher Robinson (was it?) said of the "Bible, "I believe
                more light will break out of it when we are free." "or words to that effect. So when
                H. gets free of his many encumbering, political, judicial (I don't mean just
                that—can I say <hi rend="underline">law</hi>icial?), calls &amp; duties, as I
                think he may one day, and finds his way into the serener atmosphere &amp; more
                congenial line of thought. I expect more &amp; more of the real light within him will <hi rend="underline">
                    break out of him</hi>. He has a vast deal of good insights, and seems to select the good <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03159.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/> things you have done with more
                unerring vision than anyone I have met.</p>
            <p>The Smiths<ptr target="loc.03159_n2"/> are I venture good friends, but I have yet to discern that they know the
                "track of the old <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#if">varmount</unclear>."</p>
            <p>And Tom Donaldson<ptr target="n6011"/>—a surprising sort of a man—saying so many good
                things—with insights that don't seem to belong to him (physically viewed.)</p>
            <p>Well. I am about sending you the Hicks.<ptr target="n0301"/> I shall mail to you to-morrow the engravings
                &amp; also a little sketch in oil on a box <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#if">carr</unclear> that I made from an old photo of a steel engraving
                brought me by a Mr.<unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#smb">Hines</unclear> who
                heard Elias preach when he was 10 years old. He says my copy is quite as good as the
                original. I dont think so myself, tho' it aproximates. You understand I have made
                    <hi rend="underline">two</hi> busts of Hicks—large &amp; small. The large
                one is liked best—the one I send—<pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03159.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> I want it in time for the <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#es">Fidelity</unclear> boys to use in case
                you lecture for them. And then I would like it on exhibition at the Friends
                bookstore. Mr. <gap reason="illegible" quantity="2" unit="chars"/>ston's
                    brother has enquired and can arrange that part. In case
                anyone should like a copy. I should <gap reason="illegible" quantity="4" unit="chars"/> 
                to use this one for getting others cast—replace it with new one.</p>
            <p>Mr. Schultz, an old Hicksite likes the big one much. He was 16 when Elias came here
                in 28, &amp; remembers his <choice>
                    <orig>stoping</orig>  
                    <reg>stopping</reg>
                </choice> overnight at his father's. He says he thinks he may find some old letters
                Hicks wrote about that time. He knows that there were some &amp; he once read them.
                "Elias was a great man. A wonderful preacher—why, one Sunday before he
                finished his sermon tears were coursing down all our cheeks, young &amp; old. His
                doctrine was the simplest &amp; most effective—<hi rend="underline">all</hi>
                sided, far reaching: the doctrine of the inner voice, this will guide <hi rend="underline">every</hi> one who listens to it &amp; follows its teaching,
                into all truth &amp; goodness."</p>
            <p>As soon as I can I shall see all the old friends hereabouts, <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03159.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/> &amp; glean such memoranda as they
                may have for your consideration. The wonder to all is when I meet these saintly old
                fellows why they are Hicksites:
                one would suppose they would take a hint from him &amp; stand by their <hi rend="underline">own inner lights</hi>. Instead they try to tell me the way
                    <hi rend="underline">Elias</hi> expounded the Scriptures. Strange too he should
                    <hi rend="underline">expound scriptures</hi> when the Spirit &amp; he were
                closely intimate. But—</p>
            <p>Do you hear anything of the bust that went to England? Seems to me they are a long
                while getting it on exhibition.</p>
            <p>I hear good reports about the one in B from friends who have been in to see it. But no
                word as to its being offered to the library.<ptr target="n4150"/></p>
            <p>Regards to Mrs. D—And to <hi rend="underline">all "whomever they are"</hi></p>
            <p>Keep "so, so," "fair to middlin" anyway, &amp; as much better as may be.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Truly,</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Morse</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>