<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.07046">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 21 January 1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.07046</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>           
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1918">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">239&#8211;240</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 21 January 1885</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1885-01-21" xml:id="dat1">January 21, 1885</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-24" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-03-16">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Hampstead, London</name>
                    <date when="1885-01-21">Jan. 21, 85.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dearest Friend:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                I hope the <hi rend="italic">To-days</hi> have come safe to hand. I am thinking a great deal about the new edition; and cannot help hoping you are going to revert to the plan of the Centennial Edition, which issued your writings in two independent volumes. May I, without being presumptuous, dear Walt, tell you how I should dearly like to see them arranged? I want “Crossing Brooklyn Ferry,” “Song at Sunset,” “Song of the Open Road,” “Starting from Paumanok,” “Carol of Words,” “Carol of Occupations” and either as “As I Sat by Blue Ontario’s Shore” or the Preface to edit. 55 put into “Two Rivulets”&#8212;you could make room for them that the volumes might balance in size by making them exchange places with the “Centennial Songs” and the “Memoranda During the War”; not that these are not precious to me, but I want it dearest because I want in the Two Rivulet Volume what will best prepare the reader, lift him up to the true point of view, and make him all your own, before he comes to the inner sanctuary of “Calamus” &amp; “Walt Whitman” &amp; “Children of Adam.”
            </p>
            <p>
                Monday morn. Your letter just to hand. It gives me deep joy, dear Friend. I have sent copies of <hi rend="italic">To-Day</hi> to Dr. Bucke &amp; John Burroughs but did not know of his change of address; so fear it has miscarried. I will send another, and also one to W. O’Connor.&#8212;You did not tell me about your fall&#8212;unless indeed a letter has been lost. It fills me with concern because of the difficulty it increases in getting that free out-door life that is so dear &amp; essential to your soul &amp; body, and because, too, I still cherished in my heart a hope that I should yet see you again—here in my own home&#8212;&amp; now it seems next to an impossibility. Right thankful am I to hear about Mrs. Davis&#8212;that she takes good care of you&#8212;please give her a friendly greeting from me. I am going to have rather a bothersome summer&#8212;first of all, the house full of workmen to make all clean &amp; tidy; &amp; then my Scotch lassie, friend &amp; factotum rather than servant, must have a holiday &amp; go to her friends in Scotland for a month. I shall heartily welcome your friend, no need to say, &amp; be sure to like her. Love from Grace &amp; Herb. &amp; most of all from me. I have plenty more to say but won’t delay this.
            </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good-bye, dear Walt.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>