<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch" type="xml"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02129">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Hamlin Garland to Walt Whitman, 19 April 1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Hamlin Garland</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="es">Jeannette Schollaert</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02129</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Hamlin Garland</author>
                    <title>Hamlin Garland to Walt Whitman, 19 April 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-04-19" xml:id="dat1">April 19, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Garland, Hamlin" ref="loc.02128_n1">Hamlin Garland</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt" xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-08-14" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2016-07-31" who="#ss">second round of checks</change>
            <change when="2016-06-02" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-12-07" who="#es">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter"> 
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.02129.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Jamaica Plain.</name>
                    <date when="1888-04-19" rend="right">April 19/88</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Walt Whitman:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Dear Sir: It is probable that my friend Kennedy<ptr target="n3039"/> has told you
                something of me and the work I am trying to do for you and for American literature.
                I have not written to you for the reason that you are sufficiently plagued with
                letters but now I feel that I have reached the point where I can presume on your
                interest.</p>
            <p>Mr. Kennedy I know writes to you in a depressed mood many times, saying that he finds
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.02129.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.02129.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/> a "solid line of
                enemies" (I think those were his words) This is not true of my experience. I am
                often astonished at finding so many friends and sympathizers in your work and cause.
                In my teaching and lecturing I find no difficulty in getting Converts to the new
                doctrine and find your poems nearly irresistible in effect. True they do not always agree that they <hi
                    rend="underline">are</hi> "poems" though acknowledging their power and beauty. I
                do not care what they call them (I say to them) and receive their allegiance just
                the same.</p>
            <p>I hope to do much in the way of reading and lecturing to bring your work before <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.02129.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.02129.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> the people and
                it would give me pleasure to know you consider my work valuable.</p>
            <p>I am just now delivering a course of lectures in the city on "The Literature of
                Democracy" concerning which I enclose a couple of slips.</p>
            <p>In these I am trying to analyze certain tendencies of American Life somewhat in
                accordance with the principles you have taught. How successful I may be remains to
                be seen.&#8212;I have not seen Mr. Kennedy for some months, he is so busy these
                days, but I had a characteristic letter from him a few days ago. I have the greatest
                hope of seeing you some day and <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.02129.006_large.jpg"
                    type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.02129.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/> to talk with you
                upon these matters face to face. Let me assure you again that there is everywhere a
                growing respect and love for you and a growing appreciation of your poems. The
                papers no longer ridicule or even condemn unreservedly. An acquantaince among the
                younger literary editors of the city warrants me in saying that there is much more
                sympathy and appreciation among <hi rend="underline">them</hi> than our friend
                Kennedy realizes. There is great gain.</p>
            <p>It would give me great pleasure to hear from you if you are able to write.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>With greatest love and esteem.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Hamlin Garland.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.02129.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="right" resp="#ww">Send to Dr Bucke</note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
