<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03375">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 3 December 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ktl">Kirby Little</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03375</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                    <title>Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 3 December 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-12-03" xml:id="dat1">December 3, 1890</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Dowd, Bernard" ref="n5000">Bernard O'Dowd</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-12-01" who="#ktl">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03375.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03375.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03375.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Supreme Court Library</name>
                    <name type="place">Melbourne, Victoria</name>
                    <date when="1890-12-03">12/3/90</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt, my beloved master, my friend, my bard, my prophet and
                    apostle</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I must write something to you now. I have tried during four years, but was not
                satisfied with my effort. Let my earnest will compensate for the imperfect manner +
                matter. I am only a poor clerk in a law library, I know, + it would be presumption
                on my part to write to any stranger in this way, but you are not a stranger to me,
                you are my dearest companion: and, if you feel displeased, you have brought it on
                yourself for none who understandingly read you can help loving you. I am not going
                to praise your poetry to you (we don't usually tell the sun that he does well to
                shine + shines well, or the grass do we praise for being green) + in regard to your
                other writings will only say that your hint re sunbaths has saved me many a day's
                illness + your essay on Carlyle has told me once a wanderer in the desert <unclear
                    reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#ktl">cracked</unclear> by a material
                sun, that there is a night too glowing with star-life (in a word it caused me to
                study Hegel).</p>

            <p>Sometimes I take myself out of myself + gaze at what is going on in my mind. I often
                notice that I am defending you even when this <choice>
                    <sic>unbiassed</sic>
                    <corr>unbiased</corr>
                </choice> apart-Ego know or believe that you are a little wrong. We have great
                fights over you<pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03375.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                sometimes. My mates + I myself try to spread you everythwere + we find that every
                reverent student gets to love you while those who merely glance at you are sometimes
                nearly as virulent against you as those of your maligners who have never read you at
                all. I think we have profitted morally also from your indirections. You have driven
                away a good deal of pessimism from us + we can now work light-heartedly in our small
                spheres. I was a Roman Catholic once, + had been, thus, for generations under
                pessimistic influences that the revelations of science could not drive away</p>



            <p>My personal mates are Fred Woods, a draper, Jim Hartigan, a plasterer, an adorer of
                you, Ada <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#ktl">Fryer</unclear> a
                book-shop assistant (my sister-in-law) Ted Mackefer (a scapegrace, a swagman only,
                but a true mate of 11 years standing) + my wife. I am 24, red hair, plain features,
                a little too backward for my own good, fond of poetry, philosophy, science + going
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#ktl">long</unclear> walks,
                (Have got together a philosophy class of workmen + workwomen mainly + the avidity
                with which the revelations are seized is a pure pleasure to witness. My mates all
                send their love + I do so, enclosed by my own. We have a picture of you that
                appeared in a late Illustrated London News. It is over the mantelpiece + you seem
                quite at home with us. The other night several of us had the thought that you were
                listening as we were reading "Piers the Plowman" + that you were <choice>
                    <orig>sympathising</orig>
                    <reg>sympathizing</reg>
                </choice> with him in his despair, although pleased at hearing a poet of the
                "average man" of that day. It was the Walt<pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="loc.03375.005.jpg" type="recto"/> Whitman of our souls that listened of
                course but the picture was suggestive of the other thought.</p>
            <p>I wish you hadn't quite confined (in words) your "home, I will make the continent
                indissoluble" to America. Most of us make America mean the world, or sometimes we
                put "Australia" in its place. But I mustn't criticize, I mean most to tell you that
                I love you, that my mates love you + that ere so very long, the whole world shall
                love you +, what is more, all prove their love by actions such as you would approve.
                    <del>Poetically + philosophically you have solved the great
                    equation&#8212;Spiritualising = materialism. The little Camelot volume of your
                    poems, sells well in Melbourne, a bookseller tells me.</del></p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03375.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>I don't want to give you trouble, + so, as your correspondence must be extensive,
                will not expect an answer, honoured as I would feel by one. I sincerely hope that
                your physical life is happy now + that pain does not allay your spiritual glory.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>With a "handful out of my heart"</salute>
                <salute>Good bye, Walt,</salute>
                <salute>So Long!</salute>
                <signed>Bernard O'Dowd</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>P.S. "Tom Touchstone" (Mr Bury) a journalist in Ballarat, + like you in many
                    respects, first introduced you to me</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
