<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.07973">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Richard Maurice Bucke, 12 December 1891</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="adk">Andrew David King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zs">Zainab Saleh</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.07973</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>
                        Copyright &#169; 2021 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Richard Maurice Bucke, 12 December 1891</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1891-12-12" xml:id="dat1">December 12, 1891</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 7, Reel 4&#8211;5</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">
                        The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="pasteon" xml:id="ref1">
                    <author>Louise Imogen Guiney</author>
                    <title level="a">Wolcott Balestier</title>
                    <title level="j">Boston Transcript</title>
                    <date when="1891-12-10">December 10, 1891</date>
                    <biblScope type="pp">Unknown</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Bucke, Richard Maurice" ref="n0119">Richard Maurice Bucke</persName> 
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2021-08-02" who="#km">fixed spacing issue with pasteon</change>
            <change when="2021-07-18" who="#smb">made final corrections</change>
            <change when="2021-07-12" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-06-23" who="#adk">second check, corrected, added paste-on encoding</change>
            <change when="2020-04-13" who="#zs">processed, added images</change>
            <change when="2019-12-02" who="#cn">first check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-09-27" who="#adk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter"> 
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_zs.00608.jpg" type="recto"/> 
            <opener>
                <dateline><handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                    <name type="place">Camden<ptr target="loc.07973_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1891-12-12">Dec: 12 '91</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener> 
            <p>
                I saw an item of Balestier's<ptr target="loc.07893_n6"/> death four days ago, but tho't it needed authentication (&#38; seems to me yet), but I 
                find this printed in Bost.<ptr target="loc.07973_n2"/>&#8212;</p>
           
            <p><handShift rend="manuscript"/>He was the proposer of the foreign edn L of G.<ptr target="loc.04804_n3"/> I spoke of&#8212;</p>
            
            <p>Was any thing done&#8212;or 
                is there any thing further&#8212;of sending<ptr target="loc.07973_n3"/> the plaster bust<ptr target="loc.08177_n4"/> to 
                Dr Johnston?<ptr target="n4102"/></p>
            
            <p>&#8212;fine sunny Dec: weather&#8212;</p>
            
            <p>
                Bad condition with me&#8212;"Keep good heart&#8212;<hi rend="italic">the worst is to come</hi>"&#8212;was one of the sayings of my dear old father<ptr target="n0711"/>&#8212;</p>
                
           <p>Ingram<ptr target="n0323"/> has moved into Phila: for the winter&#8212;I have sent paper-b'd copies of the new L of G.<ptr target="loc.04811_n7"/> to Dr. J. &#38; J W W.<ptr target="n6121"/></p> 
           <p>Horace<ptr target="n4267"/> here last evn'g as usual&#8212;just taken a cool refreshing glass buttermilk&#8212;tolerable night last&#8212;sitting here 
                ab't as ever big chair, wolf-skin, oak fire. God bless you
            </p>
            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="enclosure" rend="pasteon" source="#ref1">
                
                            <head type="main"><handShift rend="printed"/>WOLCOTT BALESTIER.<ptr target="loc.07973_n9"/></head>
                
                            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The cable has done few things more tragic, in its own terse and terrible way, than to announce the sudden death, last Sunday, 
                                December 6th, at Dresden, of Wolcott Balestier. To those who knew him, the news will forever remain incredible, he was so full of active boyish interest in life and work,
                                of plans and criticism, of real promise and personal significance.
                                He would make on a stranger the impression of one who meant to last long, and yet he was not of robust build. He had a look not unlike the portraits of Hazlitt<ptr target="loc.07973_n8"/> in his youth;
                                slight, fair, decisive of step and speech; and his whole character was almost typically American, as befitted
                                the descendant of Wolcott the Signer.<ptr target="loc.07973_n13"/> He had written two novels. His "Common Story"<ptr target="loc.07973_n11"/> in a recent Century<ptr target="loc.07973_n10"/> won smiling praise everywhere for its shrewd and
                                tender comprehension of women; and he had the glorious fun (it would have been his own word), of building and launching
                                "The Naulahka,"<ptr target="loc.07973_n12"/> pegging away, day by day, with his dear friend Rudyard Kipling.<ptr target="loc.02472_n6"/> He had passed most of his life with books, and he found,
                                without trouble, his vocation as publisher. The new firm of Heinemann<ptr target="loc.07893_n8"/> &#38; Balestier started out with a vast stock of courage, and many English and American authors have reason to know that it made
                                an instant, an honorable success. Press of pleasant affairs, and the occult duty of dethroning the kings of the house of Tauchnitz, carried him this month as often before,
                                to Germany; and here, in his thirtieth year, is the inscrutable end.
                                Ships at sea, the noisy New York highways where first he studied the humanities, the all-but-uninterrupted stretch 
                                of grass from Dean's Yard, Westminster, to his door at Kensington, which made his daily walk, and which he
                                pointed out with great mischief to New Yorkers reared on din and dust&#8212;these shall know him no more.</p> 
                            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>He had many illustrious friends in his delightful exile; Mr.<ptr target="n0273b"/> and Mrs. Edmund Gosse,<ptr target="loc.07973_n4"/> with their lovely little children, will miss him most of all.
                                What his loss is to his mother<ptr target="loc.07973_n5"/> and his sisters,<ptr target="loc.07973_n6"/> one of whom, long in England at his side, was his devoted playmate, comforter and stay, cannot be put into words.
                                I shall think of him always as last I saw him&#8212;loving games and dogs and natural laughter; full of enthusiasm for literature and for old London; full of kindness for every
                                creature about him; the busy, happy, unsoiled young heart! "The peace of Heaven, The fellowship of all great souls, go with thee."</p>
                            <byline><handShift rend="printed"/>LOUISE IMOGEN GUINEY.<ptr target="loc.07973_n7"/></byline>
                
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_zs.00609.jpg" type="recto"/> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_zs.00610.jpg" type="verso"/> 
        </body> 
    </text>
</TEI>

 





