<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03821">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Logan Pearsall Smith to Walt Whitman, 30 November
                    1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Logan Pearsall Smith</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="rf">Ryan Furlong</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2017</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03821</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2017 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Logan Pearsall Smith</author>
                    <title>Logan Pearsall Smith to Walt Whitman, 30 November 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-11-30" xml:id="dat1">November 30, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 16, Reel 10</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Smith, Logan Pearsall" ref="n6122">Logan Pearsall
                        Smith</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-03-12" who="#smb">final check, added notes</change>
            <change when="2017-01-18" who="#cb">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-10-01" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-03-04" who="#rf">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_jc.00137_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift new="typescript"/>Balliol College<handShift
                            new="manuscript"/> Oxford</name>
                    <date when="1888-11-30">Nov. 30 1888</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift new="typescript"/>Dear Mr. Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift new="typescript"/>I wonder if I have anything to chronicle that will
                interest you? Yesterday was Thanksgiving so I went up to dine &amp; to stay all
                night with the family. We were all there, including the baby, who had been
                especially taught to say "Uncle" for the occasion. After the exile's turkey &amp;
                plum pudding&#8212;we had to do without the pumpkin pie of course&#8212;we gave a
                play that they had written. It was called "Wilhelmina's Lehrjahre"&#8212;an
                imitation of Wilhelm Meister<ptr target="n6147"/>&#8212;&amp; depicted the various experiences of a young
                American girl in London. She takes up <choice><sic>varieus</sic><corr>various</corr></choice> enthusiasms&amp; joins various
                brotherhoods in succession. Alys<ptr target="uva.00553_n3"/> was the heroine &amp;
                Frank Costelloe<ptr target="n6114"/> &amp; I appeared as the apostles of
                various creeds. In the first scene I explained to her the esoteric meanings of
                aesthetic symbolism, &amp; she makes up her mind to devote herself to the study of
                drapery &amp; colour. But that shortly palls,&amp; in the next scene she appears in
                the country; travelling around in Home Rule van &amp; delivering speeches on the
                Irish Question. Costelloe takes the chair &amp; introduces her with an eloquent
                address to the two old market women that compose the meeting. She then makes her
                address, but in the middle one half the meeting gives a snort &amp; goes out, &amp;
                at the end the other half asks some questions that she is quite unable to answer. So
                to she then, having met a young man who convinces her that the only way in which the
                stage can be reformed is by all educated people going on it, determines to become an
                actress. This turns out in the next scene to be no greater success &amp; at last she
                is converted to Socialism. This goes all very well for a while until the socialist
                league decides that all women must dress <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc_jc.00138_large.jpg" type="verso"/> alike in dresses made out of
                buckram. At this the American girl gives out, says that she is willing to dress
                cheaply, but not unbecomingly, rises in her wrath &amp; says that she is going back
                to America.</p>
 
            <p><handShift new="typescript"/>The play was really very funny, especially as it was a
                take off on some of our friends, whom Mariechen<ptr target="n6109"/> had invited to see it. We half
                expected, as the play went on that the socialists, politicians, &amp; aesthetics in
                the audience would get up &amp; go out, but everybody took it in good nature. Ernest
                Rhys<ptr target="loc.03310_n1"/> was there &amp; told us about seeing you last June.</p>

            <p><handShift new="typescript"/>Coming down in the train to Oxford I read Specimen Days
                &amp; Collect. I am so glad that the idea came to you of printing those notes, in
                all the books that I have been reading lately, Greek, Latin, or French, there has
                been nothing that has done me so much good. I hope there are more Specimen Days
                forthcoming, indeed, is not a promise of future instalments promised by the word
                Specimen? I think it means that what you have published are only the samples or
                specimens of what you are going to give us later. The student who lives just above
                me is reading Leaves of Grass for the first time, &amp; comes down in the evening
                sometimes &amp; reads is out to me. He is one of our best orators at the "Union"
                &amp; reads very well, you would enjoy hearing him.</p>

            <p><handShift new="typescript"/>I hope the autumn has not been hard on you,, here it is
                very wet &amp; dismal, but I manage to be out of doors a good deal every day, in the
                healthy Oxford way. You must pardon my type writer &amp; my gossiping letter, but I
                wanted you to know tha that I &amp; all of us often think of you &amp; talk about
                you.</p>

            <p><handShift new="manuscript"/>With much love</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift new="manuscript"/>Logan P. Smith</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
