<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.01108">  
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Blake Bigelow to Walt Whitman, 20 March 1892</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Blake Bigelow</author> 
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor> 
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2022</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01108</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2022 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Blake Bigelow</author>
                    <title>Blake Bigelow to Walt Whitman, 20 March 1892</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1892-03-20" xml:id="dat1">March 20, 1892</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 4, Reel 2&#8211;3</idno> 
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00063</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName> 
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="unk"><persName key="Unknown">Unknown</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key= "Bigelow, Blake" ref="loc.01108_n2">Blake Bigelow</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName> 
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-04-20" who="#aja">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2022-01-04" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes, DOI</change>
            <change when="2021-09-21" who="#aja">2nd check, notes</change>
            <change when="2021-07-19" who="#aja">checked, corected</change>
            <change when="2019-10-07" who="#cn">transcribed, encoded</change> 
        </revisionDesc> 
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01108.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>FRANK BIGELOW.<ptr target="loc.01108_n1"/></name>
                    <name type="place">BLAKE BIGELOW, M.D.</name>
                    <name type="place">Bigelow &#38; Bigelow,</name>
                    <name type="place">LAWYERS.</name>
                    <name type="place">Malone, N.Y.,</name><date when="1892-03-20"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>March 20th <handShift rend="printed"/>189<handShift rend="manuscript"/>2.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Friend:&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I dare to call you my friend because I have read your poetry. So many, many times I have wanted, during the past years,
                to  write to you, and was afraid to do so. Because there was no reason for my letter <hi rend="underline">unless</hi>
                I told you what was in my heart to tell, and people generally would call that flattery, or at the least, extravagance.
                But your recent sickness determined me to write at the hazzard of being misunderstood, but trusting that you will allow 
                me to throw aside all conventionality and speak the truth heart to heart. That is how I have felt while reading some
                of your poems&#8212;as though I knew your very heart's care. I believe you are the greatest poet of this age,&#8212;at
                any rate, you interpret your thought to me as such.</p>
            <p>How I would prize a word from you, but I am too small relatively to expect you to mind writing me, and yet your fame must 
                rest with such as I, who commit your 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01108.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                verses to memory, and praise them and you to others, and defend your genius before all disputants. I used to think I would
                be a poet and think if my life had been less crowded out of shape, I might have written something worthy reading. I will
                send you herewith a musical attempt of my own, written last year, when I was Surgeon for the Nicaragua Canal Construction Company.
                I graduated at two medical colleges&#8212;practised 9 years&#8212;am now <hi rend="underline">President</hi> of the "Franklin Co
                Medical Society," and last month was admitted to the bar, and at thirty years of age, I am just starting in my choice of
                professions and intend to realize intense ambitions, so that after you are dead, you will not be ashamed to have me champion
                you as your friend.</p>
            <p>My brother and I often recite your verses and love their beauty and patriotism. In your poems I have been thrilled with thoughts
                I had known but never had read before. 'No, not even in Shakespeare do I find many thoughts you alone express.' Is not part of the 
                charm of a great poet, in finding a thought that <hi rend="underline">we</hi> have thought, and would be afraid to tell to 
                ordinary mortals? The endless procession of the human race with occurences and re-occurences all along the centuries&#8212;the
                multiplication of human events&#8212;of individual deeds and lives and deaths&#8212;all these that 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01108.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                would require pages and hours to express with adequacy&#8212;you have pictured so well. I cannot describe to you how great the
                pleasure has been to me in the perusal of what you have written.</p>
            <p>You have written for us, <hi rend="underline">more</hi> of what was before unwritten, than any other of this age.</p>
            <p>I want you to know that I cannot help loving you for your work, and the work too.</p>
            <p>Do not think I have written this to gain an answer from you (although nothing in this world could please me so much) for I have
                not&#8212;my true thought was, that if you could spare time to read it, it might please you just a little (if you could think 
                our opinions of value enough for that) and if so you are permitted to throw <choice><sic>is</sic><corr>us</corr></choice> aside from your memory, without <choice><sic>forfieting</sic><corr>forfeiting</corr></choice>,
                in any respect, our esteem and love,&#8212;that is as I expect&#8212;My only regret that my name cannot, of itself, carry weight 
                to give you pleasure; all I can hope is that you will not call me presumptious and take umbrage if you deem this somewhat <hi rend="underline">bizarre</hi>.</p>
            <p>I have learned some philosophy from your poems, but still we poor 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01108.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                foolish humans cannot break the environments of nature and attain animal complacency and content&#8212;it will be a long time yet
                that we must "Fret and whine about our condition" and "Be awake in the dark and weep for our sins,"<ptr target="loc.01108_n3"/> but we are growing towards it. I read your 
                postal and saw your picture in the "Review of Reviews" for February.<ptr target="loc.04337_n2"/></p>
            <p>I trust that your life will lengthen many years and your pen give us more of what you have been thinking.</p>
            <p>Down in Nicaragua, a lot of us Americans read your poetry (from a book I had and some liked it enough to steal it) and they all
                praised you highly, and loved the poems. There is not the difference of opinion as to your merits now that I found fifteen years
                ago&#8212;I had often to fight for you then, but all willingly agree nowadays, and call you great and good. With the kindest 
                wishes for your long life and happiness and with love that necessitates no reward or return, but cares only for your peace
                and prosperity, I am, my dear friend, 
            </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Yours truly and sincerely,</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">Blake Bigelow</hi></signed> 
                <address>
                    <addrLine>To Walt Whitman,</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>New Jersey,</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01108.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01108.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>  
            <note type="editorial" place="left" resp="#unk">136.40 1007 42 1193 82</note>
        </body>
    </text>   
</TEI> 
