<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.03220">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>   
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Henry Latchford to Walt Whitman, 28 May 1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Henry Latchford</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor> 
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="adk">Andrew David King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>
                    National Historical Publications and Records Commission
                </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03220</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>
                        Copyright &#169; 2020 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with 
                        the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written 
                        consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to 
                        reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Henry Latchford</author>
                    <title>Henry Latchford to Walt Whitman, 28 May 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-05-28" xml:id="dat1">May 28, 1889</date> 
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 13, Reel 8</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms004014.mss18630.00261</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">
                        The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, 
                        Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Latchford, Henry" ref="n7053">Henry Latchford</persName> 
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName> 
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-05-26" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-05-21" who="#adk">second check, corrected transcription</change>
            <change when="2020-03-27" who="#bjo">checked, corrected transcription</change>
            <change when="2019-12-11" who="#cn">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03220.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1889-05-28">May 28, 1889.</date> 
                    <name type="place">Office of <hi rend="underline">Evening Journal,</hi></name>
                    <name type="place">Chicago.</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Comrade,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                Will you permit me to add by anticipation my warm congratulations to those of your many other friends, in this country and elsewhere,
                on the seventieth anniversary of your birthday.</p>
            <p>
                I am only a wayfarer in Chicago, and I am not sufficiently acquainted with newspaper men or other citizens to seek their cooperations
                in a "Round Robin" to you upon this occasion.
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03220.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03220.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                There are five morning newspapers here, ("<hi rend="underline">all conducted with signal enterprise and ability,</hi>") but I know very few
                of the men engaged upon them, and, as a stranger, I feel timid about taking the initiative in any testimonial, although I am convinced that
                a better-known person than myself would find no difficulty in procuring the names of your many friends and admirers. I only mention this
                lest you should think that you have not many friends here.</p>
            <p>
                Would you be horrified to know
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03220.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03220.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                that, among others, there is a genuine Waltwhitmaniac on the Chicago Board of Trade? From all accounts he is by no means a "Chump"
                at board-of-trading. He is known to the world&#8212;polite and impolite&#8212;as "Old Hutch," (short I believe for Hutchinson<ptr target="loc.03220_n4"/>),
                though I am inclined to think that competing traders would consider "Old Nick" a more appropriate term of endearment.
                When he makes "any kind of a decent deal" at all he just plays with millions&#8212;the other fellows
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03220.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc.03220.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                witnessing considerable of the "play" but somewhat less of the millions. He is a regular old pagan, so far as I can hear; an elaborate
                machine for transforming margins in fictitious wheat and pork into very real, genuine current coin. I was a little surprised the other day
                to hear that he had once said to his son: "Charley, you should read Walt Whitman. He seems to have something to say for himself!"</p>
                <p>This was told me by a city editor who had known "Hutch" for years, and he laughed till I thought he'd expire. "'There's visions
                about,' sure,"
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc.03220.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc.03220.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                he said," when old Beelzebub takes to dropping into Walt Whitman."</p> 
            <p>
                Now, my dear friend, you will doubtless hear many more agreeable things than the foregoing said about you next Friday, but I doubt
                if you will hear anything that patriotic Chicagoans would think more like oriental adulations than this nod of recognition from 
                a literary critic like "Old Hutch" who is usually so undemonstrative.</p>
            <p> 
                It is about six years since I had the pleasure of meeting you at your home in Camden, and I can scarcely express now my obligations
                for the sanity that your book and your example
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="loc.03220.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc.03220.011_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                have introduced into a life which had been much vexed by the combined though conflicting interests of Calvinism, metaphysics, ethics,
                whiskey, and other absurdities.</p>
            <p>
                I hope that before the 31<hi rend="underline">st</hi> you shall hear good tidings from our transatlatic partners, Dowden,<ptr target="n0199"/>
                Standish O'Grady,<ptr target="n0453"/> Tyrrell,<ptr target="n0655"/> and the 
                rest of the Trinity College men.</p> 
            <p>
                The enclosed scraps are taken from the Chicago paper which is known here as <hi rend="underline">The Evening Journal</hi>, but which Europe,
                Asia, and Africa only know as <hi rend="underline">The Old Reliable</hi>. A
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="loc.03220.012_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc.03220.013_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                reporter is fined heavily for any expansion of "the simple fact," which, in the eyes of the managing editor, should seem like a deviation
                from George Washington's standard of truth. The man who wilfully makes the last exaggeration is rusticated; i. e., he is sent to St. Louis.
                The moral character of residents in the state of Illinois is accuratley gauged by the number of years their subscriptions have been fully paid
                up for the <hi rend="underline">Evening Journal</hi>. So you see that in our almost sacred column you do not appear with sinners, sabbath-breakers,
                or any others
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc.03220.014_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc.03220.015_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                of the hideously ungodly class.</p>
            <p>My good friend and fellow-laborer on the Journal, James Chisholm<ptr target="n7054"/>&#8212;An American citizen born and reared in <hi rend="underline">Awberdeen</hi>&#8212;joins
                me in sending you greeting and high esteem.</p>
            <p>What can you wish for that you do not possess? You do not want for such palliatives of old age as "Honor, love, obedience, troops of friends." 
                But your comrades here, known and unknown to you, do hope that mother Nature may continue to deal very tenderly with you, and may fondly nourish
                and protect
                <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc.03220.016_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc.03220.017_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                your great and special treasure&#8212;"The boy's heart within the man's."</p>  
            <p>You remember, perhaps, having read some verses of Arthur Hugh Clough<ptr target="n7055"/> called "Songs In Absence."<ptr target="loc.03220_n2"/> May I quote a few lines!&#8212;</p>
            <floatingText type="poem"> 
                <body>
                    <lg type="linegroup"> 
                        <l>"Beyond the clouds, beyond the waves that roar</l>
                        <l>There may indeed, or may not, be a shore</l>
                        <l>Where fields as green, and hands and hearts as true</l>
                        <l>The old forgotten semblance may renew,</l>
                        <l>And often exiles driven o'er the salt sea foam,</l>
                        <l>Another Home."</l>
                    </lg>
                </body>
            </floatingText> 
            <p> 
                Whatever remains for us in "The great labor-house vast of being"<ptr target="loc.03220_n3"/> let it be a comfort to you,
                my dear comrade, that you have built unto yourself in the
                <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc.03220.018_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="loc.03220.019_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                hearts and lives of some of us a home more beautiful and permanent than any made with hands.</p>
            <p>
                Let me then wish you a merry birthday anniversary, and as many of them as may be good for you.
                Hoping you will not forget absent friends, I remain, with all the ardor of a regular&#8212;or irregular&#8212;dyed-in-the-wool,
                born Irishman,
            </p>   
            <closer>
                <salute>Your attached friend,</salute>
                <signed><hi rend="underline">Henry Latchford.</hi></signed> 
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Au Revoir!</hi>
                </p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf011v" facs="loc.03220.020_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 














