<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.04939">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>  
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Unidentified Correspondent to Walt Whitman, 20 September 1890</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Unknown Correspondent</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2021</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2021 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the 
                        Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. 
                        Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent 
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the 
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners 
                        of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.04939</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Unidentified Correspondent</author>
                    <title>Unidentified Correspondent to Walt Whitman, 20 September 1890</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1890-09-20" xml:id="dat1">September 20, 1890</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, 
                        Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Unidentified Correspondent">Unidentified Correspondent</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2021-07-27" who="#smb">completed director's corrections</change>
            <change when="2020-01-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2020-01-16" who="#blh">Second check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-06-14" who="#if">First check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2018-06-12" who="#bjo">Transcribed and Encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.01705.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <lg type="poem">
                <l>O death I cover you over with roses and early<lb/>
                    lilies<ptr target="loc.04939_n2"/></l>
                <l>But mostly and now the lilac that blooms the<lb/>
                    first</l>
                <l>Copius I break, I break the sprigs from the<lb/>
                    bushes.</l>
                <l>With loaded arms I come, pouring for you</l>
                <l>For you and the coffins all of you O death.</l>
                <l>Sea-winds blown from East and West</l>
                <l>Blown from the Eastern Sea and blown<lb/>
                    from, the Western Sea, till there on the<lb/>
                    prairies meeting.</l>
                <l>These and with these I'll perfume the grave<lb/>
                    of him I love</l>
                <l>O what shall I hang on the chamber walls?</l>
                    <l>And what shall the pictures be I hang<lb/>
                        on the walls,</l>
                    <l>To adorn the burial house of him I love,</l>
                <l>O light and free and tender!</l>
                <l>O wild and loose to my soul—O wonderous<lb/>
                    singer. You only I hear, yet this star<lb/>
                    holds me, (but will soon depart)</l>
                <l>Yet the lilac with mastering odor holds me.</l>
                <l>Sing on dearest brother</l>
                <l>warble your reedy song.</l>
                <l>Loud human song, with voice of utter–most<lb/>
                    woe,</l>
                <l>Limitless out of the dusk out of the
                    <choice>
                        <sic>ceders</sic>
                        <corr>cedars</corr>
                    </choice><lb/>
                    and pines.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.01706.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>This moment yearning and thoughtful I turn back and think of that old man whom I met but once only for a few
                minutes, His books read and absorbed in part, his life, a part of it read of asking about of men lingers
                about the ferry houses, looking for a glimpse of his face at the little former house yet never seeing him, wondering eager
                over the names since first I saw or heard it, now learning to love the man the book and the author. I have two photographs,
                one in book, the other lately taken, within ten years. I look at the engraving in Leaves of Grass, at the gray in the beard
                at the features all absorbing and always wondering "if only he could know" everything is all light, transparent as light,
                yet all dark and moody and tearful I would prize above all earthly things to see you and loaf awhile and ask you so much
                and so many things. I wonder now if you still are the same lover of God and man
                unconventionally as is portrayed in Leaves of Grass.</p>
            
            <p>I read not long ago in the Century a line "the vagaries of my life"<ptr target="loc.04939_n1"/> 
                This troubled me—is the book and its plan and purpose a vagary.
                All the teaching of the native inherent immortality of the soul, is this a
                a<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.01707.jpg" type="recto"/>
                vagary. The Hebrew Scriptures declare so, the New Testament writings declare so. "If you love me, keep 
                my commandments."<ptr target="loc.04939_n3"/> If you care for me read my book. 
                I am sorry that the People do not understand, but as yet, the people of the States have 
                not arisen, wait for the fusion of 
                nationalities and the type shall come forth. I hear much talk of the Lord's coming, 
                but all things center on this our globe.
                I cannot understand much of these things, only of my love and affection this I am sure of. 
                May I call my self a pupil—Dear old man you are beloved more
                than you can know this is the best I have and you have it. I see you there and my hearts 
                love goes out to you to night across
                seas and continents, now three score years and ten and soon to be yours, if only America 
                would listen and the young men and young women could see that ideal life:
                To time, this is your book's dedication</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>So–long with love</salute>   
                <address>
                    <addrLine><name type="place">Nagasaki, Japan</name></addrLine>
                </address>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1890-09-20">September 20, 90,</date>
                </dateline>               
                <address>
                      <addrLine>To Walt Whitman</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Camden, New Jersey</addrLine>
                      <addrLine>U.S.A.</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.01708.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>  
</TEI>