<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch" type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.03324">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 12 July
                    1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="es">Jeannette Schollaert</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>loc.03324</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 12 July 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-07-12" xml:id="dat1">July 12, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8–9</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt 
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. </orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
                    Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-07-23" who="#smb">final corrections</change>
            <change when="2016-03-09" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-10-24" who="#cb">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-06-08" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-10-26" who="#es">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter"> 
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03324.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Washington, D.C.<ptr target="loc.03324_n1"/></name>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Life Saving Service,</name>
                    <date when="1888-07-12" rend="right">July 12, 1888.</date> 
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I got your postal of yesterday this morning<ptr target="loc.03324_n3"/> and was greatly gratified to hear from
                you. I have wanted badly to write to you for three weeks past, but have really felt
                too sad and anxious to do so, besides being quite crushed with the dead heat we have
                been having, and sick with obstinate bowel trouble and my enfeebling lameness. I
                have felt that you and I were brothers in misfortune—I hope in all other and
                better ways too.</p> 
            <p>Words cannot tell how badly I feel at your confinement to bed and to the house for so
                long, and I enter into the irksomeness of it, combined as it is with
                strengthlessness and general illness. But I hope <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03324.002.jpg" type="verso"/> the spirit will still surge strong
                in you to resist and endure—it is about all there is for us in life after a
                certain age is reached. My belief in your getting better is invincible, for your
                stamina is indomitable. If you can only get through this hot weather! It is our
                common enemy, and the worst. Everyone appears to be affected by it badly; even the 
                well, and how much more the ailing!</p> 
            <p>I had two previous cards from you, one of June 17, and one of June 23.<ptr target="loc.03324_n4"/> The proofs
                were read with much pleasure, and despatched to Dr. Bucke,<ptr target="n0119"/> as
                you wished.<ptr target="loc.03324_n2"/> I was sorry you left in the one about the Red Emperor,<ptr target="loc.03324_n5"/> but find some
                consolation in the sweet assurance that he is finally damned, and <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.03324.003.jpg" type="recto"/> can trouble the
                earth no more! Many of the pieces are very beautiful, especially the one about the
                nirwana sunset. I think the title very fine.</p> 
            <p>When you sent the proofs, you wrote that you had been better all day—relieved
                from the prostration, and added that there had been a thunder-storm. See what
                atmosphere does for one! I think another storm is brewing today, and hope so, for I
                know it will give you relief.</p>
            <p>I heard from our all-good Bucke the last of June, and owe him a letter.</p>
            <p>I heard recently from Donnelly<ptr target="n4108"/> at London. His book is much
                abused by the English press, as by ours, but in private circles, among <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.03324.004.jpg" type="verso"/> lettered and
                cultivated people, it gains great headway. Dr. Bucke is not convinced (no wonder
                since a part of the secret was withheld.) But I have no doubt that Donnelly has the
                truth and will make his way after a little, especially as the mathematicians back
                him.</p>
            <p>I don't hear of Kennedy,<ptr target="n3039"/> but hope his book has prospects.</p>
            <p>Charles Eldridge<ptr target="n0210"/> appears to have won a big law-suit. I daily
                expect to hear from him, and to hear that he has got his fee—a large one.</p>
            <p>No news here. An even tenor. Nelly<ptr target="n4137"/> is pretty well, though under
                the weather, and sends her love and hopes. Cheer up, Walt, and take all the ease you
                can! I trust you can get out soon, if only for a drive.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Always with strong affection.</salute>
                <signed rend="right">WD O'Connor</signed>
                <address> 
                    <addrLine rend="left">Walt Whitman.</addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.03324.005.jpg" type="recto"/> 
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="left">See notes 1888 Aug 21</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.03324.006.jpg" type="verso"/> 
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>