<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="loc.04191"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 9 December
                    1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Addington Symonds</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="as">Ashlyn Stewart</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04191</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>John Addington Symonds</author>
                    <title>John Addington Symonds to Walt Whitman, 9 December 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-12-09" xml:id="dat1">December 9, 1889</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630 Box 17, Reel 10&#8211;11</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Symonds, John Addington" ref="n0615">John Addington
                        Symonds</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-03-20" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2018-10-01" who="#aa">second check</change>
            <change when="2018-09-27" who="#as">First check</change>
            <change when="2017-08-17" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.00339.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>AM HOF,</name>
                    <name type="place">DAVOS PLATZ,</name>
                    <name type="place">SWITZERLAND.</name>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="manuscript"/>To Walt Whitman</name>
                    <name type="place">Camden New Jersey</name>
                    <name type="place">U.S.A.</name>
                    <date when="1889-12-09">Dec: 9. 1889.<ptr target="loc.04191_n1"/></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear &#38; honoured Friend &#38; Master</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I thank you from my heart for the gift of your great book&#8212;that beautiful
                complete book of your poems &#38; your prose, which I call "Whitman's Bible."<ptr
                    target="loc.04191_n2"/></p>
            <p>But my heart has not the power to make my brain &#38; hands tell you how much I thank
                you.</p>
            <p>None of your eleves, your disciples, will be able to tell the world what they have
                gained from you, what they owe to you, what you are for them.</p>
            <p>I cannot even attempt to tell yourself (upon this page of paper with this pen in my
                hand), what it is that makes me ask you now to bless me.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.00340.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>If my health, <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#smb">riven</unclear> to the bottom like a tree in me, twelve years ago,&#8212;&#38;
                the cares of a family, complicated with this affair of health&#8212;had not
                prevented, I should long ago had come to see you in the flesh, to ask counsel of
                you, &#38; to assure you of my inviolable fidelity.</p>
            <p>We are both growing old, &#38; nearly half a hemisphere divides us. Yet nothing can
                divide souls, or separate that which is inseparable in the divine nature of the
                world.</p>
            <p>Perhaps we shall yet meet: &#38; then, beyond the death of this life, I shall ask you
                about things which have perplexed me here&#8212;to which I think you alone could
                have given me an acceptable answer. All such matters
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.00341.jpg" type="recto"/>
                will probably sink into their proper place
                in the infinite perspective; &#38; when we meet, a comrade's hand-touch &#38; a kiss
                will satisfy me, &#38; a look into your eyes.</p>
            <p>But, if we come to be judged, I shall go to the judgment-seat &#38; say: "Call out
                Walt Whitman. Let him pronounce upon the doings of this man this me; &#38; let me
                be confronted with him; before you judges pass your sentence."</p>
            <p>I cannot find words better fitted to express the penetrative force with which you
                have entered into me, my reliance on you, &#38; my hope that you will not disapprove
                of my conduct in the last resort.</p>  
            <p>As I cannot talk to you, I feel the need to say this; because you have exercised a
                controlling influence over me for half a century. 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.00342.jpg" type="verso"/>It is not often, I take it, that one man
                can say so much as I am saying to a man whom he has never seen.</p>
            <p>Those lines which I wrote in September of this year,<ptr target="loc.04191_n3"/>
                &#38; which I am glad to see now circulated, were calculated for the public mind!
                They do not tell the half; but, as an old Greek proverb puts it, "the half is better
                than the whole"&#8212;in print at any rate.</p>
            <p>When I read your Bible, I miss&#8212;&#38; I had missed for many years in new
                editions&#8212;the poem which first thrilled me like a trumpet-call to you. It was
                called: "Long I thought that knowledge alone would suffice me" [Calamus 8. ed:
                    1860&#8211;61].<ptr target="loc.04191_n4"/> Why have you so consistently omitted
                this in the canon of your works?</p>
            <p>Upon me, your disciple, it
              <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.00343.jpg" type="recto"/>
                made a decisive impact. "I put down the book, filled with the bitterest envy."<ptr
                    target="loc.04191_n5"/> And I rose up, to follow you. I miss the words
                now.&#8212;</p>
            <p>I am old now, &#38; you are older in years, though everlastingly young, in ways not
                given to all men to be so. So perhaps I ought not ask why you omitted that poem from
                "Calamus," &#38; what you meant by it. It means for me so infinitely much. I cannot
                say how much.</p>
            <p>Well: the disciple weighs his master's words, too scrupulously&#8212;&#38; thinks
                perhaps too much of his omissions or dark sayings. He must not ask for answers to
                his questions, but express the total of the teaching in his works &#38; ways.</p>
            <p>That I shall do ever, so far as I am your man&#8212;marked with your seal &#38;
                superscription, &#38; what my addiction to you will later bring <pb
                    xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.00344.jpg" type="verso"/>forth, is a matter for
                the literary historians of England to decide&#8212;if only I had life &#38; time for
                future working.</p>
            <p>More &#38; more of you will be found in me, the longer I live &#38; the firmer I
                become in manhood.</p>
            <closer> 
                <salute>Goodnight, dear man!</salute>
                <salute>Yours</salute>
                <signed>John Addington Symonds</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_vm.00337.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_vm.00338.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
