<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"
?>
<?oxygen
SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch" type="xml"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03381">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main"> Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 24 November 1890</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                <persName xml:id="bjo">Brandon James O'Neil</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
            <edition>
                <date>2018</date>
            </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <idno>loc.03381</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address>
                <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
                <p>Copyright 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <author>Bernard O'Dowd</author>
                <title>Bernard O'Dowd to Walt Whitman, 24 November 1890</title>
                <date cert="high" when="1890-11-24" xml:id="dat1">November 11, 1890</date>
                <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 14, Reel 8&#8211;9</idno>
                <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
            <person role="sender">
                <persName key="O'Dowd, Bernard" ref="n5000">Bernard O'Dowd</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="recipient">
                <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
            </person>
        </particDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="ww"><persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName></handNote>
        </handNotes>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2018-06-20" who="#bjo">transcribed, encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.03381.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="right">
                        <handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                        Supreme Court Library
                        <lb/>
                        Melbourne
                    </name>
                    <date when="1890-11-24" rend="right">
                        <handShift rend="manuscript"/>
                        24 / 11 / 90
                    </date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My Dear Master and (may I say?) Comrade</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                I received your letter of the 23rd with enclosing "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1891/poems/388.html">Osceola</ref>"
                "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/LG/1891/poems/386.html">A Twilight Song</ref>" and 
                "<ref target="https://whitmanarchive.org/published/periodical/poems/per.00139.html">To the Sunset Breeze</ref>," and also
                a copy of a September Philadelphia Press with a poem on you, all right, and feel that I cannot express my thanks (on behalf of us all)
                sufficiently to you for your noble kindness to us. I fear I detected a tone of weariness and affliction between the lines and can only
                say we are sorry from our hearts that your winter days should be so.
            </p>
            <p>
                I am sorry that your Touchstone (Mr. Bury) had to return from England before crossing to you. He was detained long over the
                strike &#38; business connected with it. I wrote to him &#38; told him of all your expressions of good will and greetings
                of love to him &#38; us all. I enclose his letter to me.
            </p>
            <p> There is much misery &#38; pinching among us in Australia over the strike. The men lost, as was inevitable, 
                <hi rend="underline">this time,</hi> but I do not think it is really a loss after all.
            </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.03381.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <p>
                Fred &#38; Jim and Ada &#38; Ted &#38; mr &#38; mrs Fryer &#38; my wife all send their love to you, bound
                with every good wish for you. We are anxiously waiting to hear the result of Ingersoll's goodness.
            </p>
            <p>
                (I believe they have a secret good word for you, for this reason. I used to bother them a lot with a series of 
                serrated word-groups that I called poetry, but since your influence came, they have been shared, &#38; I have no doubt,
                are thankful accordingly.)
            </p>
            <p>
                I thank you again for "To the Sunset Breeze." Somehow I feel your spirit at its best through that: it is a kind
                of commentary (among other things) on the unexplainable (to me) feeling of friendship with, at times, the hot wind on the central
                plains, at others, the gale from the ice-teeth of the Southern Pole. Your breeze isn't like them but you know the language of which
                they are a (perhaps harsh) dialect. I thank you too for the precious gift of a poem signed by yourself with your own name.
            </p>
            <p>
                I am finished now.
            </p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>With warmest Love, my dear, dear Master, I remain</salute>
                <signed rend="right">Bernard O'Dowd</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>
                P.S. Will you please send me for Jim Hartigan, Fred Woods &#38; myself three (3) "Complete Poems &#38; Prose" to same address as this (£ 5 enclosed)
                </p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
        <note type="editorial" place="left" resp="#ww">Books (four complete works) sent by Express Dec 27 '90. Rec'd safely by B O'D</note>
    </text>
</TEI>