<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.04693">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">James W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 9 January 1891</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>James W. Wallace</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.04693</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>James W. Wallace</author>
                    <title>James W. Wallace to Walt Whitman, 9 January 1891</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1891-01-09" xml:id="dat1">January 9, 1891</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 18, Reel 11</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Wallace, James W." ref="n6121">James W. Wallace</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-10-17" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_vm.01055.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Anderton near Chorley</name>
                    <name type="place">Lancashire, England</name>
                    <date when="1891-01-09">9 Jany 1891.<ptr target="loc.04693_n1"/></date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
                      
            <p>Sitting here tonight after my day's work is done, thinking of some of my friends &#38; of <hi rend="underline">you</hi>&#8212;an impulse comes upon me to write to you again</p>
            
            <p>Today is Fred Wild's<ptr target="n5000"/> birthday, &#38; tonight a number of his friends are met at his house to spend the evening in social mirth &#38; rejoicing. For different reasons (health the main <unclear reason="illegile" cert="medium" resp="#bbb">one</unclear>) I am not with</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_vm.01056.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>them&#8212;and will write to you instead.</p>
            
            <p>Fred has been away from home this week on business. So Johnston<ptr target="n4102"/> &#38; I sent to his house for the copy of L. of G. you sent him (&#38; which came after he had left) so that we might <hi rend="underline">give</hi> it to him as a joint present</p>
            
            <p>I wrote the following inscription in it:&#8212;</p>
            
            <p>To <hi rend="underline">Fred Wild</hi></p>
            <p>Something for a token from</p>
            <p>J. Johnston</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">J.W. Wallace</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">9th January 1891</hi></p>
            
            <p>With the love of comrades.</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">With the life long love of comrades!</hi></p>
            <p>See Bottom of Page 119.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_vm.01057.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <p>Fred is an old school chum of mine &#38; we have been intimate &#38; affectionate friends ever since. My mother used to say he was her other son. We are very widely different in many ways, but our friendship has lasted through all these years without <gap reason="cut away"/> break, <gap reason="cut away"/> I trust it will continue through old age" too.</p>
            
            <p>He has the English edition of L. of G. but wanted the pocket book edition &#38; asked Johnston to procure it. In its presentation to him by Johnston &#38; myself <gap reason="illegible"/> &#38; in the fact</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_vm.01058.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <p>that we are all three lovers of you&#8212;I feel that we not only express an old affection, but that we enter into fresh obligations to carry on your &#38; in particular to establish wherever possible the institution of the dear love of comrades.</p>
            
            <p>As I sit here in this quiet country place, away from the clank of the world <hi rend="underline">my</hi> soul, too, rejoices in comrades, &#38; in writing to you I invoke a larger measure of your own spirit.&#8212;</p>
            
            <p>I thank you, dear friend &#38; master, for the strong illumination.</p>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_vm.01059.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <p>Outside building operations have been stopped for 5 weeks or so. Alas! for the poor fellows who with their families, <hi rend="underline">at best</hi> live only from hand to mouth &#38; who are now starving.</p>
            
            <closer>
                <salute>With love to you</salute>
                <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
            <signed>J.W. Wallace</signed></closer>
            
            <postscript><p>P.S. (by J Johnston) Jan 10th 1891<ptr target="loc.04693_n2"/></p>
            <p>This morning I called at JWW's office to show him a very kind letter I had just received from your friend WM Rossetti<ptr target="n0522"/> when he showed me this letter &#38; suggested that I should add a few lines to it</p>
            <p>I spent a very pleasant</p></postscript>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_vm.01060.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <postscript><p>time at Fred Wild's last night the only drawback being the absence of Fred himself, he being detained at Coventry on business.</p>
            
            <p>This afternoon I spent a couple of hours with JWW at Anderton &#38; we had a truly delightful walk thru beautiful Rivington now all mantled in snow. It was a lovely afternoon &#38; as we tramped along the hardened snow tracks of the field path roadways we talked a good deal about you &#38; at intervals JWW read aloud passages from "L of G," our hearts filled with loving grateful thoughts of</p></postscript>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_vm.01061.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <postscript><p>which your personal loving kindnesses to Johnston &#38; myself have cast upon your words. Powerfully as your words had moved us before, they do so still more as we see you&#8212;in your old age &#38; weakness&#8212;so full of consideration &#38; tenderness, so regardless of your own personl comfort &#38; leisure, &#38; so unwearied in your constant acts of loving-kindness to us both. Love &#38; gratitude to you evermore! And to us more &#38; more of your spirit!</p></postscript>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_vm.01062.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <postscript><p>I hope that your health has continued to improve since the date of your last communications &#38; of Traubel's<ptr target="n4267"/> letter.&#8212;</p>
            
            <p>I sent a brief harried note to Traubel by the last mail, &#38; thought of supplementing it by a letter this mail. But I cannot now do so. Will you convey to him my affectionate regards &#38; best wishes?</p>
            
            <p>Last week, we had 3 or 4 days of thaw. But the frost set in again as keen as ever &#38; last night we had a heavy snowfall.</p></postscript>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
