<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.02876">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 14 May 1874</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zk">Zachary King</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ej">Eder Jaramillo</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.02876</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <!--<biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Thomas B. Harned</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ehm">The Letters of Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Garden City, New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Doubleday, Page &amp; Company</publisher>
                            <date when="1964">1918</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">109&#8211;111</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>-->
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anne Gilchrist</author>
                    <title>Anne Gilchrist to Walt Whitman, 14 May 1874</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1874-05-14" xml:id="dat1">May 14, 1874</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS45443, Reel 2</idno>
                    <idno type="DOI">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/ms002007.mss45443.0111</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 
                        1842&#8211;1937, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Gilchrist, Anne" ref="n0259">Anne Gilchrist</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-09" who="#smb">ran image script, updated notes</change>
            <change when="2023-07-28" who="#aja">updated image pointers</change>
            <change when="2023-05-31" who="#aja">final corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-04-05" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-03-20" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-10-27" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-03-07" who="#cn">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-02" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-24">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-05-31" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-05-11" who="#ej">Checked and Corrected.</change>
            <change when="2012-04-18" who="#al">Checked with microfilm images.</change>
            <change when="2011-08-07" who="#zk">transcribed and encoded from Harned; annotated AG and family, LVVW, WMR, MDC</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter"> 
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_cb.00197.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">50 Marquis Rd.</name>
                    <name type="place">Camden Sq.</name>
                    <date when="1874-05-14" rend="right">May 14. 1874</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dearest Friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Two papers have come to hand since I last wrote; one containing the memoranda made during 
                the war&#8212;precious records, eagerly read &amp; treasured &amp; reread by me.<ptr target="loc.02876_n9"/></p>
            <p>How the busy days slip by, one so like another, yet each with its own fresh &amp; pleasant 
                flavor &amp; scent, as like and as different as the leaves on a tree, or the plants in the 
                hedgerows.</p>
            <p>Days, they are busy with humble enough occupations, but lit up for me not only with the light 
                of hope, but with the half hidden joy of one who knows she has found what she sought and 
                laid such strong hold upon it that she fears nothing, questions nothing,&#8212;no life, or 
                death, nor, in the end, in her own imperfections flaws, shortcomings. For to be 
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_cb.00200.jpg" type="verso"/>
                so conscious of these, and to love and understand you so, are proofs the germs of all are 
                in her, &amp; perhaps in the warmth &amp; joyous sunshine of your presence would grow fast. 
                Any how, distance has not baffled her and time will not. A great deal of needlework to be 
                done at this time of year; for my girls have not time for any at present; it is not a good 
                contrast or the right thing after longish hours of study&#8212;much better household activity 
                of any sort. If they would but understand this in schools &amp; colleges for girls &amp; 
                young women! No healthier or more cheerful occupation as a relief from study, could be found 
                than household work&#8212;sweeping, scrubbing, washing, ironing, cooking&#8212;in the variety 
                of it, &amp; equable development of the muscles, I should think equal to the most elaborate 
                gymnastics. 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_cb.00201.jpg" type="recto"/>
                I know very well how I have felt, &amp; still feel the want of having been put to these 
                things when a girl. Then the importance afterwards of doing them easily &amp; well &amp; 
                without undue fatigue, to all who aim to give practical shape to their ardent belief in 
                equality &amp; fair play for all! In domestic life under one roof, at all events it is 
                already feasible to make the disposals without ignominious distinctions,&#8212;not all the 
                rough bodily work never ending, still begining; and the mental culture and abundant leisure 
                all to the other&#8212;but a wholesome interchange and sharing of these. Not least too among 
                the advantages of taking an active share in these 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_cb.00196.jpg" type="verso"/>
                duties is the zest, the keen relish it gives to the hours not too easily secured for reading 
                &amp; music. Besides, I often think that just as the Poem Nature is made up half of rude 
                rough realities &amp; homely materials &amp; processes, so it is necessary for women to construct 
                their Poem, Home, on a groundwork of homeliest details &amp; occupations providing for the 
                bodily wants &amp; comforts of their household, and that without putting their own hands to 
                this, her Poem will lack the vital fresh growing nature-like quality that alone endures, 
                and that of this soil will grow, with fitting 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_cb.00204.jpg" type="recto"/> 
                preparation &amp; culture a noble &amp; more vigorous intellectual life in women, fit to embody 
                itself in wider spheres afterwards&#8212;if the call comes.</p>
            <p>This month of May that comes to you so laden with great and sorrowful &amp; beautiful &amp; 
                tender memories, and that is your birth month too, I cannot say that I think of you more than 
                at any other time, for there is no month nor day that my thoughts do not habitually &amp; 
                spontaneously turn to you, refer all to you; yet I seem to come closer, because of the Poems 
                that tell me of what relates to that time; but most of all when I think of your beloved Mother,<ptr target="n0705"/> 
                because then I often yearn more than I 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_cb.00206.jpg" type="verso"/>
                know how to bear to comfort you with love and tender care and silent companionship. May is in 
                a sense (&amp; a very real one) my birth month too, for in it were your Poems first put into my 
                hand.&#8212;I wish so I were <hi rend="underline">quite sure</hi> that you no longer suffer in 
                your head, and that you can move about without effort<ptr target="duk.00623_n16"/> or 
                difficulty&#8212;perhaps before long 
                there will be a paper with some paragraph about your health, for though we say to ourselves no 
                news is good news, it is a very different thing to have the absolute affirmation of good news.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_cb.00207.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p>My children are all well and hearty I am thankful to say, &amp; working industriously. Grace<ptr target="n0261"/> 
                means to study the best system of Kinder garten teaching&#8212;I fancy she is well suited for 
                Kinder garten teaching &amp; that it is very excellent work&#8212;</p>
            <p>Herby<ptr target="n0262"/> is still drawing from the antique in the British Museum. I hope 
                he will get into the Academy this summer. He is going to spend his holidays with his brother<ptr target="n2000"/> 
                in South Wales&#8212;and we as usual at Colne,<ptr target="loc.02871_n5"/> but that will not be till August.</p>
            <p>Did I tell you William Rossetti and his bride<ptr target="loc.02876_n5"/> were spending their 
                honeymoon at Naples? &amp; have found it bitterly
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_cb.00203.jpg" type="verso"/> 
                cold there I hear&#8212;Mr. &amp; Mrs. Conway<ptr target="n0170"/> &amp; their children are well. 
                Eustace<ptr target="n3007"/> is coming to spend the afternoon with Herby tomorrow.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye my dearest Friend.</salute>
                <signed>Anne Gilchrist.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>  
</TEI>