<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01515"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 17 October 1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.01515</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2018 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Peter Doyle, 17 October 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-10-17" xml:id="dat1">October 17, 1888</date>
                    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 9, Reel 5-6</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839–1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Doyle, Peter" ref="n0752">Peter Doyle</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-09-18" who="#blh">Second check</change>
            <change when="2018-02-10" who="#aa">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2017-10-13" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01515.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Providence R.I.<ptr target="loc.01515_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1888-10-17">October 17, '1888</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Pete,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>According to announcement in my last,<ptr target="loc.01515_n2"/> I have made a
                movement &#38; change of base from tumultuous close=packed world-like N.Y. to the
                <hi rend="underline">handsome</hi>, half=rural, brisk, handsome New England,
                third class town. I came on here last Thursday. I came as guest of Thomas Davis,<ptr
                    target="n0187"/> formerly M.C. from this city&#8212;arrived between 8 and 9
                o'clock at night&#8212;found his carriage at the depot wait'g for me&#8212;at the
                house&#8212;a sort of castle built of stone, on fine grounds a mile &#38; a half
                from the town&#8212;a hearty welcome from his hospitable wife, &#38; a family of
                young ladies &#38; children&#8212;a hot supper, a tip-top room &#38;c. &#38;c. &#42;
                So you see Pete, your old man is in clover. I have since been round the city &#38;
                suburbs <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#aa" cert="high">considerably</unclear>. I
                am going down to Newport before I <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="loc.01515.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>return. &#42; Invitations &#38;c.
                are numerous. I am in fact already dividing myself between two hospitalities, part
                of the time with Mr &#38; Mrs. Davis,<ptr target="duk.00617_n15"/> and part with Dr.
                &#38; Mrs. Channing,<ptr target="loc.00945_n5"/> old acquaintances of mine in
                another part of the city. I stopt last night at the house of the latter. It is on a
                high &#38; pleasant hill at the side of the city, which it entirely overlooks. From
                the window of my room, I can look down across the city, the river, and over off miles 
                upon miles in the distance. The woods are a real spectacle, colored with all the
                rich colors of autumn. Yesterday it was beautiful &#38; balmy beyond description,
                like the finest Indian summer. I wandered around, partly walking partly in a
                carriage a good part of the day. To-day there is an entire change of
                scenery&#8212;As I sit writ'g this, what do you think Pete?&#8212;great
                flakes&#8212;of <hi rend="underline">snow</hi> are fall'g, <hi rend="underline"
                    >sometimes</hi>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01515.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>&#8212;the wind
                blows gusts&#8212;quite a thick flurry&#8212;in fact a real snow=storm has been go'g
                on all the forenoon though without the look &#38; or feeling of winter, as the grass
                &#38; foliage are autumnal, &#38; the cold is not severe yet. Still it disagreeable,
                &#38; wet &#38; dark, &#38; prevents me from going out. So I will make it up by
                writing a couple of letters&#8212;one to mother, &#38; one to you <unclear
                    reason="illegible" resp="#aa" cert="medium">tell'g</unclear> you about things.
                Providence is a handsome city of about 70000 inhabitants&#8212;has numerous
                manufactories in full operation&#8212;every thing looks lively. From the house up
                here, I can hear almost any time, night or day, the sound of factory bells &#38; the
                steam whistles of locomotives half a mile distant. Then the lights at night seen
                from here make a curious exhibition. At both the places I stop, we have plenty of
                ripe, fresh fruit and lots of flowers. Pete I could now send you a bouquet every
                morn'g, far better than I used to, for much choicer flowers.<pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="loc.01515.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/></p>
            <p>And how are you gett'g along, dearest comrade? I hope you are well, &#38; that every
                th'g is going on right with you. I have not heard from you for a good while it
                seems. I suppose you got my last letter, 14th from N.Y. I expect to return to N.Y.
                there about the 22d. Should you feel to write after receiving this, you might direct
                to 331 East 55th st. as before. I am well as usual. I am luxuriating on excellent
                grapes. I wish I could send you a basket. At both places I stop they have
                vineyeards, &#38; the grapes are very good &#38; plenty this year. Last night, when
                I went up at 11 o'clock to my room, I took up three great bunches, each as big as my
                fist, &#38; sat down and eat them before I turned in. I like to eat them this way,
                &#38; it agrees with me.</p>
            <p>It is quite a change here from my associations &#38; surroundings either in
                Washington or New York. Evenings, &#38; meal time I find myself thrown amidst a
                mild pleasant society, really intellectual composed largely of educated women, some
                young, some not so young, every thing refined &#38; polite, <hi rend="underline"
                    >not</hi> disposed to small talk, to convers'g in earnest, on profound subjects,
                but with a<pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01515.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                moderate rather slow tone, &#38; in a kind &#38; conciliatory
                manner&#8212;delighting in this sort of conversation &#38; spending their evenings
                in it till late. I take a hand in, for a change. I find it entertaining, as I say ,
                for novelty's sake for a week or two&#8212;but I know very well that would be enough
                for me. It is all first rate good &#38; smart, but too constrained &#38; bookish for
                a free old hawk like me.</p>
            <p>I send you my love dear Pete. <hi rend="underline">So</hi>
                <hi rend="underline">long</hi>. Will write from N.Y. soon as I return there.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>W W</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>P.S. just after 12 oclock&#8212;noon&#8212;as I am just finish'g,&#8212;the storm
                    lightens up&#8212;I am sure I see a bit of blue sky in the clouds&#8212;yes the
                    sun is certainly break'g out.</p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01515.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
