<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.01294">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
<title level="m" type="main">Henry Clapp, Jr. to Walt Whitman, 4 March
    1869</title>
<title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
<author>Clapp, Jr., Henry</author>
<editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
<editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
<respStmt>
    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
<persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    <persName xml:id="br">Beverley Rilett</persName>
<persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
<persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
<persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
</respStmt>
<sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
<sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
<funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
<edition>
    <date>2014</date>
</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
<idno>loc.01294</idno>
<distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
<address>
    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
    <p>Copyright © 2014 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
    <author>Henry Clapp, Jr.</author>
    <title>Henry Clapp, Jr. to Walt Whitman, 4 March 1869</title>
    <date cert="high" when="1869-03-04" xml:id="dat1">March 4, 1869</date>
    <idno type="callno">MSS18630, Box 8</idno>
    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
<person role="sender">
    <persName key="Clapp, Jr., Henry" ref="n6015">Henry Clapp, Jr.</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient">
    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
</person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-29">added correspondent ref</change>
<change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
<change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-06-18" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-05-08" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-02-15" who="#al">Checked</change>
            <change when="2011-02-03" who="#br">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc.01294.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rend="right">
                        <address><addrLine>18 City Hall
                            </addrLine></address>
                        <date when="1869-03-04">Octo. 3d '67</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Walt,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p> I have this moment clipped the enclosed paragraph about
                    Garibaldi<!-- <ptr target="n0255"/> --> from the
                    Paris correspondence of this morning's <hi rend="italic"><choice>
                            <abbr>N Y</abbr>
                            <expan>New York</expan>
                        </choice> Times</hi>. What a fine
                        photo.h
                    of a splendid man! I wonder why it made me think of <hi rend="underline">you</hi>! It <hi rend="underline">did</hi>, though, and so I send it to you
                    with the regards of</p>

                <closer>
                    <salute>Yours truly</salute>
                    <signed>H. Clapp Jr.<!-- <ptr target="n0161"/> --></signed>
                </closer>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc.01294.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
            <!-- loc.01294.002 is blank -->
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc.01294.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1 type="enclosure" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">

                <!-- enclosure is glued into the letter - not actually a postscript -->

                <p>The last I have heard of GARIBALDI'S movements was that he was at the villa of
                    his friend, the Marquis DE PALLAVICINI, in the neighborhood of Milan. This was
                    on the 16th, the day on which it was so confidently announced by his partisans
                    in Florence that he had crossed the Papal frontier. In the last number of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Figaro</hi>, I find the following "physiology" of this
                    remarkable man, by M. VILLEMOT, which, though bordering on the caricature, is so
                    correct in many points that I think it will interest as well as amuse your
                    readers:</p>

                <p>"'Liberator' or 'heroical bungler' GARIBALDI is a figure. Had I any disposition
                    to believe in the supernatural he would have converted me. Against all reason
                    and human wisdom, and to the profound humiliation of vulgar calculations, he has
                    accomplished things which are to be classed among miracles and legends. He is
                    not a great captain; as a tactician he is no better than JEANNE D'ARC, but like
                    her he has a familiar demon; he hears voices and takes the field. When he
                    captures a throne he seats himself upon it, eats a bunch of grapes and inquires
                    after his goats. He has not got a sou<!-- sic -->, and if he is a Chevalier of
                    St. Maurice and Lazare, he is profoundly ignorant of the fact.</p>

                <p>Educated people say: 'You now see that he is nothing but a rowdy; he may have a
                    palace, receive diplomatic corps, and eat carp <hi rend="italic">a la
                        chambord</hi>, but he loves best to live on a crust of bread rubbed with
                    garlic.' But GARIBALDI likes to be judged from the point of view of his
                    temperament, and on this side of the Alps he cannot be very well understood. He
                    is reproached with not dressing himself like M. ROUHER, and with wearing a
                    boatman's shirt, a slouched hat and a Scotch plaid. They accuse him, moreover,
                    of those turgidities of style which wound ears accustomed to the small flute of
                    the Academies. They forget that he is operating in the land of TASSO and
                    ARIOSTO, and if our genius induces us to the search after symplicity that of
                    Italy accommodates itself to a lyricism which with us is not in fashion except
                    in the minor drama.</p>

                <p>GARIBALDI is the expression of the land and the age that gave him birth. You
                    cannot get him to attire himself; you cannot get him to express himself
                    otherwise than is in <choice>
                        <sic>hts</sic>
                        <corr>his</corr>
                    </choice> nature. In his general physiognomy there is a mixture of the prophet
                    and the child. Of our civilization, of our manners, of our vices and our crosses
                    he knows nothing. He marches ahead without seeing. He lives in an ideal <choice>
                        <sic>worlp</sic>
                        <corr>world</corr>
                    </choice>, and knows no more of the men of his time than a contemporary hero of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Illiad</hi> rising from his dust.</p>

                <p>His innocence exceeds all belief. The following is an example of it. A few years
                    ago he said to a friend, 'You are aware that I gave notes to M. ALEXANDER DUMAS
                    to write my memoirs from. Would you believe that he has added to them a number
                    of things of his own invention?'</p>

                <p>BRAVE GARIBALDI! Write not your memoirs and get no one to write them. Let the
                    people whom you have <choice>
                        <orig>fantacised</orig>
                        <reg>fantasized</reg>
                    </choice> compose your legend, and you will take your place among the great
                    Sphinxes of history."</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc.01294.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc.01294.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc.01294.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>

    </text>

</TEI>