<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00974">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 30 September 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00974</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 30 September 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-10">10 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 30 September 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-09-30" xml:id="dat1">September 30, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-15" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-11-21" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-09-30"><handShift rend="printed"/>Sept. 30, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Broadway, now-a-days, presents its most attractive and
                splendent appearance of all the year. Take a walk with me, up that far-famed
                thoroughfare. Cross we over from the Battery gates, to the corner where stands the
                residence of Mr. Ex-Mayor Mickle;<ptr target="med.00974_n2"/> an ancient pile, (ancient for America,) built
                originally for the colonial gubernatorial palace, and occupied as such by Sir Henry
                Clinton,<ptr target="med.00974_n3"/> and by the British commanders during their occupation of New York, from the
                disastrous week following the battle of Long Island, down to</p> 
                <q>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <lg>
                                <l><handShift rend="printed"/>"Evacuation day</l>
                                <l><handShift rend="printed"/>When the British ran away,"</l>
                            </lg>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>as the old school-boy rhyme hath it. The architecture of
                those days was of a more permanent character than marks our hasty times. The brick
                walls of this old house, for instance, keep their truest perpendicular, and the
                ceilings their exact horizontal, without a need of repair; while many structures of
                far later date and more ambitious pretensions, have long since become quite
                dilapidated. Just off at our back is the stately row that faces the Bowling Green,
                and looks so superciliously up Broadway, as if announcing to the world in general
                that there was nothing "up there" that could hold a candle to the more time-honored
                dignity of houses standing on the oldest settled spots of Manhattan.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Bowling
                Green Fountain—what think you of it? Ah, judge not by its present dry and
                desolate look. When the water gushes out and rolls over the rocks in cascadish
                little rills, and the big spout lifts itself as high as the tallest trees, <hi rend="italic">then</hi> you
                might have a better opinion of this fountain. People's judgments yet remain divided
                about its merits; some approve the design, and others pretending to equal taste,
                condemn it as a vile blotch. One thing must be acknowledged by all; that what left
                arid and bare, the dull gray rocks, and dry bed of the surrounding excavation, make
                one of the most unsightly spectacles that a pair of eyes need look upon.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>As we pass
                up Broadway, we behold numerous happy bits of solid and tasty architecture. Some
                eight or ten doors from Battery place, that tall dwelling's entrance is guarded by
                the same big lines, bronzed over, that held watch on the spot ere the former house
                was burnt down in the great fire of '45. Here, a few doors further, where Mrs. David
                Hale<ptr target="med.00974_n4"/> formerly kept an excellent boarding house, stands Delmonico's, with its
                gorgeous furniture, fit for a palace. Then comes a long row of houses, (on the
                left,) venerable and not over fashionable, but still inhabited by remnants of old
                Knickerbocker families, and of rich proprietors and merchants. To the right hand,
                the ground has been encroached upon since the great fires, by commercial men. The
                U.S. Bonded Warehouse occupied the site of the old Waverly Hotel, and some beautiful
                stores have been put up still further down.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Now we begin to meet the tide of
                fashion. Our New York belles fit along so gracefully; you may know them by that
                lithe and easy walk, and unmistakable dash of style and elegance. You may always
                confidently count on seeing a greater proportion of feminine beauty, on the Venus of
                Medici model, during an hour's walk along Broadway, than any where else out of
                Paradise. Among the men, I notice more of the cosmopolitan influence than ever; a
                genuine New Yorker, indeed, may be known by his possessing <hi rend="italic">no</hi> characteristic trait.
                The peculiarities of all nations are softened and blended in him.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Trinity Church<ptr target="med.00989_n7"/>
                here lifts its head; a majestic and somber pile, whose proportions are so true and
                chaste that the beholder, at first, does not realize its magnitude—for that's
                one of the results of an exact proportion of parts, in architecture. The interior of
                this church is even nobler than the outside; there is a <hi rend="italic">sermon</hi> even in the arched
                inner roof; I have often spent half an hour in roaming my eyes over that roof, and
                along the great rear window, which pourtrays the Saviour and Apostles, of life-size.
                Come along here any Sunday morning, and you will hear the bells chiming merrily; it
                is a pity they don't get some competent player upon them, however. Merely trolling
                over an octave of tones, and repeating that continually, is but a poor substitute
                for the real music that might be drawn from the bells. There at the entrance, just
                to the left, is the brave <hi rend="italic">Lawrence's</hi><ptr target="med.00956_n5"/> burial place and monument, a marble sarcophagus
                above the surface, with several cannons half buried perpendicularly around, and
                supporting an iron chain. On one side of the monument is the following inscription:</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"The Hero whose remains are here deposited, with his dying breath expressed his
                devotion to his country. Neither the fury of battle—the anguish of a mortal
                wound—nor the horrors of approaching death, could subdue his gallant spirit.
                His dying words were—<hi rend="italic">Don't give up the ship!"</hi></p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Still wending our way onward,
                the current increased, becoming more dense, and its elements affords study enough
                just to walk Broadway, and behold the mixture of character and appearance spread
                over the sidewalks. The shops and their glittering wares—the foreign
                sights—"the fashions"—both masculine and feminine, are all together of
                inferior interest to the <hi rend="italic">humanity</hi> one sees in Broadway:</p>
                <q>
                    <handShift rend="printed"/>
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <lg> 
                <l>"Youth, with pale brow and slender frame,<ptr target="med.00974_n5"/></l>
                <l>And dreams of greatness in thine eye,</l>
                <l>Go'st thou to build an early name,</l>
                <l>Or, early in thy task, to die?</l></lg>
                <lg><l>"Keen son of trade, with eager brow,</l>
                <l>Who is now fluttering in thy snare?</l>
                <l>Thy golden fortunes, tower they now,</l>
                <l>Or melt the glittering shapes to air?</l></lg>
                <lg><l>"Who of this crowd to-night shall tread</l>
                <l>The dance, till daylight gleam again?</l>
                <l>Who sorrow o'er the untimely dead?</l>
                <l>Who writhe in throes of mortal pain?</l></lg>
                <lg><l>"Some famine-struck, shall think how long</l>
                <l>The cold dark hours, how slow the light;</l>
                <l>And some who flaunt amid the throng,</l>
                <l>Shall hide in shame to-night."</l>
                </lg>
                </body>
                </floatingText>
                </q>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Expressive verses
                those, a'int they? and in Bryant's<ptr target="n6116"/> own concise, smooth, sculptuary style.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>At our
                left hand and right, the windows are of thick plate glass, that seems like varnished
                air. Some of those panes cost hundreds of dollars; and, inside, behold the riches of
                all climes and arts and nations! Hats of a gloss darker than the still waters that
                lie in the shade of mountain chasms—patent-leather boots, ditto—garments
                with the royal signet of Broadway in every seam and fold—books, and such
                books, <hi rend="italic">O they</hi> indeed are to be envied, particularly if one looks in at Wiley's or
                Putnam's, or Appleton's—jewelry more beautiful than Shas and Sultans ever
                wore, because arranged with civilized taste—and five hundred other things, and
                et ceteras far, far too many to mention—these line the sides of Broadway,
                fenced in from the operation of "communist principles" by iron sticks and the
                aforesaid plate glass. Let us pause a moment on the flagging before St. Paul's. This
                crowd, which surrounds us, as you see, is composed mostly of foreigners and
                country-folk. They are curiously gazing at the pictures which placard the walls of
                the American Museum opposite—pictures of fish, flesh and fowl, and of some
                objects which surely were never before seen in earth, sea or air. The "Mammoth
                Boys," and the "Real Tong-Gong Minstrels," are, doubtless, especially
                attractive—though their "counterfeit presentments" there would hardly
                enrapture an artist.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Perhaps the noisiest part of Broadway is from the Astor House
                to Chambers street. There resounds an incessant clang, like the roar of an endless
                battle, with dust to match, sometimes—opposite, lies the Park, with its
                thrifty trees, and its lovely fountain, ever gushing. Amid the rumbling, you from
                moment to moment distinguish the dull click of the iron gates of the Park, falling
                to from the myriad of in and out-goers. The massive square walls of the Astor, which
                ages to come will probably look upon as we look now, are adorned here and there, by
                the glancing out of pleasant faces from the windows—women's and children's
                faces. Just beyond, glimpses of it appearing through the trees, shows the dirty
                white of the City Hall; Justice, up aloft, as far out of the way as it was possible
                to put her, and where not one human being out of a thousand could possibly reach
                her.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>So much for even a hasty transcript of a part of one's impressions in Broadway.
                We will reserve the rest for another epistle.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>   
    </text>
</TEI>