<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00978">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 9 October 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00978</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 9 October 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-19">19 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 9 October 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-10-09" xml:id="dat1">October 9, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-11-28" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-10-09"><handShift rend="printed"/>Oct. 9, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Something that troubled Presidents Washington and
                Adams fifty years ago&#8212;an article called "Red Republicanism" now-a-days&#8212;has been
                paraded at Tammany Hall lately. I mean, of course, the meeting last Saturday night,
                to compliment Mr. Hecker,<ptr target="med.00977_n2"/> and listen to a speech from him and other ultra radicals.
                All day long the great folds of the flag of "gold, red and black," had been
                flaunting from the staff at the top of old Tammany, joined with our own
                "Star-Spangled;" and at night, the immense room was an absolute jam of human beings.
                The Socialists, National Reformers, and Free Soilers,<ptr target="med.00954_n6"/> gathered in great force; Old
                Hunkerism,<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> and all sorts of Conservativism, looked on with a sour face, and
                retreated from the scene. It was a ga'a time for all the highest and most
                enthusiastic doctrines of "Liberty, Equality, Fraternity!" I, too, caught the
                enthusiasm, and though I understand German about as much as Choctaw, found myself
                cheering the Herr as loudly as the rest. Ah! there is something in the breast that
                bursts all control, in responding on such occasions to high and lofty dreams of
                political perfection&#8212;the wish to stab all sorts of tyranny that have for so many
                ages enchained the physical and mental powers of the "lower orders" of human kind!
                The popular feeling in New York would, even now, receive such men as Rollin and
                Blanc<ptr target="med.00978_n8"/> with joy. We do not so much wish their doctrines tried here in America, for we
                are doing well enough; and every successive ten years shows an opening still wider
                of radicalism&#8212;about as fast and as far as the people can stand it. But there is a
                deadly hatred toward the oppression and misery which the continent of Europe has
                received as its black legacy from the past. Devastation and blood seem horrible
                enough, but folks think they are not much worse than the wretchedness of stagnation,
                poverty, and death, for the millions of the old world.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Theatrical goers here and
                falling into the Macready<ptr target="loc.03259_n4"/> current with a looseness. It is singular&#8212;perhaps it might
                be called absurd&#8212;for Macready is little better than the "remains" of a good actor.
                The Literary World hits the truth of the thing in the following paragraph:</p> 
            
            
            <q><floatingText><body><p><handShift rend="printed"/>It seems
                to be a solemn engagement the American people have entered into with themselves, to
                fall into a frenzy or a <hi rend="italic">furor</hi>, at certain periodical intervals. Whatever object may
                happen to catch the current at its flood, is pretty sure to be borne on to fortune.
                At one time it is the domesticity of Miss Bremer,<ptr target="med.00978_n1"/> then it is the diabolism of Sue,<ptr target="med.00978_n2"/>
                the drollery of Dickens;<ptr target="med.00978_n3"/> one day it is all nature, the next day it is all art. On
                the very heel of a successful engagement of that "natural actor," Forrest,<ptr target="loc.03259_n7"/> we have
                the whirlwind raised to fill the sails of that great "artistic performer," Macready.
                Six months ago, Mr. Macready might have whistled for a hearing on the "merits"&#8212;six
                months hence his chances might be equally slender.</p></body></floatingText></q>
            
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Highway robberies are now
                variegating the somewhat dull business at the police offices. A. Joseph White<ptr target="n5001"/> was
                nabbed yesterday for attacking a German, at 1 o'clock in the morning, and robbing
                him of a gold watch and chain. The robbers of the &#36;8,500 from young Crommeline,<ptr target="n5001"/> at
                Paterson, have not yet been discovered.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>An innovation has been attempted here, after
                the Southern fashion, in the self-nomination of Mr. Edwin Williams,<ptr target="med.00978_n4"/> of much fame in
                "Registers" and statistics, for the office of Register of the county. It would be a
                good choice....Phonography (writing according to sound) has made many disciples
                here, and new classes are continually forming. Really the science is founded on true
                principles; but the worst of it is, few of its pupils carry its study to
                perfection....Rev. Dr. Hawks,<ptr target="med.00978_n5"/> of your city, is in town. He preached yesterday at St.
                Thomas's, formerly the scene of his regular labors....Mrs. Bishop<ptr target="med.00978_n6"/> continues warbling
                at the Park. Her voice is sweet and clear as ever&#8212;if not "more so"....You have
                heard, doubtless, that Fashion was beaten at the Union Course, L.I., last Friday by
                the Virginia Bostona. Lots of cash changed hands on the occasion; and many were the
                disconsolate faces....McNulty's<ptr target="med.00978_n7"/> trial has been postponed on account of the illness
                of one of the jurors. It won't amount to any thing decisive....We are to have some
                entertainment in the way of balloon ascensions, the current week, of a Dr. Morrill.<ptr target="med.00980_n4"/>
                (I hope they will prove more authentic than those which, for several successive
                Sundays gathered all the New Orleans boys, negroes, and curious ones, last spring
                around the corner of Poydras and St. Charles streets....Yellow Jack<ptr target="med.00953_n4"/> having departed
                from Quarantine, intercourse by ferry with Staten Island has been renewed....I saw,
                on Saturday last, a specimen of the California gold<ptr target="med.00984_n10"/> that is creating such a
                "sensation." It is the pure stuff, and no mistake.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>   
</TEI>
