<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00975">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 2 October 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor> 
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00975</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 2 October 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-12">12 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 2 October 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-10-02" xml:id="dat1">October 2, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-15" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-01-23" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener> 
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-10-02"><handShift rend="printed"/>Monday,</date>
                    <date when="1848-10-02"><handShift rend="printed"/>October 2.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent:</hi></salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Drizzle, darkness and a warm humidity form the
                character of the weather here to-day; yesterday ditto. A gummy dampness penetrates
                everywhere; and meat and vegetables "spoil" with wondrous quickness. The trees on
                the Battery and in the Park have cast a good share of their leaves, and the rest
                begin to turn yellow. In the streets mud and hogs reign triumphant&#8212;their
                domain only disputed, here and there, by the little crossing sweepers, with their
                petticoats draggled in front and tucked up behind. A bad day for walking, shopping,
                or going out of doors any way!</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Leonard, the seaman wounded by the Captain on board
                the ship Thomas H. Perkins,<ptr target="med.00973_n2"/> proves not to be dangerously hurt;<ptr target="med.00973_n9"/> on the contrary, he
                is recovering.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Coroner's jury in the case of Austin,<ptr target="med.00973_n4"/> Captain of the Empire Club,
                charged with the murder of Shea, in Leonard street, found a verdict on Saturday that
                Shea was shot by the said Austin. Notwithstanding this, the latter was admitted to
                bail&#8212;Elijah Purdy,<ptr target="med.00973_n5"/> Daniel Sweeney<ptr target="n5001"/> and Alderman Foote<ptr target="n5001"/> becoming sureties.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Cornelius S. Bogardus<ptr target="med.00973_n6"/> has been appointed by the President Naval Officer for the port
                of New York, in the place of the late Mr. Hoffman.<ptr target="med.00972_n7"/> Orders were received last week in
                the Customhouse here, from Washington, for turning out the barnburners who hold
                clerkships, inspectorships, and so forth. Mr. Lawrence<ptr target="n5001"/> returned, for answer, that he
                was responsible himself for the performance of his duties&#8212;wherefor he had
                given heavy security; that the officials sought to be expunged were men that he had
                tried&#8212;many of them old officers&#8212;and found to be competent and
                trustworthy; and that, if that Government was not satisfied with his conduct, and
                the discharge of his duties, it was at liberty to appoint another Collector in his
                place. Thus the matter stands at present.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The VanBurenites<ptr target="med.00973_n7"/> hold a mass meeting in
                the Park on Wednesday evening next, 4th inst. John Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n3"/> and Mr. Wilmot,<ptr target="med.00973_n8"/> of
                "Proviso" fame, are to speak. I shall endeavor to be there, and render you an
                account of the personal appearance and manners of these gents.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Tribune of this
                morning calls upon the members of the old "liberty party," or abolitionists proper,
                to vote for General Taylor<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/>&#8212;What are you laughing at?</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The sum of &#36;11,000, which
                sailed away from Rotterdam in the packet, accompanied by a Mr. F. H. Gernus,<ptr target="n5001"/> who
                "defalcated" it&#8212;and the sum of &#36;2000, in the same way from Bremen by Mr.
                Martin Valerius<ptr target="n5001"/>&#8212;were nabbed by the police officers here on Saturday
                last.&#8212;What with magnetic telegraph and steam communication, it is hard for
                rogues to escape. If they flee to the uttermost parts of the earth, their character
                is apt to be there before them&#8212;and a police officer besides.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Macready<ptr target="loc.03259_n4"/> appears
                at the Astor Place Theatre on Wednesday night. Many will no doubt go to see this old
                man, whose remains of genius even are no doubt respectable; but it is idle to claim
                for him, in his decay, the name of a great actor. Collins<ptr target="med.00971_n7"/> continues at the Broadway;
                Esmeralda at the Park; Hamblin<ptr target="med.00952_n6"/> is playing a round of tragedy characters at the
                Bowery; Chanfrau<ptr target="med.00971_n13"/> and Esmeralda at the National; light comic and musical pieces at
                the Olympic; ditto at the Chambers street....The grandest concert ever given in this
                city comes off at the Tabernacle to-night.....The Crescent City is to start at 4
                o'clock this afternoon.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
