<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00958">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 2 August 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00958</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 2 August 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-14">14 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[3]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 2 August 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-08-02" xml:id="dat1">August 2, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-13" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-06" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-28" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter">
        <body> 
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-08-02"><handShift rend="printed"/>August 2, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds.
                    Crescent</hi>—</salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Among the long resident literary and professional men
                here, no ordinary event of the last few months has caused more sympathy and talk
                than the death, last Monday, of Mr. Simpson,<ptr target="med.00958_n2"/> of the Park theatre. Going by the Park,
                early that same morning, I stopped a few minutes to look at the workmen, busy in
                their plans of demolition and reconstruction. The lower front of the theatre, with
                the steps and entrance, are all taken down; and the inner regions thoroughly
                disembowelled, without saving an item! It looks indeed like a day of revolution to
                see such work as this; for the Park theatre of the last thirty years had become so
                associated in the minds of New Yorkers with "the stability of our institutions," as
                to make an attack upon it something beyond even the most daring minds. There on
                those old boards we saw Mrs. Knight<ptr target="med.00958_n3"/> in her palmy days, before her voice had settled
                upon the <hi rend="italic">one-tone</hi>, than which she now sings nothing else. To Richings's<ptr target="med.00958_n4"/> Caliban, how
                sweetly she could then play and sing the gentle Ariel. And poor Fisher,<ptr target="med.00958_n5"/> with his
                Trinculo quips?, shall we ever forget him? And Mrs. Chapman,<ptr target="med.00958_n6"/> too, (otherwise Mrs.
                Richardson,) she too was in the spring of health and vigor then: all the dry goods
                clerks in the pit were in love with her. She was famous in sentimental young
                ladies—one or two of whom are in every old English comedy. Then Mrs. Wheatly;<ptr target="med.00958_n11"/> O,
                Lord! to see <hi rend="italic">her</hi> in Miss Lucretia <choice><sic>MacTub</sic><corr>MacTab</corr></choice>, and in the Old Nurse in Romeo and Juliet,
                and in Mrs. Duberly—ah, those were treats indeed! Her daughters, Emma and Julia,<ptr target="med.00958_n7"/>
                used to dance in a way that (bless our innocent souls!) we all thought, then, quite
                divine. And young Wheatley,<ptr target="med.00958_n8"/> we remember well—so straight that he bent over
                backwards. Mrs. Vernon,<ptr target="med.00958_n9"/> too—and Placide<ptr target="med.00958_n10"/>— than whom better players (they gave the
                intellectual as well as the physical to comedy,) never trod the boards.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>On the Park
                stage we first saw Fanny Kemble.<ptr target="med.00958_n12"/> Hers <hi rend="italic">was</hi> playing. 
                She "did" Marianne, in The Wife; 
                and many a man, who had visited the theatre for years, then saw playing for the
                first time. We well remember the impression caused on the audience, (as full and
                fashionable a one as New York could boast,) when the heroine of the piece came
                sailing up the stage on the startling announcement of "the Duchess," in the midst of
                her husband's camp, while his treacherous brother was pouring out a tale of
                falsehood and cruelty. Miss Kemble was about the first of the long train of English
                stars and staresses that have since poured in among us with uninterrupted
                succession. It is somewhat singular, that with hardly an exception, the principal
                personages (literary as well as dramatic) who have been thus lionized, returned
                Yankee fallibility with slander and flippant insolence.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>In still later times, the
                Park has introduced more modern matters. Specially worthy of mention is the way it
                brought out King John, three years ago, with Mrs. and Mr. Charles Kean.<ptr target="med.00958_n13"/> Beyond
                question this was the most perfect in its appointments and general getting up, of
                any piece that has yet been produced upon the American stage.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>But the Park has
                passed into new hands, and Mr. Simpson is dead! So the world "marvels" along. And
                perhaps it is better to. The old must give place to the new; those who have sat long
                at table must sooner or later yield to fresh-comers—if gracefully and cheerfully,
                the better for both parties. The advent among us of a whilom New Yorker, but more
                lately a resident of New Orleans, Mr. Jacob Barker,<ptr target="med.00958_n14"/> has given rise to several
                newspaper paragraphs, all of them good natured. Mr. Barker is a fine specimen of the
                enterprising New Englander—always ready, whether successful or "down" for a
                speculation and for business enterprize.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Hermann is not in yet, but it is not
                improbable she may be before sundown. The city wears a pleasant appearance—partly
                attributable to the delightful weather we have had for the last two days.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>   
    </text>  
</TEI>