<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00964">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 August 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00964</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 August 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-28">28 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 August 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-08-17" xml:id="dat1">August 17, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc> 
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">updated notes for publication</change>
            <change when="2023-02-14" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-06" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-11-07" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body> 
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-08-17"><handShift rend="printed"/>August 17, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent</hi>—</salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Rarely, at any former period, has the health of the
                city been worse, without an epidemic, than at present. Dysentery<ptr target="med.00964_n2"/> is the most
                prevalent disease, carrying off scores and scores every week. It is particularly
                destructive among children. In my circle of acquaintances, I know four families, who
                have lost from two to four children each by this destructive malady. It attacks
                grown persons, also, with severity—though its most unmanageable cases are those in
                persons under 16 years of age. Nor does a change of residence to the country afford
                any relief. Several families that have been for some time out in the country,
                principally on account of their children, have been obliged to return; in one large
                country boarding-house on Long Island, seven persons died last Sunday, and five on
                Monday.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The surrounding regions are suffering very much from drought. Corn and
                potatoes, in certain section, will be quite cut off—many fields are so already. A
                heavy shower here, a few days since, was confined to the immediate neighborhood of
                the city; and even here it does not seem to have modified the heat.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Our city streets
                present a plentiful sprinkling of well-dressed, bronze-faced personages, from the
                West Indies—families who have removed hither in consequence of the troubles among
                the slaves of those regions. A great many hundreds of these West Indians are in
                town. They must affect lounging in Broadway; and their easy, indolent air, sometimes
                exemplified in the person of a fine-looking brunette, may be seen on that famous
                pavement, at almost any hour of the day.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The editors of New York are vigorously
                plying their pens in politics—each with his peculiar preferences and dislikes. Our
                friend of the Tribune hath a somewhat vague, disconsolate method of procedure; the
                tendency of his editorials, however, is plainly in support of "the Buffaloes." The
                Courier and Enquirer is ardent and most industrious in its advocacy of Gen. Taylor,<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/>
                each number having one or more vigorous articles to the praise and admiration of the
                old hero. The Express has also, since the nomination, laid its Clayism<ptr target="med.00954_n8"/> on the shelf,
                and goes for Taylor, "without a why or wherefore." The Express likes, as a side
                amusement, to have one or two little personal quarrels with brother newspapers—and
                generally, indeed, is furnished with abundance of such recreation. The Evening Post
                contains incessant appeals and arguments in behalf of Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/> and "the
                non-extension of slavery;" with occasional dashes at Mr. Polk<ptr target="med.00968_n2"/> and Secretary Marcy.<ptr target="med.00964_n5"/>
                The Globe ditto—only more so. The Herald gives its editorial speculations and its
                "news to the latest moment," as usual. The Sun "goes in" for Cuba; and furnishes its
                habitual melange of news and advertisements. The Morning Star seems to be pursuing
                an imitative tack after the Sun. The Commercial Advertiser is certainly conducted
                with more ability than ever before;—it supports Taylor, with an occasional squinting
                towards Buffaloism. The Sunday papers are professedly neutral; but I believe the
                Atlas goes for Taylor, and the Times leans to Cass.<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/></p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We have another great meeting
                to-night, at Vauxhall, in behalf of Ireland's rights,<ptr target="loc.03571_n1d"/> and to collect money for her,
                now, in her time of sorest need. Funds are pouring in by thousands—and thousands
                more behind! O, that we may not be disappointed in our hopes!</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body> 
    </text>
</TEI>