<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00980">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 12 October 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00980</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 12 October 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-23">23 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 12 October 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-10-12" xml:id="dat1">October 12, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-05" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-10-12"><handShift rend="printed"/>October 12, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Half the people you meet this morning, have something
                to say about the Pennsylvania and Ohio election news. It seems every way probable,
                from the complexion of the returns so far, that the Whig<ptr target="med.00961_n4"/> tickets are successful in
                both those States. In Pennsylvania this was not expected. And to have two such big
                States declaring for the Whigs, adds highly to Gen. Taylor's<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/> chances&#8212;which his
                friends believe are "the best out." A large portion of voters are like the bubbles
                on a river; they run just which way the current runs.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We have the loveliest of
                weather, and have had for a week. The sun shines bright and clear in the day; and
                the harvest moon by night. The air is dry, bracing, and coolish&#8212;just the stuff for a
                respectable pair of lungs. Thirty or forty thousand visiters are in town, either
                buying goods for country stores for winter, or attending the Fair at Castle Garden,
                or something else. Never have I seen a more varied or spangled crowd than filled the
                sidewalks of Broadway, about noon yesterday! It was a close and uninterrupted
                phalanx of youth, beauty, manliness, moustaches, distant and domestic celebrities,
                dandies and spruce lads. Commend me to a stroll in Broadway, of an October noon!</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>I
                spent an hour at the Fair yesterday afternoon. One of the first attractions, at the
                entrance, is what appears to be a flannel-shirted "one of 23's b'ys," with hat on
                forehead, and a segar in an almost perpendicular position from his mouth. Upon a
                second look, you find it is wax-work&#8212;and capitally done it is. The grand saloon is
                crowded with the usual variety of wares&#8212;not forgetting the bed-quilts and
                pound-cake. Some sofas and a magnificent Gothic bookcase, attracted my attention;
                and a splendid display, too, of saws, and steel fixin's to enginery. Wending your
                way through the alleys, you have a first rate opportunity to see the pleasant
                country girls, with the fresh plump cheeks, and looks of modest wonder and pleasure.
                On these occasions it is that many families pay their only visits to the city. Gen.
                Scott<ptr target="med.00980_n7"/> was at the Fair yesterday. The band played a complimentary tune, and the folks
                stared at the old hero; but there was no hurrahing. Jerome,<ptr target="n5001"/> the sailor, is also to
                be seen in the area; he has a subscription paper to Berford's<ptr target="med.00980_n3"/> new periodical, (to be
                edited by Wm. Wallace,<ptr target="n5001"/> of Kentucky.)</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The balloon ascension, mentioned in my last,
                came off according to promise, at Niblo's, yesterday afternoon. 
                Mr. Morrill<ptr target="med.00980_n4"/> had a
                very pleasant time of it, according to appearances. He sailed over toward Long
                Island, but where he struck the earth, has not yet been announced. Macready<ptr target="loc.03259_n4"/> still
                "goes it s'rong" at the Astor Place; to-night he plays Hamlet&#8212;his best performance.
                Those pleasant singers, the Seguins, with their satellites, are at the Broadway,
                giving Balfe's beautiful plagiarism of "the Bohemian Girl." The German Musical
                Society, twenty-three performers, have been giving concerts at the Tabernacle. They
                are glorious players&#8212;in individual perfection fully equal to the Steyermarkers,<ptr target="med.00980_n6"/> and
                more of them. A youth named Ikelheimer,<ptr target="med.00980_n5"/> aged only 15, said to be a wondrous
                violinist, has come among us, from Germany&#8212;last from Paris. You have no idea how
                music "takes" here. Our Evening Free Schools&#8212;capital institutions, that ought to be
                established in every city in the United States&#8212;open on Monday evening next. Do
                persuade your functionaries to have something of the same sort in New Orleans.*
                Frost has made its appearance hereabout. Indeed a little glaze of ice appeared, some
                miles at the east, the other morning</p> 
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
