<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00960">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 7 August 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00960</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc> 
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 7 August 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-17">17 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 7 August 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-08-07" xml:id="dat1">August 7, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-06" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-31" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-08-07"><handShift rend="printed"/>August 7, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The anticipated rising in Ireland<ptr target="loc.03571_n1"/> continues to engross very much of the public interest
                here, even though the political witchery of the season is fast closing its spells
                around us. Ireland has such a large representation here in New York—many of
                the most distinguished professional men, as well as a large portion of the working
                classes, looking back to Erin as their native land—more beloved, because most
                oppressed. In almost every quarter the subject of the trials of the arrested
                Repealers is talked of, and the consequences it will lead to discussed. One thing is
                beyond doubt: if the fall of 1848 passes on to winter, (which latter rigid season is
                a fitting symbol of the icy clutch which the Russell<ptr target="med.00960_n3"/> government are tightening
                around Irish freedom) and the English officials go on imprisoning the glory and the
                pride of Ireland—for such are those young Repeal editors, as brave hearts as
                throb on old earth's surface!—and packing juries to convict them, and sending
                them off to the hulks, and the oppressed submit to it all, without actual resistance
                of <hi rend="italic">deed</hi>, then the sympathy of the world—at all events
                of our New World—is shorn of its proportions, and we can hardly think the
                Irish yet deserving of their freedom. We can hardly think of any worse or more
                cowardly enemies, then, than they are to themselves. As it is, the great heart of
                America and of France would be with them. Nor could it be, in case of a deadly
                struggle, that the <hi rend="italic">honest</hi> heart of Old England would willingly
                see the Government carrying fire and sword against men whose only crime is loving
                their country, and who have been pushed to desperation by untold
                persecutions—by starvation, stripes, scorn and outrages upon conscience!</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Buffalo Convention<ptr target="med.00954_n9"/>
                convenes next Wednesday—and a huge unwieldly meeting it will be. Delegations
                have been sent to it not by twos and tens, but by hundreds and thousands, without
                any regard to proportion or to relative sizes of places. That there will be very
                considerable excitement there, is a matter of course. Not unlikely, there will ensue
                a pretty bitter conflict of opinion between the committed friends of Mr. Van
                    Buren,<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/> and those who prefer somebody else. The
                probability is, however, that Van Buren will be the nominee for President, with
                Judge McLean<ptr target="med.00956_n2"/> for Vice president; if not the Judge,
                Senator Hale.<ptr target="nhs.00001_n1"/> Even the New York Tribune, you see,
                endorses Van Buren. These are wonderful days, when such things come to pass!</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Quite a conflict is going on between the omnibus
                proprietors and the drivers. The former have (they say in their own defence) passed
                some pretty stringent resolutions to dismiss all drivers who misbehave, or don't pay
                up every one of "them" sixpences. The worst of it is, that when one has been thus
                dismissed the other proprietors are bound not to take him into their employment.
                This don't suit the Messrs. Jehus, who number some four or five hundred of our "free
                and enlightened." So, on Sunday morning they held a grand meeting,<ptr target="med.00960_n2"/> and made
                speeches, and "resolved" many things—among the rest that they were an injured
                community, and wouldn't stand it; moreover, that they wouldn't work for less than a
                dollar and a half a day. Heretofore their pay has been a dollar a day.</p>
            <closer> 
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>   
        </body>    
    </text>
</TEI>