<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00979">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 10 October 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00979</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 10 October 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-21">21 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 10 October 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-10-10" xml:id="dat1">October 10, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-11-28" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-10-10"><handShift rend="printed"/>Tuesday,</date>
                    <date when="1848-10-10"><handShift rend="printed"/>October 10.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent:</hi></salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Last evening, by dint of an early
                appearance on the ground, and waiting resolutely amid those annoyances and
                commonplaces that full up the first hour of a "mass meeting," I got a first-rate
                view and hearing of John Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n3"/>—saw him in the strong glare of a thousand
                firework lights, and heard every word that he uttered. This was my best sight yet of
                Prince John; and I tugged the matter through on purpose to give your good Crescent a
                full description of the great Barnburner.<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> As to the meeting, (it was on the old
                spot, in the Park,) it was one of the big ones. Standing on the front steps of the
                City Hall, the most vitreous of moonlight bathing the whole scene, I stretched my
                eyes in vain to mark the confines of the mighty crowd. Lord, what a lovely night it
                was, though! And the great roar of Broadway and Chatham street—the dark and dim
                trees of the Park—long row of printers' lights in the top stories from Tammany Hall
                to Spruce street: know you not those features from your own remembrance? Surely you
                do.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The personal appearance of Van Buren would hardly warrant one in expecting from
                him any high evidences of intellectuality. His complexion is light; hair ditto; no
                beard; full and placid blue eye; frame tall enough and stout enough, and with an
                evidence of youthful freshness and vigor that would attract nineteen women's eyes
                out of twenty:</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                <q>
                <floatingText>
                <body>
                    <l>"You may look from east to west,</l>
                    <l>And then from north to south,</l>
                    <l>And never an ampler month;</l>
                    <l>A softer tone for lady's ear,</l>
                    <l>A daintier lip for syrup,</l>
                    <l>Or a ruder grasp from an axe or spear,</l>
                    <l>Or a firmer foot for stirrup."</l>
                    <byline>—<hi rend="italic">Praed.</hi><ptr target="med.00979_n7"/></byline>
                </body>
                </floatingText>
                </q>
            </p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>With his pink color, rather expressionless visage, and no
                earthly means of telling from his manner what tack he is going to take, John Van
                Buren gets small good from any earliest impressions on his audience. The matter is
                not mended either by the quality of his voice, which, neither deep nor sonorous,
                strikes you at first like the chromatic notes after hearing regular ones. But that
                voice reaches and pierces clearly to a remarkable distance in the largest and most
                noisy assembly. Mr. Van Buren has probably systematized his pitch of voice on
                acoustic principles, and from close experiment and practice. Nor would it be
                unprofitable for public speakers generally to follow his example; for some of the
                loudest and showiest speakers can neither be heard distinctly by those near them, or
                the rest at a distance. Not so with Mr. Van Buren. You have the comfort of losing
                not a word—not the inflexion of a syllable even. By-and-by, too, the voice becomes
                more agreeable, and you find it inimitably fitted to the dry and crispy humor that
                makes so large a portion of his address.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The fire of oratory, as we are accustomed
                to picture it to our minds is the historical exemplars of that divine art—the
                sweeping train of regal ornament—the impassioned appeal—graceful and dignified
                gestures—such a grand temper and port as we would identify with Cicero,<ptr target="med.00979_n4"/> or such
                lightning breath as in Demosthenes,<ptr target="med.00979_n5"/> or such molten scorn and persuasion as in
                Patrick Henry<ptr target="med.00979_n6"/> or Clay<ptr target="med.00954_n8"/> in his best days—all or either of these, in any excellence,
                Mr. Van Buren does not possess. His manner, on the contrary, is serene and smooth:
                not like the ponderous smoothness of Silas Wright,<ptr target="med.00971_n11"/> that carried with it the signs of
                depth that common plummet hardly could sound; but a calm complacency more like that
                of an indifferent, heedless child. He uses very little gesture; when he bends down
                it is almost a sure thing that he gives one of those sarcastic bits of humor that
                cut to the very hearts of his victims. And yet all seems done in good humor. There
                is not a particle of malignance or spite. I question, indeed, whether any one of
                John Van Buren's speeches shows a jot of those qualities. Honored be he, for his, at
                any rate! We have too much, among our politicians, of personal bitterness, and its
                exposure in their public proceedings. Even those at whose expense he launches his
                jokes may generally laugh with the rest.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>If I were asked to give the leading
                peculiarities of Mr. Van Buren's style and matter, I should say they were
                condensation, clearness and wit. He often presents no very new arguments; but he
                invariably presents them in a new and clearer light—so clear, indeed, that they come
                upon your mind like an explained problem in mathematics. This is assisted by his
                slow and deliberate manner; no hurry, no feverish pushing forward, but every thing
                in its due order. The difference between him and other speakers is a good deal like
                the difference between a man working by the day, and another working by the job.
                John Van Buren never tired an audience in his life, I am sure; and never worried
                them by his rapidity. His wit is of the purest sort in the world. It would extort a
                laugh from the most morose anchorite. Nothing artificial, nothing strained; but it
                comes into the body of his remarks apparently just as much a matter of course as the
                prepositions and conjunctions. No words can describe the droll way in which he now
                and then turns off a sentence on some of his opponents—thousands, meanwhile, shaking
                with laughter, does as well as friends. He possesses that rare faculty of appearing
                perfectly unconscious of his own wit; he never utters the points of a joke with an
                air which seems to demand, "Isn't that a good one?" While others laugh, he is cool,
                dry and caustic, changing not a muscle; and not a put on gravity, either.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Perhaps
                some free and easy spectator takes advantage of his right of "free speech" to utter
                a criticism or a question. He never does it a second time, however. Mr. Van Buren
                seizes upon the interpolation, and turns the laugh so totally upon the offerer of
                it, that he is fain to clinch his tongue in his teeth for the rest of the evening.
                His sarcasm has no venom, however; it is the edge of the keenest razor, not the
                tooth of the snake. It cuts so clean and clear, that you wonder for a moment whether
                there be any cut at all. Polished and vulgar, educated and ignorant, alike
                appreciate John Van Buren his humor, his logic, and his aim. There is a charming
                <hi rend="italic">abandon</hi> about him; you are fully convinced that there are no hidden motives, no
                finesse, no clap-trap or mean selfishness, behind what he has arrayed before you.
                Right or wrong, whatever the man and his mind may be, <hi rend="italic">there they are</hi>, without any
                tricks of curtaining or shading.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>You have doubtless wondered that such a man as
                Martin Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/> should have such a son as Master John. Well, I have had the same
                wonder. For John has utterly thrown overboard and set at defiance all the old rules
                and observances among professional politicians. The young men, here, would almost
                lay down their lives for him. He will prove the type of a thousand, before ten years
                are past. He will, in all likelihood start a newer and better school of political
                speech-making; which heaven help forward! The turgid and flippant manner, the
                senseless and stale matter of the whig and democratic spouters, of late years, had
                grown vile beyond endurance!</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Newspaper reports of Mr. Van Buren's addresses, unless
                they are strictly verbatim, contain but a faint copy of his wit. The latter consists
                generally in the turn of a sentence, conveying a contrast or an image so
                irresistibly comic—so Hogarthian—that you cannot for your life help laughing. It is
                not the broad humor of puns and distortions; it is fine and diffused. It is not
                farce, but the highest and most intellectual comedy. It is not an idea, one of whose
                parts is very funny; it is the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi> idea, so ludicrous. It is not a dashy stroke of
                color in the picture, making a novel effect; it is the general color, pervading the
                whole work.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>In England such a man as John Van Buren would command any gift the
                government had to bestow. Perhaps it is not that his aid would be invaluable; but
                that his enmity would have to be bought off at any price. He could do more than
                argue down the First Lord of the Treasury and his measures—he could make him and
                them ridiculous. If I were a near friend of the President, I wouldn't have John Van
                Buren in the opposition, and in Congress, for the Presidential salary. Randolph's<ptr target="n5001"/>
                attacks had so much acerbity that there was a rebound after them; but where, in a
                different and purer vein, John Van Buren's lampooning paint has once touched, there
                remains such an appearance of the preposterous in him whose garments wear the mask,
                that neither high station nor erasive soap will ever get it out.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Some of the papers
                will probably furnish you, if you have a curiosity of seeing them, a tolerable
                report of Mr. Van Buren's remarks of last evening; a correct report, as I have said,
                is almost out of the question. The sentiments of the Radical leader, here, however,
                are not likely to be preserved long, as he gives them in these addresses. They are
                for listening audiences, not for the pages of books. They will not be preserved. His
                merit is, in some sort, more the actor's merit than any other. Whether the
                sentiments will tell in future upon the action of government, time will show.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Will
                you allow me, (I am sure you will) to say one word of justice to the New York Free
                Soilers, <ptr target="med.00954_n6"/> for publication in a region where their movements are too often unfairly
                represented? Not a breath, not a thought, of unfriendliness, exists in the Van Buren
                party of New York, toward the South, or Southern men. From what I have heard and
                seen, I believe that the fraternal bond of union and good will, from this section
                toward the South—toward Louisiana and Texas in an especial manner—holds its
                brightness and its warmth unabated. At this very moment, should danger or wrong
                threaten any of the Southern States, or any general harm to life or property,
                thousands of those great masses who form the Van Buren phalanx here, would rush to
                your aid, and fear neither for comfort or life in giving it, as brother should give
                aid to brother. If I know anything of my native State and her people, (and I have
                lately had an opportunity of observing them nearly all) the general heart holds this
                faith and love toward the South, with as true and steady a truth as human nature can
                know. But the democracy of New York believe in the great principle promulgated at
                Buffalo;<ptr target="med.00961_n2"/> and the democracy of New York were virtually excluded from the Baltimore
                Convention.<ptr target="med.00952_n5"/> While they live, they will adhere to that principle; nor will they
                submit to any injury from other portions of their party. Let a few years hence
                decide the right or wrong of the dispute; they are content to leave it so.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Certain
                persons, either in error themselves or from the worst of motives, are in the habit
                of painting the Van Buren party of the North as identical with the "Abolitionists."
                A greater or grosser untruth was never written. Nearly every document emanating from
                the Free Soilers, recognizes the well understood constitutional guaranty, that over
                all subjects not expressly reserved to the General Government, States, whether they
                be North or South, have sovereign jurisdiction within their own limits. Of the
                remainder of the points at issue, I presume you do not desire any labored
                disquisition. Common justice, however, demands that no one in the South should
                charge the Radicals of New York with enmity toward their Southern fellow countrymen,
                as no one will make that charge who <hi rend="italic">knows</hi> New York. As to any danger, from this at
                present warmly conducted dispute, to our Republican Union, we laugh the idea to
                scorn! The acorn has not yet germinated, whose product oak shall be ruffled by winds
                that howl the tidings of her dissolution. The man is mad, or worse, who talks of it,
                in the same hour with his talk of events either probable or to be endured.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>  
</TEI>