<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00983">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 1 November 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00983</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 1 November 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-11-13">13 November 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 1 November 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-11-01" xml:id="dat1">November 1, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-05" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-11-01"><handShift rend="printed"/>November 1.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Oh, but we are in the midst of exciting times, now!
                Every vacant wall, despite of its "Stick no bills here," is covered with huge
                posters; and politicians have even adopted the plan of hiring boys with
                bulletin-boards, on which party announcements are pasted, to perambulate the
                streets. All the newspapers give up their columns to articles characterized by the
                various moods, potential, imperative, subjunctive and indicative&#8212;though I use those
                terms not exactly in the grammatical way. The large balls, and the back parlors of
                taverns, "teem" with political gatherings, or with secluded caucuses or committee
                meetings. O, indeed, but we <hi rend="italic">are</hi> in the midst of exciting times!</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Probably this
                excitement does not pervade any other part of the land so much as New York city.
                From what opportunities I have had for observing, there is, indeed, elsewhere, a
                remarkable apathy and lukewarmness. Here, however, the opposite currents meet: the
                results are divers dashing whirlpools. Alas, and a-lack-a-day! but the Republic is
                sure to be ruined, any how!</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>How is it going? perhaps you ask. No mortal man can
                tell, or even make a truly reliable judgment. For me&#8212;I stick to my prediction of a
                month ago, that, as the most probable event, Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/> will get this State. If he
                does, it will be one of the most remarkable triumphs ever achieved on the ground of
                an abstract principle, in our Republic! The Administration, using without scruple its
                immense scope of power against the ex-President&#8212;openly putting itself in the field
                against him; both of the old phalanxes united in an enmity toward him; no chance of
                his carrying any other State than this&#8212;and thus not the remotest probability of his
                being President; hardly a prominent, well-known leader, except a few of the faithful
                old VanBuren guard, coming out for him; and yet, I tell you again, Martin Van Buren
                is going to get the thirty-six electoral votes of New York. It is rather hazardous
                to say so&#8212;but I venture to say it.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>At danger of being somewhat trite, I cannot help
                calling the attention of your readers to the superiority of American institutions
                over those of all other governments on earth, as exhibited in the operations of an
                election for the Presidency. What in France would cause collisions certainly, and
                perhaps massacres, will here cause but a collision of opinion, and all will
                peacefully submit to the decision of the majority. Rightly viewed, indeed, these
                contests are purely contests of opinion, and not in behalf of men. Every candidate
                should, therefore, inscribe, fully and plainly upon his banner, his principal rules
                of action. Warm partisans will put forwards some excuse for the not doing of this by
                their favorite candidate; but in reality there is no fair excuse for it.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The weather
                continues warm and damp, helping forward the remarkable plenteousness of bilious
                attacks which has marked the past four months hereabout. Our "beautiful slattern" of
                a city is reveling in dirt, like a pig; the gutters are horrible. Fall lingers about
                in the appearance of the willows and the grass&#8212;those latest verdant of growing
                things.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>No gossip or news of any interest. Politics engross every body's attention;
                and so will it be till next Tuesday&#8212;after which I hope to commune again more
                frequently with your readers.</p> 
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body> 
    </text>
</TEI> 
