<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00959">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 August 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00959</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 August 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-14">14 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[3]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 August 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-08-04" xml:id="dat1">August 4, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-13" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-06" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-31" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-08-04"><handShift rend="printed"/>August 4, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>A considerable portion of "society," has after all,
                gone, out of town, to ruralize and fashionize, and achieve for themselves more
                annoyance from the change of habits, living, and every thing else that conduces to
                comfort, than if they had staid in the city. Many persons go, merely because it is
                "the fashion." In reality, however, New York, with the myriad channels of
                communicating with pleasant spots not distant—with Brooklyn, Staten Island,
                Hoboken, and other delectable retreats within sight—affords about as
                comfortable quarters as any other place; as good, even, as many fashionable summer
                resorts. Every body knows that there is just as much hot weather at those resorts as
                in town. Such is the philosophy with which we, who have to stay in New York, console
                ourselves, and make out the case in our own favor. The members of the Common
                Council, do not seem to coincide in this view of the case. Those safe grave men have
                decided to take a month's suspension from their labors. The great steamer, (her name
                is to be "the New World,") mentioned in one of my late letters, could not be induced
                to "slide," yesterday—to which time her launch had been postponed. She was
                to have been pulled afloat to-day, and probably has, by this time. She is a
                tremendous craft, the largest on our waters. Thousands were disappointed here
                yesterday from her not going off.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Among the peculiarities of the season, here, may be
                mentioned the numerous public pic-nics. Every pleasant day, there are more or less
                of these. Sunday Schools, Temperance Societies, "Unions," and all sorts of
                associations, have them. Some go by water, and some by land. Very many are
                catchpenny affairs; some are crowded to suffocation—as much money being made
                as possible, and tickets sold without any proportion to the accommodations engaged.
                It is wonderful that the steamboats hired for these occasions, are not more often
                the fields of terrible accidents and life-losing. You see these boats, of a morning,
                with children, women, and men, all clustered over like bees in a swarm—a black
                mass of humanity, without room to turn about. When they arrive at the appointed
                place, ten to one but something very important to the general comfort has been
                neglected. I went on one the other day, crowded in the manner just described, and
                not a drop of cold water to drink, on board! which, when you consider that
                two-thirds the passengers were juveniles and females, you may well conceive the
                awkwardness of. But then the bar-keeper made a capital job out of it. The weather
                has been warm and dry for the last few days. Some of the journals publish statements
                of the potato rot, but it is not generally thought, yet, that there is any reason
                for alarm. All the other crops continue to do well, and to turn out well.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>It has got
                to be quite the fashion among certain of our New York bachelors, to forego the old
                and pleasant custom of courtship, before matrimony, and seek for a wife by newspaper 
                advertisement. Here, for instance, is a specimen, from this morning's Herald:</p> 
            <q>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <p><handShift rend="printed"/>MATRIMONY.<ptr target="med.00959_n2"/>—A gentleman of twenty-five, possessed of a superior education, and a
                            more than ordinarily kind and a fortunate natural temperament, would be happy to marry 
                            a worthy girl of fair personal appearance, sound health, and respectable education, 
                            from seventeen to twenty-five years of age. A lady possessed of some property 
                            preferred. For further acquaintance, address J. F. D.,<ptr target="n5001"/> Postoffice.  The subscriber
                            begs to assure his fair readers, that whatever motives may have prompted matrimonial 
                            advertisements in other instances, his own intentions are sincere and honorable; 
                            and he earnestly requests that no lady will reply to him with views foreign to this 
                            idea. Reliance may be placed upon a strictly confidential treatment of all 
                            communications.</p>
                        <byline><handShift rend="printed"/>J. F. D.</byline>
                    </body>  
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The above no doubt is an advertisement in good faith, and it is very likely,
                will secure the object aimed at. Moreover, you must know that, of late years, there
                are two or three "matrimonial exchanges" here—offices where bachelors, widows,
                maids, and widowers, are furnished with husbands and wives, to order!</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We are just
                received the first guns in the way of election returns, from North Carolina. No
                judgment of the ultimate result can be formed from them. Though, from this moment
                the ball may be said to have opened. For three months, we shall have plenty of
                excitement. But then it is both wholesome and necessary. What in other countries,
                would be thrown off by a revolution, or an attempt at one, exhausts itself here in
                politics.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>