<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00820">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Louisa Snowdon to Walt Whitman, 2 August 1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schöberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt> 
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00820</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                <monogr>
                    <author>Horace Traubel</author>
                    <title xml:id="ht">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>
                    <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                        <date when="1953">1953</date>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">223</biblScope>
                    </imprint>
                </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Louisa Snowdon</author>
                    <title>Louisa Snowdon to Walt Whitman, 2 August 1887</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1887-08-02" xml:id="dat1">August 2, 1887</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of this manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc> 
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Snowdon, Louisa" ref="n4129">Louisa Snowdon</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-06-01" who="#smb">final check</change>
            <change when="2016-05-27" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-03-03" who="#cb">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-02-01" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-11-13" who="#aa">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Hampstead, London N. W.,</name>
                    <date when="1887-08-02">Aug. 2, 1887.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Presumptuous as it may be, I cannot refrain from sending these few lines to you from
                the old country to thank you for the new life your poems have given to me. Since
                reading them—and I have read them again and again—especially the Leaves
                of Grass, I have felt conscious of a new vista opening before me. I am only
                twenty-three—yet I feel as if the past few years (breaking away gradually, as
                I have been, from surroundings orthodox and conventional) were long eras of
                indifference and lethargy. How delightful to feel that there are such great
                possibilities in life! All my sceptical rejection of creeds and dogmas is giving
                place to a sense of the eternal fitness of things. In my blind unreasoning egotism I
                mistook the shadow for the substance, and thought that "religion" was what is
                preached from the orthodox pulpit and practiced in the city. And then I came upon
                two lines of your Leaves of Grass:</p>

            <lg>
                <l> "I swear the earth shall surely be complete to</l>
                <l> him or her who shall be complete!</l>
                <l> I swear the earth remains jagged and broken only</l>
                <l> to him or her who remains broken and jagged!"</l>
                <l/>
            </lg>
            
            <p>I wish I could explain to you in what way they touched as with a magnet some latent
                chord. And yet I feel there is no need to explain anything. <hi rend="italic">You
                will understand</hi>.</p>
            <p>I have already reached across the water and clasped your hand. I have found something
                deeper and more precious to me than your printed words. I am looking forward
                hopefully and joyfully to a future which shall not be lacking in strength.</p>
            <p>Forgive my illogical desultory manner of writing. I think you will understand all I
                would convey. The little picture of your home life in Specimen Days has so much
                interested me. Now I feel as if I knew you in the flesh as well as in the spirit.
                Accept the grateful thanks of yours faithfully.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Louisa Snowdon.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>