<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00953">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt> 
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 19 July 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00953</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahatta</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 19 July 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-07-29">29 July 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The The Daily Crescent</hi>, 19 July 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-07-19" xml:id="dat1">July 19, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc> 
        <revisionDesc>    
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-02" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-21" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-16" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-07-19"><handShift rend="printed"/>July 19, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent</hi>:—</salute>
            </opener>   
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>About the pleasantest news of the
                morning, here, is that of the report made by the Territorial Committee of eight, in
                the United States Senate, on the subject of the Oregon bill, slavery, a government
                for California and New Mexico, and so forth. Surely this is the way to settle the
                matter; and just as surely, all sensible and clear-minded men will come into it. The
                great beauty of the "laissez faire" doctrine is exemplified here—the gem above all
                price for our country—contains more vital and preservative power for the Union, than
                all the schemes of all the modern politicians combined.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>How are you receiving this
                report in the south-west? Do you not like it? Is it not perfectly consistent with
                the rights of all parties: and, above all, with the rights of the inhabitants (whom,
                by-the-bye, nobody seems to think any thing about,) of the territories themselves?
                The probability appears to be, almost beyond a doubt, that the plan reported by the
                committee of eight will satisfy the body of the "Free Soilers"<ptr target="med.00954_n6"/> of the north and
                west. It is almost sure, however, that they will meet in convention at Buffalo, in
                less than three weeks, and "pile up" their endorsement of Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/> for the
                Presidency.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The meeting of the Barnburners<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> in the Park last evening was a very large
                and somewhat tumultuous gathering. Martin Grover, M.C.,<ptr target="med.00954_n3"/> made a long and animated
                speech. At its close a few young Cass<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/> and Butlerites<ptr target="med.00954_n2"/> attempted some vigorous pushes,
                in the way of a row; but the "unterrified" rallied in great anger round a flag with
                the portrait of Martin Van Buren on it, and drove the enemy from the field, with
                divers bloody noses and contusions. It was one of those pleasant commentaries on
                political freedom, which act on the rest of its articles like the pepper of a
                wholesome soup. The police here never interfere in these interesting feuds—which is
                right and proper.</p>   
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>For some time past the strife between our New York Guelphs and
                Ghibellines<ptr target="med.00953_n3"/> has been for the possession of Old Tammany, the Mecca of the Democracy.
                Keen and exquisite have been the tactics of either; but night before last the
                Sachems, who have control of the matter, met in solemn council, and decided that Van
                Burenism <hi rend="italic">should</hi> formally enter the wigwam, and directed the rooms of the Hall to be
                placed at its use. In the meeting of last evening, a son of Mr. F. P. Blair,<ptr target="med.00954_n4"/> of the
                old democratic organ, the Washington <hi rend="italic">Globe</hi>, addressed the audience in behalf of Van
                Buren.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Among the late improvements of New York, may be particularly mentioned the
                long-talked-of widening of William street, now nearly completed. For ten years past
                Nassau street, from Wall to Chatham, has been one of the most crowded thoroughfares
                in the city. Unfortunately it is at the same time one of the narrowest and most
                inconvenient. At any hour of the day, and particularly towards dusk, it is a
                difficult feat to thread the walks of Nassau street, without some unpleasant
                jostling and squeezing. Tangling of carts, with much detention and cartmen’s oats,
                is an hourly occurrence. These difficulties could not well be obviated by enlarging
                the area of the oppressed avenue itself, which is lined with the most valuable
                structures, Clinton Hall among the rest; so they thought to draw off some of the
                travel into William street, and open it into Chatham just opposite the junction of
                the latter streets and Chambers. A good device all 'round, this is generally
                considered—though the putting of it in execution has made the dust fly in what was
                formerly the very heart of the city, (answering to your First Municipality,) for
                months past. For my part, I am astonished that, while they were about it, they
                did’nt make the street twenty feet wider instead of six. It will undoubtedly be a
                great convenience both to vehicles and pedestrians. They have for the last four or
                five days, been tearing down the houses (in the verg middle of the Jew clothing
                quarter) in Chatham street, to make the exit of William. It has an odd look already
                to the eyes of the "oldest inhabitants."</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Many of our citizens, particularly those of Irish birth and descent, are looking for 
                the arrival in New York of Mr. Meagher,<ptr target="med.00954_n5"/> the
                Repealer and Chartist. It is singular, though, that Mr. M. should have chosen just
                this occasion to withdraw himself, even briefly, from Ireland. If there be any truth
                in signs, or any determination in the Irish heart, the approaching fall will witness
                a violent struggle on the Emerald Isle—a struggle where every patriot should <hi rend="italic">be</hi> and
                <hi rend="italic">act</hi>, God defend the right, when the struggle comes!</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Rumors of the potato rot are
                appearing in the papers. Among the other places mentioned as subject to this
                vegetable malady, is Long Island; but I think I can put this down as an error—for I
                have lately travelled nearly the whole length of Long Island, and have heard nothing
                about the potato rot.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>New York is getting to be more and more disagreeable and
                unhealthy, for residence. Even in the early morning, the effluvia from the gutters
                can hardly be borne. The paving stones get so heated through during the day, that
                they do not "cool off" again till next morning. It is a great deal worse, here than
                in New Orleans. I never was so annoyed there either by heat or by the exhalations.
                Let your citizens believe me, when I tell them seriously that the city of New
                Orleans is one of the healthiest locations in the land—Yellow Jack<ptr target="med.00953_n4"/> to the contrary
                notwithstanding.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>All over our Northern cities great preparations have been made (as
                is but just) for the complimentary reception of the returned soldiers—those of them
                who <hi rend="italic">have</hi> returned. In the cases of many of them, however, the actual necessaries of
                comfort, such as clothing, etc., are more needed by the volunteers, than any empty
                glorification. Still it argues well of the public spirit of the citizens that they
                offer these courtesies. We all have part in the immortal glory won by our troops in
                that Mexican war; and it will do us good, more ways than one for many a year yet.
                Among the rest of the returned volunteers are several of our New York printers.
                Right glad are we to welcome them back again, safe and sound.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANAHATTA</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>