<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00977">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 6 October 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00977</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 6 October 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-17">17 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 6 October 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-10-06" xml:id="dat1">October 6, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc> 
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-15" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-11-28" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-10-06"><handShift rend="printed"/>October 6, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent:</hi></salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Among the choice sights of those
                diggings, few are prettier than that of a fine ship, on a fine day, dashily entering
                or departing from our noble harbor! I saw the Hendrik Hudson come up yesterday
                afternoon, in beautiful trim, and her decks swarming with passengers. How pleasantly
                they must have been impressed with their new home&#8212;those of them who were emigrating
                here. Almost every day you can see these vessels coming in, with their human
                cargoes; and sometimes, two or three ships at once......The weather still continues
                beautiful; and it is said, from the country, that the late rains have furnished
                additional grazing to the cattle, which comes very welcome, after a long drought.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Mr. Hecker,<ptr target="med.00977_n2"/> a German republican, who has suffered some for free principles in the
                Grand Duchy of Baden, was received complimentarily here yesterday. New York, you
                know, opens her arms, and gives a "treat" to every visiter of the least distinction;
                and I like the practice. Mr. Hecker receives his friends in the Governor's room
                to-day....The Taylor<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/> meeting of the New York Cartmen at Vauxhall, last night, was a
                rouser indeed! David Paul Brown,<ptr target="med.00977_n7"/> W. H. Seward<ptr target="med.00989_n8"/> and Ogden Hoffman<ptr target="med.00977_n8"/> held forth. The
                Whigs,<ptr target="med.00961_n4"/> at least the prominent ones, are generally falling into the Taylor ranks....I
                notice a capital suggestion in one of the city papers: that the new line of Collins
                &#38; Co.'s ships be named, individually, after Irving,<ptr target="med.00977_n3"/> Prescott,<ptr target="med.00977_n4"/> Bancroft<ptr target="med.00977_n5"/> and 
                Bryant.<ptr target="n6116"/> Why are not our great writers as deserving of such honors as third rate politicians?</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>During the last year there have been built in this city, about 50 large sewers, 30
                new piers, 115 new streets, including some which have been re-graded and paved: of
                the new public and private edifices, ships, and numerous such like enterprises,
                there could hardly be a catalogue made. We shall soon wrap Harlem and Manhattanville
                in our mantle; besides stretching an arm to Brooklyn, Jersey City and Williamsburg
                .... Mrs. Bishop<ptr target="med.00978_n6"/> is singing at the Park Theatre; but it is an up hill job there. The
                audiences are slim. Mr. Lover<ptr target="med.00977_n6"/> sailed for home in the Europa the other day. A band of
                25 musicians, a recent importation from Berlin, are giving concerts here....Among
                the boarders now at the Astor House is Gen. Harney.<ptr target="med.00977_n9"/> Military fame is, however, at a
                less grade, in the public estimation, here, than usual. This is noticeable at the
                theatres, where the appearance of the biggest military characters attract no
                attention......That story going the rounds of the papers, (from the Buffalo
                Commercial,) about a "man going over the falls," smacks too much of the
                penny-a-liner. It is a very pretty story as it stands; but one has no spare sympathy
                to expend these days....It is estimated by "E. M."<ptr target="n5001"/> the celebrated Brooklyn
                weather-man, who is up all night watching the clouds and thermometer, that the rain
                of the late storm here fell to the unusual depth of 5&#190; inches....Korth,<ptr target="med.00961_n3"/> (Brooklyn,)
                whose case I have described in former letters, has been pronounced <hi rend="italic">guilty</hi>, of
                assault with intent to murder, and will in all probability receive a pretty severe
                sentence....The mails for the Acadia, which left Boston on the 3d inst., did not get
                in from New York in time&#8212;including the great Southern mail. They will go out by the
                next steamer.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
