<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00952">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>   
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 July 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00952</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahatta</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 July 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-07-27">27 July 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>   
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 July 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-07-14" xml:id="dat1">July 17, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc> 
        <revisionDesc> 
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-02" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-14" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-16" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-07-17"><handShift rend="printed"/>July 17, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent</hi>—</salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Whatever may be said of the "horrible state of society"
                in Paris, it certainly affords glorious times for newspaper editors and
                correspondents. How beautiful! every week some plot or counter-plot—some
                <hi rend="italic">èmeute</hi>—some danger to Government and public safety. Why, they will soon turn
                up their noses in Paris, at a disturbance that involves the destruction of less than
                a thousand or two lives!—"Blessed is that people," says some very big
                philosopher whose name I forget, "who have no annals to write"—meaning, I
                suppose, that nothing bad, at least, can be said about said people. But that's
                questionable philosophy. Human nature looks best when developed by struggles, and
                changes of circumstances. Lethargy and stagnation, you know, are not only connected
                together, but are the most uninteresting qualities in the world.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Our good city of New York, now-a-time, is blessed with hardly
                any annals to write. Editors, it is true, <hi rend="italic">are</hi> writing, every day; and the people read what
                they write. But the latter is merely created, for the most part, "to fill up." 
                (Alas, that some process equally handy could'nt be hit upon to produce the same effect 
                on the poorer children of Old Ireland!) The situation of New York precludes her daily journals
                from making an important ingredient of that melange of miscellaneous news, which is so desirable to
                the papers of other places. We have to eke out something original; something that
                <hi rend="italic">looks</hi> fresh, at any rate—even though it is like a new quilt made of old
                materials. Readers' appetites here will no more be satisfied with any thing less
                than dishes on a great scale, and of the latest style of dressing. Yet there is a
                wondrous amount of superficiality in the daily disquisitions spread before that
                hydra-headed creature "the public," by the daily and weekly gazettes. "Flat, stale,
                and unprofitable," are, indeed, more than half the "leaders" (particularly during
                summer) of the Northern newspapers. I will say nothing of the Southern ones, because
                you have them among you to speak for themselves.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/><choice><sic/><corr>"</corr></choice>It is now a settled and
                irrevocable <hi rend="italic">fact</hi> that the democrats of New York," yclept Barnburners,<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> have broken
                away utterly and altogether from "the party," as organized in the Baltimore
                Convention,<ptr target="med.00952_n5"/> and developed in the nominations of 
                Cass<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/> and Butler.<ptr target="med.00952_n2"/> 
                Martin Van Buren,<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/>
                from his farm at Kinderhook, looks out upon the troubled waves, but evinces no
                inclination to say, "Peace, be still." It is understood that he was violently
                opposed to accepting the nomination of the Convention at Utica; but things took such
                an enthusiastic turn there, and his oldest and truest friends had so committed
                themselves, and his name, that he will now, it is said, allow matters to take their
                own course. The Radicals here, confidently expect, in his name, to carry the State
                of New York.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>John Van Buren,<ptr target="med.00989_n3"/> as soon as the nomination was made, wrapped himself up
                in lavender, and laid his political body on the shelf—swearing with an oath of
                the old sort, that he would spout no more during this campaign. John will keep good,
                though, for future use; and that, before many seasons, he must be "brought out," is
                as certain as that the morning star will rise. All the young fellows of the North,
                cotton to John; there is such a buoyancy, frankness, and such a charming <hi rend="italic">abandon</hi>, in
                his sayings and doings. Shrewd judges of mankind say that Master John has the making
                of a better man, than the man who made him. In the way of amusements, New York is
                yet unflagging. Hamblin<ptr target="med.00952_n6"/> has taken the Park Theatre, which he will carry on in
                conjunction with the Bowery. Heaven send him success; for the "old man's" stout
                heart deserves it. Burton's Theatre, (Palmo's old place in Chambers street,) has had
                the Viennoise dancing children. At the Astor Place Opera House, have been performed
                during the summer, comedies and vaudevilles—to-morrow night, they present some
                music, with a Mons. and Madame Laborde,<ptr target="med.00952_n3"/> from Paris. The Monplaisiers<ptr target="med.00952_n4"/> are at the
                Broadway—and "the "B'hoys" at the Chatham. Besides all these, we have Castle
                Garden, Museums, Concerts, Shows, etc., without end.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Our streets and public places present, at intervals, something connected with the "late war," 
                as it must now be called—something in the way of a soldier or officer in his yet worn uniform,
                or a mutilated relic of what <hi rend="italic">was</hi> a stalwart man, but whom disease, or bullet or
                bayonet, has shorn of his fair proportions. Will it not be a little curious to see
                what effect, over and athwart the land, the bringing home whence they started, and
                rediffusing among us, a <hi rend="italic">real army</hi>, will have on the affairs of the Republic? You
                remember, through the war, the anti-fighting folks predicted all sorts of dangers,
                when peace should make it necessary to disband our army. It is difficult, though, to
                perceive any likelihood of such dangers in any circumstances at present existing.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANAHATTA</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>