<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00951">
    <teiHeader> 
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The
                        Daily Crescent</hi>, 14 July 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00951</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahatta</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                                Crescent</hi>, 14 July 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-07-25">25 July 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                        Crescent</hi>, 14 July 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-07-14" xml:id="dat1">July 14, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>  
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>   
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-02" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-14" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-16" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter"> 
        <body>
            <opener>  
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-07-14"><handShift rend="printed"/>July 14, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>As we are now "on the eve of an important election,"
                such meetings as I have attempted to describe in my last are frequent here. They are
                held by whigs<ptr target="med.00961_n4"/> and democrats, Taylorites<ptr target="med.00989_n10b"/> and Clayites<ptr target="med.00951_n2"/>—Barnburners 
                and Old Hunkers.<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> I
                have noticed, however, that the Clay whigs and the Barnburner democrats seem to be
                the most anxious to hold these grand talking matches. The other parties call as few
                as possible.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>There is much complaint in and about the city, among all classes, 
                of "dull times." I know very many mechanics who are out of work, and can't get pay for
                work they have done. This is the complaint among all branches and trades, to an
                unusual extent. Immigration pours in without the least abatement. Hardly a day
                passes that hundreds of poor wayfarers from Europe do not land upon our wharves;
                some no doubt, to sink amid disease or poverty, but most, I am happy to say, to take
                a start which brings them amid better times and far more comfort. What is most
                astonishing to me, is the fact that with such prevalent poverty as characterises the
                masses of the immigrants, there is so little criminality. Political economists are
                fond of arguing that Penury is the Mother of Crime: but take an equal number of
                well-off people, and, compared with these immigrants, you will surely find not only
                a great deal more viciousness, but infinitely more of crime which the law takes
                cognizance of. The police very seldom have any trouble with the poor
                immigrants—except, alas! now and then to take a pallid mother and her starving
                children to the alms house. There are certain persons who see evil in these
                accessions from abroad; but I defy even them to contradict the well-known facts
                above mentioned. Moreover, this city is the great receiving point of European
                emigration.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>A very general satisfaction exists here at the prospect presented by the
                advent of the steamer "Crescent City," of reducing the travelling time between New
                York and New Orleans, to a point before considered out of the question, except in
                rare cases, and then only by being racked to death with incessant travel and daily
                changes. It is now pretty certain that, when you get off the levee at New Orleans of
                a Sunday morning, and go on board the right sort of steamer, the next Sunday will
                find you in New York—and vice versa. By the inland route, either down the Ohio or
                across the Lakes, you require, allowing for unavoidable stoppages, detentions, etc.,
                from thirteen to twenty days, averaging fifteen days at least. Then the comfort of
                making the entire trip without transferring yourself or baggage. My belief is that
                New York and New Orleans have more identity of character and interest than any other
                two cities in America. Both are distinguished by a sort of citizen-of-the-world
                disposition; and in both there is a blessed freedom from all provincialism and the
                gossip of second-rate towns. May the telegraph and a few lines of rapid steamers
                conduce to draw still closer and stouter the bands of union!</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANAHATTA</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body> 
    </text>
</TEI>