<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00818">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 28 April 1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00818</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Horace Traubel</author>
                        <title xml:id="ht">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="page">487&#8211;488</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 28 April 1887</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1887-04-28" xml:id="dat1">April 28, 1887</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of this manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-05-31" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-05-27" who="#ss">final check</change>
            <change when="2016-02-15" who="#cb">checked</change>
            <change when="2015-11-21" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-11-07" who="#aa">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">59 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea,<lb/>London</name>
                    <date when="1887-04-28">April 28, 1887</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute> 
            </opener>
            <p>Your two postcards are to hand. I expect the printed
                slips to Preface and Additional Note have reached you ere this; I told the
                publishers to forward them. We have taken great pains to make the reprint
                correct&#8212;following the American spelling, &#38;c., faithfully. It is all out of
                my hands now, and I do hope everything will turn out well. It has been rather a
                troubled time with me lately, with far too much work on hand to do everything with
                the ample margin for revisal that I like, but all's well that ends well. As there
                was some uncertainty about the process reproduction of that photo, for frontispiece
                or inserted plate, and having the unlucky experience of the portrait in L. of G. to
                go by, we decided to leave the portrait out altogether. Better none at all, as you
                say, than a bad one.</p> 
            <p>By this post I send a copy of the Pall Mall Gazette with a paragraph taken from the
                Additional Note to the new vol. The P.M.G usually treats me rather cavalierly over
                my own things: the young fellows who do the literary part, and do it capitally
                too&#8212;Henry Norman<ptr target="loc.00720_n1"/>, O. Wilde<ptr target="med.00818_n3"/> and so on&#8212;are
                most of them university men, with rather a contempt for unacademic outsiders. In
                the case of this paragraph I got young Horne to propose it to Norman, and so worked
                the oracle. In the same paper, notice the article, Some April Insects, by Richard
                    Jefferies.<ptr target="med.00818_n2"/> I think you will like it. Jefferies is
                one of our best writers on Nature over here; his writing is at once true and subtle,
                and very natural and simple withal. Did you ever read his Story of My Heart? A very
                passionate confession of faith and fear it was, with a sentiment in it that made
                some of the critics say it must be inspired by your L. of G. If you have not yet
                seen it, I should like to send it on. Jefferies is editing the vol. to follow yours
                in the series&#8212;White's Selborne. He writes to tell me that he is an invalid,
                poor lover of all things bright and helpful. He lives down in Sussex, near the
                sea.</p>
            <p>W.S. Kennedy<ptr target="n3039"/> sent over a fresh batch of addenda for his book. It
                    <hi rend="italic">is</hi> unfortunate&#8212;this delay through Wilson's illness;
                but Kennedy takes it very cheerily. He seems a fine impulsive fellow by his letters.
                In the last one he proposes that I should try some other schemes for getting the
                book afloat. We shall see. This evening Herbert Gilchrist<ptr target="n0262"/> is
                coming down here to look through Kennedy's book, and something may suggest itself to
                us. We are going on afterwards to Costelloe's, as H.G. is anxious to know Mrs.
                C.,<ptr target="n6109"/> who has been away in Surrey over Easter with her
                husband. I look forward with delight to seeing her again. She is truly a most noble
                and delightful nature. She is a little afraid perhaps of your deterministic theories
                (further elaborated by Doctor Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/>) and non-moral apotheosis
                of evil; but that is natural enough. I, too, often doubt any absolute empire, even
                the most cosmic, over the human will: that is my feeling only, for I don't pretend
                to any philosophical complete creed.</p>
            <p>I was glad to hear of the great success of your Lincoln lecture.<ptr target="med.00797_n1"/> Would that I had
                been there to hear it. I should like to have come over with H. Gilchrist, but cannot
                manage to leave so soon. He will be with you I expect in the course of a few weeks
                more.</p>
            <p>Are you going up to Doctor Bucke's place for the summer?</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Affectionately yours,</salute>
                <signed>Ernest Rhys.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
