<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>  
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00711">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 9 April 1883</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D, O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="rf">Ryan Furlong</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00711</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Horace Traubel</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ht">With Walt Whitman in Camden vol. 4</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">138-139</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 9 April 1883</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-04-09" xml:id="dat1">April 9, 1883</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">Mediated.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt"/>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-06-24" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-11-16" who="#rf">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Washington, D.C.,</name>
                    <date when="1883-04-09">April 9, 1883.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Here you are! Good, too! I managed to get down to the Congressional this morning, and copied the 
          enclosed from the Areopagitica. I think it makes a capital epigraph.</p>
            
            <p> It will add force to the argument to print it as I have copied it, with the full title of the treatise
           appended, since "unlicensed printing" is the subject of our story. I think you will agree that the passage
           fits the case also in other ways, and I hope you will like it.</p>

            <p>Winter has a characteristic dirty squib in today's Tribune anent of Doctor Bucke's<ptr target="n0119"/> book. I hope the 
           dose I have given him in the Introductory may be appreciated by him. Goodbye. Faithfully</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>W.D. O'Connor</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>[Enclosure] "As good almost kill a man as kill a good book; who kills a man kills a reasonable creature, God's image; but he who 
                    destroys a good book, kills reason itself, kills the image of God, as it were in the eye. Many a man lives a burden to the earth, but a 
                    good book is the precious lifeblood of a master-spirit embalmed and treasured 
                    up on purpose, to a life beyond life. 'Tis true no age can restore a life, whereof perhaps there is no great loss; but revolutions of ages 
                    do not oft recover the loss of a rejected truth, for the want of which all nations fare the worse. We should be wary, therefore, what 
                    persecution we raise against the living labors of public men; how we spill that seasoned life of man preserved and stored up in books,
                    since we see a kind of homicide may be thus committed, sometimes a martyrdom."</p>
                
                <p> W. exclaimed: "That should be carved over the door of every library, every publishing house, every public place whatsoever:
                    children should be taught it: grown-up people should be forced to remember it: it is precious, sacred, everlasting: William was right:
                    it fits our case, our struggles against adversity: few people know what we have had to go through to get even where we are today&#8212;
                    which is none too far. Horace,<ptr target="n4267"/> read it again before you stick it in your pocket." I did so. He exclaimed "Amen! Amen!" when I was 
                    through.</p>
            </postscript>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
