<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00971">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 26 September 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="pjz">PJ Zaborowski</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00971</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 26 September 1848</title>
                    </analytic> 
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-07">7 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 26 September 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-09-26" xml:id="dat1">September 26, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-14" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-08" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-12-13" who="#pjz">added notes and checked transcription</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-09-22"><handShift rend="printed"/>September 26, 1848</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds.
                    Crescent</hi>—</salute>
            </opener> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>There is a fair probability of the "malignants" of the
                whig party here coming into subjection soon, under the banner of Taylorism.<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/> 
                Mr. N. B. Blunt<ptr target="med.00971_n1"/> has followed David Graham,<ptr target="med.00971_n2"/> and, though 
                no one knows exactly "who's the next customer," it wouldn't be very surprising if it were Mr. Greeley<ptr target="med.00972_n1"/> himself. His paper
                has had an unusual squinting that way of late. The separate nominations for State
                officers by the whigs,<ptr target="med.00961_n4"/> hunkers and barnburners<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> have exercised considerable influence
                toward re-marking distinct lines between the parties. Then there is the great
                probability of Fish's<ptr target="med.00970_n1"/> election, and whig success in the Legislature, which will
                result in some hundreds of appointments. The latter facts have contributed very much
                toward a general "harmonizing" of the whigs. The Clay<ptr target="med.00954_n8"/> men have a meeting at Vauxhall
                to-night, whereat the fiery and eloquent Virginian, John M. Botts,<ptr target="med.00971_n8"/> is to hold forth.
                It will doubtless be serviceable in letting the said Clay men drop gracefully into
                the open and expectant arms of Taylorism. Probably, however, as much mischief has
                already been done as could be done, on this point. Those among the masses who have
                been carried over from the whigs to "free soil" cannot easily be recaptured.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>John
                Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/> is roaming around through the interior of the State. During the last days
                of last week he addressed large meetings at Herkimer and Utica. All accounts agree
                in stating that Van Buren divides the western and interior parts of the State with
                Taylor. In those parts, Gen. Cass<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/> may be emphatically said to be "nowhere." In the
                eastern regions, in Kings county, and in two or three other counties, he does much
                better.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Capt. Bertrand<ptr target="med.00969_n1"/> and Mr. Watson,<ptr target="med.00969_n2"/> of 
                the ship Alhambra, (for Antwerp, but put
                in here) whose case, under charge of murder by flogging a seaman, was detailed in
                one of my late letters, yet remain in prison here. The bail of Capt. B. has been
                fixed at $2500</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Green, the ex-gambler,<ptr target="med.00971_n9"/> is again lecturing in town. He exhibits, at
                these lectures, some curious diagrams and tricks—quite sufficient to astonish such
                unsophisticated ones as your humble servant.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Bishop Onderdonk's<ptr target="med.00971_n3"/> case is again to
                come up before the Annual Episcopal Convention, which convenes at St. John's Church
                to-morrow. His friends are trying to move heaven and earth (particular earth) for a
                revocation of the sentence on the amorous Bishop, and a general white-washing of his
                character.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Theatricals are prospering better now than erewhile. At the Park, which
                was miserably attended for the first fortnight after its opening, the manager has
                brought out "Esmeralda," the Monplaisirs,<ptr target="med.00952_n4"/> Miss Bulan<ptr target="med.00971_n4"/> 
                and Corby<ptr target="med.00971_n5"/> doing the leading
                characters. The piece has a good run, and still attracts fair audiences. At the
                Bowery, last night, Mr. Hamblin<ptr target="med.00952_n6"/> appeared as Hamlet, with Miss Mary Taylor<ptr target="med.00971_n6"/> as
                Ophelia! Forty years ago, Hamblin could have done justice to this sublimest drama in
                the language; he never can any more. Miss Taylor is shockingly out of place as a
                tragedy queen. Her voice is pleasing, but she cannot even begin to exhibit the
                beauties which "Shakspeare drew" of the love-sick daughter of old Polonius. Forrest<ptr target="loc.03259_n7"/> 
                played all last week at the Broadway to crowded and applauding houses. Mr. Collins<ptr target="med.00971_n7"/> 
                commenced, last night, at the same place, a round of Irish characters. He is very
                popular, and really plays better than any Irish comedian at present among us. At the
                National, "Mose" and "Captain Tobin" continue to attract. That was a capital idea of
                Chanfrau's<ptr target="med.00971_n13"/> (or somebody else's), in carrying out an original representation of the
                New York rowdy and "b'hoy." It wouldn't be bad if the originality were extended
                farther and wider. Placide,<ptr target="med.00958_n10"/> Sefton<ptr target="med.00958_n16"/> and 
                Vanderhoff<ptr target="med.00958_n23"/> are enacting "London
                Assurance"—that flippant production—at Niblo's, Astor Place. Mmlle. Adelaide Lehmann<ptr target="med.00958_n22"/> 
                and Charles Winther<ptr target="med.00958_n20"/>  glide, leap and hop through the "Sylphide," at Burton's, in
                Chambers street; and there are are concerts, and picture exhibitions, and panoramas,
                and dioramas, and all sorts of negro minstrels with twenty other kinds of
                amusements, good, bad and indifferent....The Acadia brought over Macready<ptr target="loc.03259_n4"/> and Mrs.
                G. Barrett,<ptr target="med.00958_n21"/>  who will probably play together. It is not known positively, but it is
                expected they will appear at the Park. Whichever house they don't play in should
                forthwith checkmate them by engaging Charlotte Cushman,<ptr target="med.00958_n19"/>  who has more real genius
                than all the foreign actors that have come to us since the time of Edmund Kean<ptr target="loc.03259_n2"/> and
                George F. Cooke.<ptr target="med.00958_n18"/>  A plan is in operation for a grand benefit to the family of Mr.
                Simpson;<ptr target="med.00958_n2"/>  it will come off the ensuing month.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>I see that the Crescent City leaves
                here on the 2d of October, and is advertised to sail hence again on the 30th of the
                same month. The new steamer Falcon, Capt. W. T. Thompson,<ptr target="med.00958_n17"/> leaves for New Orleans—via
                Havana, same as the Crescent City—on the 16th of October; passage $75 and $60. The
                U.S. mail steam-packet California, to San Francisco and Astoria, and intermediate
                ports, leaves on the 2d of October.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>