<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00957">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 30 July 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00957</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 30 July 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-11">11 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 30 July 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-07-30" xml:id="dat1">July 30, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-03" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-28" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-07-30"><handShift rend="printed"/>S<hi rend="smallcaps">UNDAY</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">IGHT</hi>,</date>
                    <date when="1848-07-30"><handShift rend="printed"/>July 30, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent</hi>—</salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>A Sunday morning in the city of New
                York, and in the heart of summer! Let me describe to you how it is. First of all, the
                dry, dead-warm air, is any thing else than pleasant. From a hundred thousand close
                yards, sinks, gutters, etc., come up exhalations that do not exactly remind one of
                those "perfumes of sweet flowers," which the deceptive Mr. Melnotte<ptr target="med.00956_n3"/> pourtrayed as in
                his palace gardens, "by the Lake of Como." Comparatively, all is quiet—for in New
                York we don't consider the rattling of a few hundred milk wagons, and the shrill
                cries from the army of news-boys, as of much account in the way of noise. The
                omnibusses, and the whole list of trading and pleasure vehicles, are put by;
                although some of the latter do come out in the afternoon ("Bowery boys" and young
                cartmen, are the most remorseless creatures toward horse-flesh in the world.)</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>During the hours from sunrise to 10 o'clock, this stillness, 
                and the closedness of all the
                stores, give a peculiar appearance, and rather a dreary one, to our city. The
                fountains of vitality seem dried up. It is not a religious aspect—I have observed
                that in Protestant countries it is impossible to give such an aspect to <hi rend="italic">cities</hi>. It
                is more of a constrained and uncomfortable look—one not from disposition, so much as
                fear. Still people buy and read the Sunday papers at a great rate; as that, during
                the morning, is the only amusement left them. It is a singular fact that the best
                paying newspaper establishments here, are those which issue on Sunday.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Towards 10
                o'clock, more signs of liveliness are exhibited. Groups of young fellows, sometimes
                accompanied by the female members of their families, start out on excursions to the
                country, or on some of the steamboat trips up the North or East Rivers. Very many go
                for miles on foot, after crossing the ferry, either to Staten Island, Hoboken,
                Brooklyn, or Williamsburg. Half-grown lads, on these occasions, are "death" to any
                fruit trees that stand in their path—even green apples disappear before them with
                wondrous celerity, and many and many are the angry disputes that arise between these
                young insurgents and the farmers of the neighboring towns. A little after 10, people
                of a pious turn of mind, and many that are not, begin to wend their way churchward.
                That's the time to see the New York ladies! By hundreds and thousands—aye, by tens
                of thousands—they slowly fill the side-walks, and, as if conscious of their charms,
                eke out the time between starting from home and arriving at church, to its utmost
                dimensions. If you have courage enough (which many have not, who are as brave as
                lions in cases of personal peril,) to stem a continual tide of slowly-walking,
                well-dressed and curiously observant human beings—walking at them for square after
                square—you will behold something, now, worth seeing. What care has been evinced in
                their toilets! How bewitchingly the ladies' bonnets sit upon their heads! How proud
                look the very breast-pins reposing upon their bosoms! After all, can there be a work
                of Nature that will compare with a beautiful, tastefully dressed female, in whose
                face the good points of the sex are expressed, and who has no affectation?</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>From half-past 10 to 12, there is a lull again. If you pass by the churches, you will
                hear the vocal utterance of worship, in some of its various forms—prayer, song, or
                sermon. Occasionally, some powerful brother makes the air vibrate with his
                wrestlings and exhortings—then, elsewhere, the deep notes of some heavy organ shake
                the very ground under your feet. But why should we merely describe? Let us go forth
                and enter one of the temples.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Here we are in front of "Trinity." The brown marble
                rises above, in its elegant and grand proportions—the cross on the top of the spire
                glitters in the sun. Though it looks so little up there, it is, in reality, some
                fifteen feet in length. The spot on which we stand has been used, from the first
                settlement of the Island, for church purposes; it is one of the few <hi rend="italic">historical</hi> spots
                yet preserved intact. This is the fourth temple erected on it—each being
                successively larger than the preceding one. Upon entering it, the eye is first
                struck by the immense window, of beautiful stained glass, in the rear, on which the
                Saviour and several of the Apostles are delineated, of the size of life. The colors
                are of the most brilliant description—almost painfully brilliant, unless one's eyes
                are strong. The roof, with its arches and hollows and sounding depths, is of the
                same solid marble as the walls. The columns, with their tracery and knotted work,
                are also of marble. The floor is of polished stone. Even the window frames are of
                similar lasting material. It is a grand place; the mind feels awed and hushed, and
                made serene, here.—Now the organ is touched. How it reverberates through the arches;
                and how the sound seems sent back from the roof above! The brilliants colors of the
                glass would seem gaudy under any other circumstances; but they are prevented from
                being so by the fact that all the rest is somber brown, the marble color, and no
                fancy hues of gilding anywhere. The pews are of dark oak, merely polished by
                rubbing—no varnish or paint.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Trinity is a <hi rend="italic">free</hi> church, too; at least it is so to all
                intents and purposes. Some of the old pew-holders, and those who own rights there
                hereditary, still remain in possession; but the large majority of the worshippers
                are those who come "without money and without price." On every successive Sunday,
                you even behold many of the "lower orders" worshipping at Trinity. Old Mr. Berrian<ptr target="med.00956_n4"/>
                is still the rector; but the principal talent resides in, and most of the work is
                done by, two or three assistants. Rev. Mr. Berrian is not only aged, but his voice
                is not good—a serious defect in such a large place.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Very much of the interest
                connected with this church lies in the grave-yard which surrounds it. At the left
                hand of the entrance is the grave of Lawrence,<ptr target="med.00956_n5"/> the gallant captain, whose memory
                will ever be idolized in our Navy. Until a couple of years since, it was in an old
                dilapidated corner of the yard, on Rector street. Since the completion of the
                present church it has been removed. At the corners are four cannon, placed in the
                ground in a perpendicular manner, and serving as corner posts.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Soon after 12
                o'clock, the churches begin pouring out their living tides. Then the flood is
                plentier than before. They block up the walks and impede each others' passage. For
                about half an hour, the streets are indeed "alive." Walk in through them, and
                beholding so many myriads, all dressed so well, and looking well, one might be
                excused for doubting whether there were any such thing as penury on Manhattan
                Island.—(He would make a great mistake, however, who should so doubt.)</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>During the
                afternoon and evening, the city presents a more varied aspect than in the morning.
                The more lazy ones, who have dawdled through the morning in a half dressed and
                half-awake condition, now come forth. Some of the Eastere<ptr target="med.00957_n1"/> avenues witness the fears
                of equestrians, and behold the presence not only of "three minuters," but of hacks
                and drudges, whose sinews are whipped to their utmost exertions.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Sundown and
                darkness do not close the scene; then the churches are filled again; and,
                particularly among the Methodists, an additional vigor seems infused through their
                spiritual tendencies. It is a creditable fact, that, though groups and parties,
                enjoying themselves as much as the day and circumstances will permit, continue in
                the streets and public places till a late hour, there is very rarely any disturbance
                that calls for the interference of the police.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>So much for some of the features on
                the surface of a New York Sunday. Of course, the great volume of individual and
                family life rolls on beneath this, much as elsewhere. Whether on the Rhone, the
                Mississippi or the Hudson, the principal points of human nature are the same.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>  
        </body> 
    </text> 
</TEI>