<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00992">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 5 January 1849</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00992</idno></publicationStmt> 
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 5 January 1849</title>
                    </analytic> 
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1849-01-16">16 January 1849</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[1]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 5 January 1849</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1849-01-05" xml:id="dat1">January 5, 1849</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2022-02-23" who="#smb">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-26" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-10-28" who="#smb">added notes</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1849-01-05"><handShift rend="printed"/>Jan. 5, 1849.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Among the New York editors, your and my old friend M.
                M. Noah,<ptr target="med.00992_n1"/> the Nestor<ptr target="med.00992_n2"/> 
                of the band, leads the list—in point of age and experience, at
                any rate. What a successful editor he has been! Good-hearted, always willing to do
                a kindness, liberal handed, not too nice in his political morality, true to his
                friends, and not very spiteful toward his foes, desirous to live well, and almost
                equally desirous that others also should live well—such are some of the
                characteristics of Major Noah. He has seen New York grow up, as it were; at any rate
                he has seen the growth of what we possess in the way of literature and classic
                refinement. For some forty years he has trod the stage—and life, that has proved a
                tragedy to so many, has been to him an even drama. Long may it be ere the curtain
                drops upon his last act!</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Major Noah still retains his portliness of form, activity
                of limb, and benevolence of feature. He mixes much with the world, and is acceptable
                every where. You may see him of an evening, for a stray hour, on a back bench in the
                first tier of the Olympic—or perhaps the Broadway. He has excellent taste as a
                critic of the drama, and has written some by no means bad pieces himself. When he
                condescends to talk in the gossiping vein, of past times, then you get a treat
                indeed. We know few persons who are more entertaining in conversation than Major
                Noah. He is always lively, with French vivacity and grace in his style—and always
                brings up something interesting. He is now a proprietor and editor of the "Sunday
                Times,"<ptr target="med.00992_n3"/> and it is said, likes a little dab in the editorial columns of some other
                prints, too. Few men have more personal friends, and few men have done as much good,
                according to their means.</p>   
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Col. James Watson Webb,<ptr target="med.00992_n4"/> may perhaps, without impropriety,
                stand next upon our list. His journal undoubtedly exercises a good deal of
                influence—at least it does, if those appalling large advertising sheets ever
                exercise any influence. The style of Col. Webb's writing is forcible, almost
                dictatorial, with many dashes of self opinion, scorn, and impatience of opposing
                argument. Col. W. is considered as the head, among editors, of "the other side" of
                the whigs, than Horace Greeley.<ptr target="duk.00474_n11"/>  He lives in style, and always among the "upper ten."
                He used to have town houses and country houses; but alas! such things seem not
                intended for editors; and so they have failed him. Col. Webb, in person, is full and
                healthy looking; he limps a little, from the effects of a wound in a well-known
                rencontre.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Since the death of Col. Stone,<ptr target="med.00992_n5"/> 
                Mr. John Inman<ptr target="med.00992_n6"/> has been principal editor
                of the Commercial Advertiser. By most persons it is considered a still better paper
                under his management than formerly. Col. Stone was remarkably conservative; he
                inherited the notions of the old federalists, or rather shared them, and was, in
                politics, somewhat of a thorn in the whig side, for he never deigned to "soft soap"
                the people. Mr. Inman is more genial in ideas and sentiments. He possesses
                considerable literary talent, and was for some time the principal editor of the
                "Columbian Magazine." His writings, however, are not deep; their principal merits
                are a flowing style, and an opportune choice of subject. Mr. Inman labors under an
                infirm state of health consequent upon too continued application.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Mr. Beach,<ptr target="med.00992_n7"/> you
                know, has retired from the "Sun," and left it to his boys. That was a lucky "spec"
                of his, in getting hold of the little ricketty, dingy concern that few expected to
                live six months! Perhaps the records of newspaper experience furnish no instance of
                a more rapidly growing and widely flourishing newspaper. Mr. Beach had his good and
                his indifferent qualities. I cannot say I think he possessed <hi rend="italic">bad</hi> ones, decidedly.
                One of these days I intend to give you a description of the "Sun" establishment.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Should you like, these sketches of New York editors will be continued from time to time.</p> 
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>