<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00963">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 August 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00963</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 August 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-26">26 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 17 August 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-08-17" xml:id="dat1">August 17, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">updated notes for publication</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-14" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-06" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-11-07" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-08-17"><handShift rend="printed"/>August 17, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We were blessed with a most refreshing rain this morning,
                after a dry spell of three weeks, which had parched the ground to powder. New York
                is now in the height of the "dog-day" season. In every street, except those high up
                town, the very air one has to breathe is offensive, even without the loads of dust
                we have had of late. I am convinced that for some four or five weeks, the hot
                weather here is much more unbearable than any of yours at the South. Our evenings
                and mornings afford no relief during this time. The former are too disagreeable to
                sleep, and the latter send up odors to heaven whose offence is indeed rank. The heat
                is very stifling and oppressive, to people of feverish dispositions, causing a very
                fair idea of purgatory. Of course the only philosophy for the time is of that cool
                and easy sort which does not get disturbed by trifles. One had far better bear the
                ills he has than get excited and fly to others a thousand times worse.<ptr target="med.00963_n5"/> What's the
                state of the caloric in the Crescent City?</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>You can have no idea of the highly-strung interest felt by
                us New Yorkers in the progress of affairs in Ireland.<ptr target="loc.03571_n1d"/>
                It even divides public attention with the political matters of our own land. Surely,
                never before was there such a prospect of a collusion between power and right, as
                the last accounts from Ireland warranted.<ptr target="med.00963_n3"/> Here is the
                spirit-stirring appeal of the Directory<ptr target="med.00963_n4"/> for this
                city:</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>[We published yesterday the appeal above alluded to. It is
                a nobly and eloquently worded document, short but comprehensive.—<hi rend="italic">Eds. Crescent</hi>.]</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>I see a little letter under date of July 24th, from Gen.
                    Taylor,<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/> in which the old hero says, "I am not a
                party candidate, and, if elected, shall not be the President of a party, but of the
                whole People." Good for Taylor! Such letters do him benefit here, far more than may
                be imagined.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Notwithstanding the heat, the places of public amusement
                keep open and are doing a good business. Hamblin<ptr target="med.00952_n6"/> is
                progressing rapidly with his improvements of the Park Theatre, both internally and
                externally. I have no doubt at all that he will make the establishment pay, and that
                it will prove one of the most popular places of dramatic entertainment in America.
                At the Bowery, now, they are balleting—Ciocca<ptr target="med.00963_n2"/> and
                Miss Turnbull<ptr target="med.00963_n1"/> being the principal performers. Niblo's
                (the Astor Opera House,) gives light comic pieces; Barton's ditto; and the National
                (Chatham) the usual variety.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Have you had any meetings in New Orleans to raise
                contributions for Ireland? If not, will you allow me to suggest the holding of one
                    <hi rend="italic">forthwith?</hi></p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>