<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00970">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 22 September 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00970</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 22 September 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-03">3 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 22 September 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-09-22" xml:id="dat1">September 22, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">updated notes for publication</change>
            <change when="2023-02-14" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-08" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-11-18" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-09-22"><handShift rend="printed"/>Sept. 22, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We are all glad to see, in this morning's telegraphic
                account from your city, that agreeable little sentence, "The yellow fever<ptr target="med.00953_n4b"/> is
                gradually decreasing." Although the terrible reputation of the fever is much of it
                fanciful, still, there is quite enough of bad about it, to make it a dreaded
                visiter. It is singular, however, how much alarm there is in a name. Thousands of
                persons have been kept away, and hundreds have been frightened away, of late, from
                New York, because the yellow fever existed, in the most limited manner, on Staten
                Island, eight miles off. At the same time, and particularly for some months
                previous, a deadly and malignant dysentery,<ptr target="med.00964_n2"/> and that frightful malady the ship
                fever—in both of which the deaths are more numerous, in proportion to the cases
                attached, than in the yellow fever—raged in the city, and in the neighborhood for
                many miles around. Both partook of an endemic character, and are probably more
                contagious than the yellow fever. Compared with the latter two, both are more
                tedious and far more painful. Yet the mere name of yellow fever seemed to be a spell
                to conjure up every thing dreadful and repulsive!</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Indeed what earthly matter is
                there where people show a more weak judgment, than in bodily illnesses and their
                relative danger and cure? We at the North have our <hi rend="italic">great</hi> malady in a variety of
                pulmonary forms, centering in the vampyre consumption. And while every body knows
                this well enough, yet the same habits (so favorable to a development of the disease)
                are pursued, the commonest precautions avoided, and the danger rushed into with the
                victim's eyes wide open! And still the immense steam of quackery rolls on, putting
                money in the purses of the pill, potion, and lotion manufacturers, and weakening the
                bodies and spirits of the deluded ones who trust their ills to these <hi rend="italic">specifics</hi>.
                Truly, as the sensible physician knows, there are hardly any specifics, properly so
                called, in medicine. No two cases, in any ailment, are exactly alike; because the
                circumstances, constitutions, and detailed habits, in all particulars and forms, of
                no two persons are the same. Yet the modest pill-makers sometimes give us a list of
                fifty diseases, in their nature wide as the poles asunder, for which their little
                globules are a "sure cure."</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We have had a taste—just the slightest taste in the
                world—of fall weather since my last. After a good hearty rain, the nights and
                mornings for the last three days have been cool enough for blankets. At the clothing
                stores along Maiden Lane, Park Row, and William and Fulton streets, (nor forgetting
                our Israelitish friends of Chatham street,) may already be seen all the varieties of
                cloaks, overcoats, and woolen garments, and here and there "<hi rend="italic">Summer goods selling off</hi>
                <hi rend="smallcaps">BELOW COST</hi>!" And the shops for tin and metal ware begin to lumber up the passages
                with stoves of all sorts, prices and sizes—"the Cook's comfort," "the People's
                choice," "the treasure for housekeepers," and others with the like attractive
                titles.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>No news, general or local, of any interest, have I to furnish you with
                to-day. Our military, a small portion of them, joined with those of Brooklyn two or
                three days ago, in rendering a military funeral to Lieut. Küne,<ptr target="n5001"/> killed in Mexico.
                This is probably the last ceremony of the sort that we will be called upon here to
                hold. Lieut. K. was buried in Greenwood Cemetery, that loveliest of Places of the
                Dead. I saw the procession return about 8 o'clock, music playing, and so forth;
                contrary to the usual practice, they played the most plaintive marches and held a
                solemn demeanor.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>It is not probable that Mr. Clay's<ptr target="med.00954_n8"/> letter, declining any
                countenance to the "enthusiastic whigs" of this city, in their separate movement for
                him, will have the effect of really calming the troubled waters. The <hi rend="italic">hearts</hi> of the
                whigs of this city, and most of this State, are devoted to Clay; the early support
                they give Gen. Taylor, is because the latter has received the regular nomination.
                Nor will disaffection burn less intensely because it makes no open show. The flames
                may be smothered, but they are there still. Party organs (on both sides) are not
                reliable, now, as to their statements; because, never before were the old landmarks
                so utterly broken up. You can tell where disaffection exists, but you can't tell
                where the disaffected will "go," or, indeed, whether they will vote for any body at
                all. This is a pretty state of things, isn't it?</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We have three candidates in the
                field, for Governor: Mr. Fish,<ptr target="med.00970_n1"/> for the Whigs—Chancellor Walworth,<ptr target="med.00970_n2"/> for the Democrats,
                and John A. Dix,<ptr target="med.00970_n3"/> for the Barnburners.<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> Dix is a man of great amiability and
                considerable talent; he will get a fair support, but is likely to run behind his
                ticket.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The stranger who perambulates around New York will be apt to notice the
                large number of new buildings in process of construction. Many of these,
                particularly up town, are of remarkable beauty and amplitude, all through, for
                private residences. The architectural taste of the New Yorkers has undergone a very
                happy improvement during the last ten years. Both here and in Brooklyn, the visiter
                will now behold many buildings of true proportion and noble appearance. There is, it
                is true, some room left for reformation. But that reformation will come, doubtless.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Howard's new hotel on Broadway, near Chambers street, attracts a good deal of
                attention and praise. The arrangements are indeed made on a grand scale, and the
                luxuries make one think of a palace; the furniture of some of the rooms is gorgeous
                beyond example. French's Hotel, corner of Chatham street and Frankfort—on the corner
                where the old groggeries and clo' shops used to cluster—(don't you recollect that
                middling-sized, spectacled Jew, with the tremendous hook nose, and the cap slouched
                down behind?)—French's new place is being enclosed. The workmen are up to the third
                story. It will be on the same plan as Tammany Hall, which lodging rooms, refectory,
                &amp;c.; a place where "the million" can enjoy all the comforts, and many luxuries, at
                half the expense of the Broadway houses.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>William street it building up from Chatham
                street where it now opens, inward; the rubbish is not yet cleared away, but when it
                is, the living current will pour in there mornings, and out evening, on a tall and
                plentiful scale. The widening and repaving of William street, has led, (how, I do
                not know,) to raising the grade of Frankfort street, and to the repaving of that
                ancient thoroughfare also. This, as you will readily imagine, has created a sort of
                subterraneanizing (there's a word for long breath!) of many of the old shad-ties in
                Frankfort street, which were not much higher than the former pavement. Of course the
                old tumble-downs must soon give place to more substantial places.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Thus the progress
                of improvement goes on. In a year or two, no doubt, they will cut a grand wide
                thoroughfare straight down from Broadway to Chatham street, eating into the heart of
                the Five Points, and lighting it up at night. That <hi rend="italic">will</hi> be an innovation, indeed!</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>