<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00973">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 29 September 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00973</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 29 September 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-09">9 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 29 September 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-09-29" xml:id="dat1">September 29, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-15" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-01-23" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-09-29"><handShift rend="printed"/>September 29, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>On Tuesday next, October 3d, the Fair of the American
                Institute (<hi rend="italic">exhibition</hi> of American manufacturers, is the proper phrase,) commences at
                Castle Garden. I stepped in yesterday afternoon, and made my way with difficulty
                through the vast confusion of articles that lie along the covered bridge, and the
                ample area inside. Time was when this exhibition produced good effects; but that
                time has gone by. Under the management of superannuated old men, wedded to the
                notions of the past, it is entirely behind time. This is a pity, too; because an
                institution of this sort is capable of doing much real benefit. It must strike
                higher though, than the aim of bringing together some large pumpkins, rich
                plum-cakes, and curiously patched bed-quilts.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>A new daily paper, to be called "The
                Drawing Room Journal," is on the eve of its appearance in this city; its editor is
                Mr. G. G. Foster.<ptr target="med.00973_n10"/> Book publishing languishes badly enough, about now. Harpers,
                Wiley, Putnam, Appleton, etc., now and then bring out a reprint; but all are waiting
                till after election before doing much in this way.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Towards sundown yesterday
                afternoon, Capt. Jas. Baker,<ptr target="med.00973_n2"/> of the ship Thomas H. Perkins, lying at one of our
                wharves, Narrowly escaped with his life from the hands of an infuriated mob, who
                seized him because he had shot and cut one of his crew, named Wm. Leonard. The
                latter was a sort of rival to the Captain, in the good graces of a female steerage
                passenger. He went, yesterday, in the cabin for his pay; was ordered out;
                altercation arose, and the Captain ran for a pistol and cutlass, and shot and cut
                Leonard so that his life is despaired of. A mob rapidly collected, and were so
                incensed that they dragged, cuffed, and bruised Baker pretty severely. The police
                came down in force, and, partly by stratagem, and partly by force, carried the
                Captain off to the Tombs, where he is at present locked up. The public mind here in
                New York is highly incensed, of late, against the cruelty of marine officers. There
                is a plentiful dash of Jacobianism among the "common people," which breaks out,
                sometimes a little too hastily perhaps, against those in authority. Jacobianism is
                far, far, far better though than the lethargic cowardice which will let a whole
                people stagnate in mean submission to any sort of tyranny.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>John S. Austin,<ptr target="med.00973_n4"/> well
                known as a prominent member of the Empire Club, was arrested last night, charged
                with the murder of a young man named Timothy Shea. The affair occurred in a low
                place in Leonard street.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Postmasters, Customhouse officers, and other United States
                officials, are being removed pretty extensively in this State; cause&#8212;adhesion
                to Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n2"/> instead of Cass<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/> and Butler.<ptr target="med.00952_n2"/> The 
                Customhouse and Naval office were
                closed yesterday, in respect to Mr. Hoffman,<ptr target="med.00972_n7"/> deceased.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>I confess plumply to have
                made a blunder in predicting the nomination of Walworth<ptr target="med.00970_n2"/> by the anti-renters. It
                appears that they have nominated John A. Dix,<ptr target="med.00970_n3"/> the Barnburner candidate 
                for Governor.<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/>
                This is somewhat remarkable, for Dix was understood to stand by Gov. Wright<ptr target="med.00971_n11"/> in his
                anti-rent measures.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Odd Fellows of this State seems to be getting up a little
                bit of a row among themselves. What it is about I must confess I do not exactly
                understand. The Lodges of the Oneida District have resolved not to submit to a
                certain important decision of the Grand Lodge of the United States. Very likely you
                know more about it than I do.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Greeley<ptr target="med.00972_n1"/> comes out in this morning's Tribune with the
                regular whig<ptr target="med.00961_n4"/> ticket flying at the head of his paper. His leader, attempting to
                fortify his course, is lame and impotent. Still, time remains for him to plaster the
                flaws up, pretty well, before the election. Undoubtedly these defections from the
                Free Soil<ptr target="med.00954_n6"/> ticket will reduce its vote considerably. The whigs hold a grand pow-wow
                at Vauxhall this evening, to clinch the "harmonizing" of the elements, and the
                return of the various prodigal sons. Leslie Coombs<ptr target="med.00973_n1"/> is to speak. Both whig and
                democratic (Cass) meetings, thus far, have had the worst speaking that has marked
                any political campaign within my remembrance. Every body acknowledges that the
                orators and the addresses are positively shocking.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body> 
    </text>
</TEI>
