<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00976">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 October 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00976</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 14 October 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-10-14">14 October 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 October 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-10-04" xml:id="dat1">October 4, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-02-15" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-11-21" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-10-04"><handShift rend="printed"/>October 4, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Blessed be the fine bright sunshine! Here, after three
                days of cold darkness and rain, we have at last a clear warm day again; proving,
                that what we get of the delightful, can only be truly enjoyed after a pretty long
                taste of the disagreeable. Although the rain poured down plentifully enough, on
                Monday night, the great concert, under the direction of Mr. Strakosch,<ptr target="med.00976_n1"/> 
                came off according to announcement, at the Tabarnacle. Never, in New York, was
                such a performance; never, such an audience. The great area was illuminated by
                hundreds of wax-lights, in addition to the gas. Four thousand people, the tip-top of
                the city, crowded themselves upstairs and down. A band of eighty instruments, each
                of the first class of performance, rendered some of the choicest musical productions
                ever composed.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The exhibition of the American Institute opened yesterday.
                Nobody there; it rained too hard. The articles are of the same old sort and variety.
                Hardly any thing new. Some of the Antiquarians hereabout are floating over a
                valuable MS. document, recently discovered, in Dutch, at the Hague, giving the
                earliest account of the New Netherlands. It has been sent hither to the New York
                Historical Society.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Irish Directory,<ptr target="med.00976_n3"/> (Messrs. O'Connor,
                Emmet,<ptr target="med.00976_n2"/> Greeley,<ptr target="med.00972_n1"/> J. W. White,
                T. Hayes,<ptr target="med.00976_n5"/> and M'Keon,<ptr target="med.00976_n4"/>) have issued
                another manifesto to the American people in general and the Irish in particular, on
                the subject of the funds in their, the Directory's hands. They talk independently
                and bluntly. Their motives are commendable; but the day of their cause is <hi rend="italic">past</hi>. We had all better let the question go by default.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Macready<ptr target="loc.03259_n4"/> appears to-night as
                Macbeth, at the Astor Place Theatre. Hamblin,<ptr target="med.00952_n6"/> at the Bowery, is
                another goodly ruin of an actor, who <hi rend="italic">will</hi> come forward and
                exhibit the mere shell of genius.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>You remember the case of Korth,<ptr target="med.00961_n3"/> mentioned
                in a former letter, arrested for an attempt to murder Mrs. Behm,<ptr target="med.00965_n2"/> at
                the corner of Johnson and Adams streets, Brooklyn. The trial came on yesterday. The
                case seems to be clear enough; here is Mrs. B's testimony:</p>
            <q>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"The prisoner often called at her husband's residence, and
                was on terms of friendship with him; on the evening of August 6, he called while she
                and her husband were at tea, and after some time said he would like a drink of
                water; her husband went to the pump, and while he was out Korth attacked her with a
                cane-sword and beat her with a whip until she was insensible."</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The Coroner testified that Mrs. Behm had three stabs on
                the neck and breast, besides cuts and stabs elsewhere, Mr. B. also swore to being
                attacked by North on returning from the pump, and so beaten and banged as to become
                insensible. Korth's counsel say that the blame of the attack lies on the other
                side.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The new naval officer, Mr. Bogardus,<ptr target="med.00973_n6"/> has
                made a clean sweep of all the Barnburners<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> in his establishment, and filled their
                places with Hunkers. Lawrence,<ptr target="n5001"/> the Collector, still sticks out. Some
                more changes in the head officers here and elsewhere at the North, are every way
                likely before a fortnight elapses.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Immense numbers of immigrants continue to pour in by the
                Liverpool, Havre, and Bremen packets. Two thousand arrived, one day last week. Let
                them come and welcome—the more the better. Let them, however, not remain in
                cities, but post westward forthwith, and vote themselves farms.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Some of the Protectionists and Paper Moneyists here are
                trying to resuscitate a little of the old malignance against R. J. Walker,<ptr target="med.00976_n6"/> low Tariff, and the Independent Treasury. Few pay any attention to
                them, however; if they provoke public notice, so as to bring on a contest,
                "Protection" will very likely lose the ground it already retains. Walker will stand
                higher in the history of these times, than any other man of the present
                administration: he deserves to, too.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>