<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00967">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 1 September 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00967</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 1 September 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-09-13">13 September 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The The Daily Crescent</hi>, 1 September 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-09-01" xml:id="dat1">September 1, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">updated notes for publication</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-08" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-11-11" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-09-01"><handShift rend="printed"/>1 September, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The arrival of the steamer Niagara last evening, confirmed
                the intelligence of a total triumph by the "bloody Government" of England, over the
                Irish patriots.<ptr target="loc.03571_n1d"/> Let others say what they may, I believe
                few will, at heart, differ from the following opinion:—that the masses in
                Ireland have none to blame so much as themselves. The <hi rend="italic">determination</hi> to achieve their freedom and rights, would effect that
                result. They have been tried in the balance and found wanting. Their most
                noble-hearted and devoted young leaders—men of as chivalrous courage and pure
                patriotism as ever warmed the human breast—have been caught and handcuffed by
                the minions of English tyranny, in the midst of the people, who ought to have laid
                down their lives before letting those brave spirits be thus imprisoned and outraged.
                What another few years may bring forth, we can only see as the time elapses; but for
                the present, I am free to confess, for one, I have lost my enthusiasm for the Irish
                people. They are to be pitied, for their sufferings, no doubt; but after craven
                conduct like that of the past month, our pity will hardly fail of borrowing a tinge
                of contempt. For a noble people, oppressed but dauntless, we utter our warmest
                sympathies; nor will America ever be backward in tokens of more substantial aid,
                when it can reach them. But for a people three times in number what our forefathers
                were when the latter defied the proudest earthly power, and <hi rend="italic">defeated</hi> it too—for a people, oppressed beyond all conquered
                communities that history ever mentioned, to <hi rend="italic">flunk</hi> at the
                vital hour when resolution and action would have overthrown their loathed
                tyrants—I openly confess I sicken of such conduct, and think it but right to
                apply fiercely the terms it surely deserves. As to the Irish not being "united,"
                little excuse is there in that. The Americans were not "united" either, in '76;
                wealth and influential tories were numerous; but the <hi rend="italic">party of
                    independence had determination and</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">COURAGE</hi> and would to a man, or women
                either, have fought against any odds, and died fighting before deserting the meanest
                of their leaders. "Who would be free, themselves must strike the blow;"<ptr target="med.00967_n2"/> and until they show the hearts and the hands to do it,
                let them never ask for assistance from abroad.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The isle of New York is somewhat frighted from its
                propriety, just now, by the advent of Yellow Jack,<ptr target="med.00953_n4"/> who
                has appeared in force at the Quarantine station five miles below the city, on Staten
                Island; and has, indeed, sought some victims in the neighboring villages of that
                lovely spot. The weather is bad for the fever—being very hot, stifling, and
                dry. The heat has caused a considerable emigration of city people again to country
                place near by.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Half the town is annoyed by the odor caused by the burnt
                gas-works—which, by the by, have removed already to better and more
                appropriate quarters, up on 21st street.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/>Yours,  &amp;c.,</salute>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>