<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00950">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Daily Crescent</hi>, 13 July 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00950</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address> 
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>   
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc> 
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahatta</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The
                            Daily Crescent</hi>, 13 July 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-07-24">24 July 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl> 
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The
                        Daily Crescent</hi>, 13 July 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-07-13" xml:id="dat1">July 13, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc> 
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-02" who="#aja">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2022-10-03" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-16" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body> 
            <opener> 
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-07-13">July 13, 1848.</date>
                </dateline> 
                <salute><hi rend="italic">Eds.
                    Crescent</hi>&#8212;</salute> 
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"Barnburner" and "Hunker,"<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/>&#8212;Taylor,<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/> 
                Cass<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/> and Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/>&#8212;"What are Taylor's principles?"&#8212;"Is there no way to
                compromise?"&#8212;Tammany Hall in a Pandemoniac state&#8212;the Tribune corner a
                focus for all sorts of loud words and excitement&#8212;a huge crowd around the Globe
                bulletin-board&#8212;dust flying in the Park&#8212;men whose names are known from
                one corner of the land to the other walking unnoticed along the walk, and across
                from the great gates, to the Nassau street side-walk&#8212;the cracked tones of the
                man with "leg of mutton candy," now and then piercing through the din&#8212;a mighty
                and never-ceasing tide of humanity rolling along from day-dawn till midnight, a
                majority of whose members would not stop two minutes to look at Queen Victoria,<ptr target="med.00989_n12"/> or
                even a street assassination;&#8212;there you have, in disjointed sentences, and some
                words that are heard in every part of the neighborhood every five minutes, a picture
                of current "life" as developed in that part of New York where Nassau street pokes
                its nose out to the Park, at the south end of City Hall. A calculation was made
                sometime since, by a curious boarder at Tammany, of how many persons passed and
                repassed there in the course of the day. Somewhere about forty or forty-five
                thousand, I believe, was the number, estimated from actual counting at several
                periods of several days! In the morning come tripping along hundreds and hundreds of
                girls from fourteen to twenty-five years old, many of them really beautiful, and
                all, with a rare exception here and there, neat and healthy looking; they are
                employed in book-binding, umbrella, lace, and other establishments, and their wages
                range from two to six dollars per week. It is astonishing what a vein of
                intelligence&#8212;one may say refinement&#8212;is perceptible in these young women;
                no other city on earth, not even Paris, where grace is the female's birthright, can
                equal them. Besides these girls, there are innumerable swarms of mechanics and other
                workmen, porters, store-boys with their big brass keys, etc. An hour or two later,
                the complexion of the crowd is a little changed. There is a great quantity of better
                broadcloth, less worn and less dusty; but, in general, the wearers are not so comely
                as the more hard-working folk of the earlier morning. The merchants and
                store-keepers&#8212;the head clerks, editors, late risers, lawyers,
                traders&#8212;make up the volume of the stream. Still a little later, and all during
                the middle of the day, it continues to be of the most ample and heterogeneous
                materials. If you are fond of studying "character," here is your chance; here you
                have it in all its varieties, each variety presenting itself in all its different
                forms. Important news is generally known here, the first place of all the town. In
                times of political elections, when returns are due from distant States, or from
                quarters of New York itself more important even than some States, here you may see
                packed in a dense body, sometimes filling up the whole of the immense area,
                thousands and tens of thousands of that majestic animal "the People," waiting to
                hear "who's elected." <choice><sic>Nothimg</sic><corr>Nothing</corr></choice> else on God's wide and beautiful earth, would
                stop them one tithe as long from their regular avocations.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Of late years, nearly all the big meetings&#8212;the "mass
                meetings" of the people&#8212;have been called in the Park, just nigh the quarter
                described in the foregoing lines; and it has been found that the best time to call
                these meetings is 6 o'clock in the evening. By the time the business of getting
                under weigh is through with, the "masses," who stop work at 6 o'clock, are on their
                way home in myriads. Rarely do they fail&#8212;those who come from down town, on
                their course up to the immense section above Chatham Square (all our triangular
                pieces of land here are called "squares")&#8212;to stop and tarry awhile at these
                meetings. Working men thus lose no time, and if the speakers make out a good
                argument, and show a fair cause, they seldom fail of creating an impression on the
                minds of hundreds of their auditors; for, after all, the body of the "common
                people," away from the corrupting influence of politicians, are anxious to do right,
                on principle. Perhaps there is no completer or more convincing evidence of the
                superiority of the political fabric of this country, over any other that has yet
                existed on earth, than one of these Park meetings&#8212;where, of late years, it is
                no uncommon thing to see from twenty to thirty thousand people assembled. It is n't
                considered any thing at all unless the attendance numbers six or eight thousand. The
                moment the audience gets too large to be conveniently talked to by a couple of
                speakers, (one on each end of a large stage,) up go other stages with the rapidity
                of magic. If these all get enveloped with hearers, and more "accommodation" is
                wanted yet, the steps of the Hall of records, the jutting stones at the top of the
                basement windows of the City Hall, a neighboring hogshead or barrel, any thing
                handy, is put to the uses of a standing place, where the multitude can come nigh and
                be talked to. All the various branches of a great question are sometimes discussed,
                in full blast, at the same moment, by twenty different voices. Invariably there is a
                German and a French speaker at some of these stands&#8212;sometimes others, of other
                languages, particularly Italian and Spanish. As the evening advances, the talkers
                and listeners both grow more impassioned&#8212;the first bringing forward their
                stoutest points and most eloquent appeals, and the others responding with such
                shouts as make one feel how grand is the voice a human myriad! A few lights are
                brought to each stand, but they seem only as a drop in the ocean&#8212;you can do
                nothing but <hi rend="italic">hear</hi>; and the excited voices, the flickering and darkness, and the
                impressible multitude around, make up a strangely picturesque scene.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANAHATTA</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>   
    </text> 
</TEI> 
