<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00515">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Rudolf Schmidt to Walt Whitman, 18 August 1875</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Rudolf Schmidt</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName> 
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any 
                        medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital 
                        Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners 
                        of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00515</idno></publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Horace Traubel</author>
                        <editor>Sculley Bradley</editor>
                        <title xml:id="traubel">With Walt Whitman in Camden</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                            <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                            <biblScope unit="page">336–338</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Rudolf Schmidt</author>
                    <title>Rudolf Schmidt to Walt Whitman, 18 August 1875</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1875-08-18" xml:id="dat1">August 18, 1875</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">Transcription derived from Traubel; the location of the original manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Schmidt, Rudolf" ref="n3070">Rudolf Schmidt</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-08" who="#smb">final check, updated</change>
            <change when="2023-07-10" who="#aja">final corrections for Ed</change>
            <change when="2023-05-12" who="#aja">updated notes</change>
            <change when="2022-11-30" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-04-03" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-12-14" who="#aja">checked, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-30">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2013-02-07" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-29" who="#js">checked (without images)</change>
            <change when="2012-02-29" who="#al">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2012-02-09" who="#km">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Copenhagen,</name>
                    <date when="1875-08-18">August 18, 1875</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>I have indeed been extremely sorry to hear firstly from the transmitted paper of 
                July 23 and then from your kind letter of July 31,<ptr target="med.00515_n1"/> 
                that your prospects of recovering your health seem to have darkened forever.<ptr target="loc.03649_n3"/> You 
                are no old man, and I had always hoped that your giant frame at last should supersede 
                the lurking enemy. Even yet I won't give up hope. That you don't give up your 
                literary activity is to me a good token!</p>

            <p>From Kristian Elster<ptr target="n0216"/> I have not heard myself in a very long 
                time, and I don't wonder that he has not written to you. He is a true virginal 
                nature with the shyness of a virgin. As he was nearly suffocated by the dullness 
                and coarse materialism of the Norwegian Society,<ptr target="n0447"/> I pressed 
                him for two years ago (when he had previously sent me some very fine articles 
                for my periodical)<ptr target="n0239"/> to come for some months to Copenhagen. 
                I introduced [him] to some of the leading literary men and in some rich families, 
                but he did not come to them and I myself must fetch him in his lodging, when 
                I would see him. It seemed to him to be an intrusion to pay a visit, when not 
                expressly asked to come! This is the fruit of a lonely education in stern and 
                harsh national surroundings The Norsemen can be described in the shy ones and 
                the impudent ones. Björnson<ptr target="loc.01711_n6"/> and Ole Bull<ptr target="n0455"/> 
                are of the last sort, Elster of the first. The meanest sort—as usual—has 
                first produced <hi rend="italic">its</hi> gifted men: when the better sort in 
                its time has sprung into flowers, they shall all be forgotten. Then as truly as 
                Denmark is at this moment doing the principal part of the intellectual work of 
                the Scandinavian race, its accomplishment is kept back for Norway.</p>

            <p>The intellectual work of the Scandinavian race! What a humiliating thought to us 
                Danes, that Hans Christian Andersen<ptr target="n0039"/> shall be nearly our only 
                <choice><sic>representant</sic><corr>representative</corr></choice> to the world. 
                There are men in Denmark of such an intellectual greatness that Andersen was not 
                reaching to their knees. The world did to his last days take the selfish old man 
                for a child; the spirit of the Danish people is <hi rend="italic">no</hi> child; 
                it [is] a warrior with the sword in his hand bleeding from combats, when he fought 
                one against seven, with great thoughts of his brow and stern resolution in his 
                eyes! At last Andersen lived only among our rich Jewish families, who endured all 
                his whims and harshness, hoping to be gilt by his fame. He was buried as he had 
                lived. The King and the Crown Prince<ptr target="med.00515_n2"/> were in the church, 
                reporters for foreign papers, also from America, swarmed everywhere; but there 
                was no wet eye in the whole assembly.</p>  

            <p>But our time shall come! Most probably America, in the next century, shall be the 
                vanguard of humanity, its greatest leading power. But <hi rend="italic">your</hi> 
                eyes will not be open to see the outlines filled your bold hand has drawn. As 
                <choice><sic>representants</sic><corr>representatives</corr></choice> for mental 
                power and intellectual vigor such people as Bret Harte<ptr target="med.00515_n4"/> 
                and Mark Twain<ptr target="ucb.00961_n2"/> are fainting away into ridiculousness. 
                <hi rend="italic">Ours</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">next</hi> future. You have 
                no idea of the intellectual decay that in Germany is accompanying the political 
                grandeur of the country. In June I met with professors and teachers of the 
                university who in all earnest were Buddhists, believers of nothings, or properly 
                spoken, believing that <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> is the true reality of the 
                existence of world and man. <hi rend="italic">This</hi> is the dark and black gulf 
                that Goethe<ptr target="n0270"/> and Schiller<ptr target="med.00515_n3"/> decked 
                with the flowers and branches of their genius. At present the flowers and foliage 
                are fading, and the black fathomless abyss of despair opens its giant yawn to the 
                horrified mind. The faith, the youth, the hope, the vigor of spirits, the soaring 
                flight of lofty aspiration, is only to be found in Scandinavia. Martin Luther<ptr target="n0371"/> 
                spoke the prophetic word: in the north is a place of refuge! The day of the 
                fulfillment is near.<ptr target="med.00515_n5"/></p>

            <p>I have never doubted that I could make myself understood to you, and a letter 
                of business or concerning the usual affairs of human life I could most probably 
                write without faults at all, when I did take pains with it. But all the striking 
                expressions, all the elaborate work of the thought, is fading away beneath my 
                feather, when treating more difficult matters in English. I am never saying exactly 
                what I would say, and you know, my dear friend, that this is a great pain to anyone 
                who is accustomed to clothe his thoughts in the garment of language. I shall be 
                glad to receive your new books. A Danish philosopher defines a hero as a man who 
                is holding on the possible against probability.</p>

            <closer>
                <salute>Hoping amelioration of your health <hi rend="italic">against</hi> probability I am yours</salute>
                <signed>Rudolf Schmidt</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>