<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00988">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 20 December 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00988</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 20 December 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-12-30">30 December 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[1]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 20 December 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-12-20" xml:id="dat1">December 20, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc> 
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-12" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-12-20"><handShift rend="printed"/>December 20.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Messrs.
                    Editors</hi>&#8212;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Let me paraphrase the first line of one of Bryant's<ptr target="n6116"/>
                poems, and say,</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"The dissipating days have come, the jolliest of the year," for
                that's a fact, as far as New York is concerned, and I rather suspect it equally true
                of the dashy capital of the great Southwest. If you want to see how many balls are
                "set in motion," hereabout, just examine the third page of any of the popular Sunday
                papers; for it is a singular truth that all the dancing sprees, and theatrical
                entertainments, advertise in the Sunday press. Likewise it is a known fact that,
                among the Emeralders, (and I don't state the fact as discreditable, either,) when
                they get up a ball for benevolent purposes, the invitations and tickets are
                distributed round <hi rend="italic">at Church</hi> of a Sabbath morning. We have no very splendid ball-room
                in New York. We have Tammany Hall, to be sure, and the large saloon of the Astor
                House, and the New York Hotel; but there is no really sumptuous and extensive place,
                on a scale commensurate with the wants of <hi rend="italic">the</hi> city of America. It always seemed to
                me that the Broadway Tabernacle would make a noble ball-room.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Several benefits are
                already under way for the persons thrown out of employment by the destruction of the
                Park Theatre. Of course, every body is willing to assist in so good a work. By the
                way, I made a little mistake in my reckoning of the <choice><sic>nett</sic><corr>net</corr></choice> profits of the Simpson<ptr target="med.00958_n2"/>
                benefit; Mr. Simpson's family will receive (have received, probably,) &#36;4000, from
                the Theatre, and about &#36;500 from other sources. This is quite well.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Ah, but you
                Southerners should have just seen what weather New York has been blessed with, the
                last two days! Not spring in her warmth, not autumn in his blandness, ever outdid
                it! The old man, the young child, the invalid, all who could get out, were enjoying
                it. Unfortunately, however, the delicious time only lasted long enough to make us
                feel how good it was&#8212;and then left us. This morning the raw, chill air, and murky
                clouds overhead, are by no means pleasant.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Nothing of progress has been accomplished
                in the way of a Washington Monument; and my private impression is that the scheme
                will fall through&#8212;which I shan't be sorry to see; for no monument the present folks
                are likely build will one tithe come up to a proper monument to Washington. Let them
                build such mementos to the common heroes; our great exemplar needs none. One of the
                late propositions is to construct an arch over some upper part of Broadway, and put
                a colossal statue upon it....The late editor of the New York Globe, Mr. A. Ingraham,<ptr target="med.00988_n3"/>
                has retired from that station, and will now conduct a large radical Weekly, "The
                American Statesman."....Marietta Smith,<ptr target="med.00988_n4"/> since her return to New York, has been quite
                a lioness. She can hardly go out in the street, without attracting public attention
                to an annoying extent.....Yesterday the health officers reported two new cases of
                cholera,<ptr target="med.00989_n5"/> and two deaths; the previous day five cases. For the last week, no cases
                have occurred in the city.</p>  
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>I went in, the other day, to see Delaroche's<ptr target="med.00988_n5"/> painting of
                Napoleon<ptr target="med.00988_n6"/> crossing the Alps. It is grand! Never was the sublimity of nature better
                depicted, in all simplicity, by art! You know the ordinary engravings (from former
                paintings) represent Napoleon on a fiery house, the said horse twirling around on
                his hind legs, and standing almost perpendicularly&#8212;while the great conqueror, with a
                drawn sword, points his toiling soldiers onward&#8212;his cloak, drapery, in the meantime,
                floating with a lightness and looseness very convenient to make a showy painting,
                but rather chilly for the winter snows of the mountain. Well, in this painting, he
                is on a mule, well wadded with clothing, and guided by an old muleteer. I stood an
                hour and gazed on that picture; and if I were to attempt describing the feelings
                that passed through my mind then, every body would laugh at me.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Hundreds of sloops,
                steamboats, and barges, are busily engaged now, bringing produce down the river,
                anticipative of the ice that must soon close the passage up above...Fires, many of
                them undoubtedly incendiary, still continue to vex the public peace. Hardly a night
                passes without one or more....The musical furor has somewhat subsided&#8212;nearly all the
                German bands having departed for other cities. The opera, it seems, is doing
                remarkably well, this season; although the Herald continues its spiteful attacks,
                (because Mr. Fry<ptr target="med.00988_n7"/> will neither give Mr. Bennett<ptr target="loc.01086_n6"/> the printing nor a free ticket!)...No
                cessation, but rather an increase, is developed by each succeeding day, to the gold
                fever. You may see by looking at the shipping advertisements of our morning papers,
                what a rush there is. The knowing ones are all going round Cape Horn. A gentleman is
                in town who has had to return from Chagres, because he couldn't get across Panama,
                on account of the crowd.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Business is brisk enough now, in view of the approaching
                holydays. The retail shops make a great show of goods, and the shopkeepers seem to
                be in an especially good humor. The jobbers have had a profitable fall trade, and
                still keep up a lingering of custom; and the importers are all smiles, because they
                too have "done well." Every body is expecting, somehow, to get a dip into those
                cargoes of California gold.<ptr target="med.00984_n10"/> Well, I hope they won't be disappointed.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>   
    </text> 
</TEI> 
