<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00987">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 19 December 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00987</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 19 December 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-12-29">29 December 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[1]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 19 December 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-12-19" xml:id="dat1">December 19, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-12" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-12-19"><handShift rend="printed"/>Dec. 19th, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute><handShift rend="printed"/><hi rend="italic">Eds.
                    Crescent</hi>&#8212;</salute>
            </opener> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Imagine the highest state of excitement you ever saw in
                this city "on the eve of an important electtion," then multiply it by three, and you
                may realize some-thing of the California gold excitement<ptr target="med.00984_n10"/> now pervading nearly all
                classes of our "society." Since the publication of the documents accompanying the
                President's message, the flames have spread with tremendous intenseness, and to a
                very wide extent. Perhaps it is safe to say that at least <hi rend="italic">one-third</hi> of the mechanics
                and young working-men are <hi rend="italic">trying</hi> to go to California. Of course many will be unable
                to get the requisite means; for two or three hundreds dollars in ready cash is not
                as common as "common people" are themselves. Of this one-third however, a very large
                proportion will probably succeed, through dint of borrowing, begging, selling off,
                (many times at a sacrifice,) or even by more questionable means; for it has been
                discovered, in more than a few cases, that the California fever blinds some of its
                victims to the laws of strict honesty.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Gold! gold! how thou are worshipped by the
                human "critter"! What will not man undergo to clutch thee! And yet how truly have
                poets sung and philosophers said, since the world began, that thou art unable to
                make a man really happy! Still, a few drops of thee&#8212;say about a hundred and twenty
                five pounds, Troy weight, (as it is best to be specified,)&#8212;wouldn't come amiss to
                one who scribbles for his bread and butter. The pen may be mightier than the sword;
                but, candidly and without clap-trap, gold is a <hi rend="italic">guid</hi> bit stronger than both pen and
                sword. Proof: the two latter a thousand times doubled, couldn't draw folks half so
                fast toward those distant shores of the Pacific, as the sight of a few shining
                little lumps that went off the other day to the Philadelphia Mint. But I dare say
                you see the same thing exemplified, in pretty nearly the same way, in New Orleans.
                Human nature is just the same ("with a difference") all over the world. It is the
                same, <hi rend="italic">without</hi> the difference, in respect to greediness for the aforesaid gold.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Thus
                far, the session of Congress has produced no sensation. Some significant moves, it
                is true, have been made in the House of Representatives; but it rarely happens that
                the Congress which sits immediately before the advent of a new Administration takes
                very important steps. We here think not much of the doings at Washington. We
                exhausted all our available sympathies during the two months preceding the election,
                and look on politics for a while yet with apathy.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Still does the cholera<ptr target="med.00989_n5"/> linger at
                Staten Island, like some bore of a visiter&#8212;such <hi rend="italic">as will</hi> come at times even into the
                editorial holy of holies. It lingers, and will not be gone, although sixty-five
                doctors have been down to see it. After this, no one knows what it will be able to
                stand, perhaps even the severest of frosts.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The destruction of the Park Theatre on
                Saturday night, still remains unaccounted for, as to the origin of the fire. Do you
                know there has long been a standing tradition that a deadly enemy of Hamblin<ptr target="med.00952_n6"/> has
                pursued him for years, moved thereto by a fiendish oath to incendiarize every
                theatre the said Hamblin shall control. The insurance offices ought to offer a
                reward for that chap, as he does <hi rend="italic">them</hi> more harm than he does "the old man." My
                impression is clearly that Hamblin's insurance will cover his losses&#8212;though the
                papers state the contrary.</p> 
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>  
            </closer>
        </body>  
    </text>  
</TEI>
