<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="med.00985">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 25 November 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00985</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 25 November 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-12-06">6 December 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 25 November 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-11-25" xml:id="dat1">November 25, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-04-15" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-16" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-12-09" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>New York,</name>
                    <date when="1848-11-25"><handShift rend="printed"/>Saturday Night,</date>
                    <date when="1848-11-25"><handShift rend="printed"/>Nov. 25.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>A most savage feeling is beginning to pervade the
                public mind in New-York, towards the infernal class of villains who commit the
                incendiarisms which for the past three months have been laying waste so much
                property, as well as human hope and comfort, here and in Brooklyn. The destruction
                of Murphy's large stables<ptr target="med.00954_n11"/> last Sunday morning, contributes to intensify this wrath.
                Woe be to the first of these incendiaries who shall be caught! I should not be much
                surprised if a dash of Lynch law were to come in play, then, unless the police
                muster strong.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>You will notice by the papers that Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n11"/> runs considerably ahead
                of Cass,<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/> in this State. The Free Soilers<ptr target="med.00954_n6"/> say that large numbers of their men voted
                for Taylor,<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/> with the determination of defeating Cass at any rate. Probably this is
                so; but then some of the dissatisfied Whigs<ptr target="med.00961_n4"/> voted for Van Buren. All that the
                Michiganian received in this State is attributable to the strong attachment of the
                Democrats to "regular nominations." But here I am babbling of politics&#8212;without any
                need.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The other night, Mr. Fillmore,<ptr target="med.00989_n4"/> the Vice President elect, (you know he was
                defeated in '44, when he ran against Silas Wright,<ptr target="med.00971_n11"/> for Governor,) had a
                complimentary dinner given him at the Irving House. Many celebrities and jovial
                folks were there. But Fillmore isn't over-popular even among the Whigs. He is
                generally understood as belonging to the Courier and Express side, in opposition to
                the Tribune side. O, Lord, how those "sides" do hate each other!</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Much learned debate
                is held in certain quarters, especially among the medical and municipal
                functionaries, about the probable approach of the Cholera.<ptr target="med.00989_n5"/> It seems to be the
                general opinion that we have got to take it. If so, the sooner it comes, the better.
                It is queer to see the antics "some people" cut up, at the mention of the cholera.
                Consumption,<ptr target="med.00964_n3"/> dysentery,<ptr target="med.00964_n2"/> and inflammatory attacks all around us, are ten times worse
                than the cholera, but you can't make the people think so. Isn't there something in
                "a name?" Something? Why, the whole civilized world is governed by <hi rend="italic">names</hi>.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>About 11
                o'clock this morning, your humble servant went to take a stroll in Broadway. Never
                did the gay thoroughfare look more lovely! Never did the sun shine more gladsomely,
                or the air feel balmier, or the women look sweeter! True, there was a <hi rend="italic">little</hi> mud&#8212;and
                if one didn't take good care, he received awkward splashes of the same; but "what
                can't be cured, must be endured," and mud in New York must be endured, most
                emphatically. (This is a kind of "Free Soil" doctrine, however, that all people
                won't agree with.)</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>On the <hi rend="italic">other</hi> corner of Rector street, (Trinity Church,<ptr target="med.00989_n7"/> you know,
                fills the upper side,) they are putting up a large brick and marble structure, whose
                depth and recesses, as you stand in Broadway and look at them, make one think of
                those endless perspective halls that the "flats" on the stage sometimes represent.
                The walls of Grace Church&#8212;delightful, musical Grace, where Malibran<ptr target="med.00971_n12"/> used to sing in
                the choir, and which always was celebrated for its singing&#8212;the old walls that stood
                threateningly for two years, have been pushed and pulled down;&#8212;and here goes up this
                flaunting, measureless hall. What it's for, nobody yet knows.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>New York is unusually
                full of stray visiters. A score or two of miscellaneous thousands make no great
                difference, of course; but a few hundreds, who dress well&#8212;only a little different
                from "<hi rend="italic">the</hi> touch"&#8212;and who go about seeing sights, form an item that people are not
                sorry to behold. They add to trade, for one thing; and do the office of "lookers on
                in"&#8212;New York. What good were all the fine things of the metropolis, if people didn't
                come and admire them?</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
