<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00954">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>  
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 21 July 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00954</idno></publicationStmt> 
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manhattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 21 July 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-02">2 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct> 
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 21 July 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-07-21" xml:id="dat1">July 21, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>   
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc> 
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">edited notes</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-03" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-10-21" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-07-21"><handShift rend="printed"/>July 21, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Quite a neat and appropriate way of testifying the
                public gratitude to our New York Volunteers, returned from the Mexican war, has been
                carried out in this city. The Corporation have had nearly four hundred large silver
                medals, struck from an appropriate design, and have given one to each of the
                Volunteers. The medals, themselves, are very beautiful, and their intrinsic value is
                about seven dollars a piece. On one side are the words—"<hi rend="italic">Corro Gordo, Chapultepec,
                Cherubusco, Vera Cruz</hi>." And on the other—"Presented by the City of New York to the
                Volunteers of the 1st New York Regiment in Mexico."</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The first-mentioned side has
                also a device of the Genius of Liberty, with a bundle of arrows, pointing to the
                Halls of the Montezumas. The other has the arms of New York. Take it altogether,
                this is a very liberal and well-arranged testimonial, and reflects honor on "him
                that gives and him that takes." Each Volunteer, it is to be hoped, will preserve his
                gift, and transmit it as an heir loom. Of course, the <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>, too, are not forgotten.
                <hi rend="italic">Their</hi> medals will be preserved as sacred indeed.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We are expecting the steamer
                Crescent City here by tomorrow, or the next day, at farthest. She brings us, I see
                by the telegraphic dispatch announcing her departure, a big lot of the ready
                rhino—an article much needed hereabouts. In every point of view, the establishment
                of a line of steamers, each equal to the Crescent City, would be prodigiously
                advantageous to New York, Havana and New Orleans, all and each of them.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Every body
                here is quite disgusted with the Congress of the United States and their dawdling,
                long-drawn-out style of legislation, or rather their no legislation. What good are
                they doing at Washington? What need is there that they should stay there ten days
                longer? Indeed, if they had possessed ordinary application and industry, two months
                ago would have seen them adjourned. The plain truth is, that nearly all of them—and
                one party is just as bad as another—are busy (at the people's expense)
                electioneering and President making. The people, it seems, are not capable of
                managing this matter for themselves, and must have their "public servants" do it for
                them. Indeed, this impertinence on the part of Hon. Senators and Representatives, is
                getting to be quite unbearable. In olden times, even, when the people (at least we
                moderns say so) were not half so intelligent and well-informed as now, such
                interference wouldn't have been permitted at all; it wouldn't have been permitted,
                however, in the days of Washington, Adams and Jefferson. Politicians think
                altogether too much of themselves and their influence. As a body, they are very
                corrupt and selfish, thinking more of "spoils" than any thing else. Gloomy would it
                be for this Republic, were there not an immense body of <hi rend="italic">middlemen</hi>, uninterested in
                politics any further than to do right, or to have right done, who control political
                action. At Washington, now, nearly every member of both houses is engaged in this
                abominable game of injuring certain parties, or benefitting others—<hi rend="italic">parties</hi>, as such,
                and not connected with any national question or political measure, in which any
                human being—except politicians—is interested! It is equally true, I hope, that the
                masses of the people, are beyond the effect of these improper influences.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Evening
                before last the performances at the Chatham theatre were for the benefit of Messrs.
                Kipp &amp; Brown,<ptr target="med.00954_n7"/> who met with such a sweeping loss a couple of months since. The house
                was well filled, and the benefit must have been a substantial one. The pieces were
                light and lively. The Chatham, by the way, is making money at no small rate, though
                its <hi rend="italic">prices</hi> are on the small rate.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>If you remember much about New York, in the way of
                what places are, and what places are not "genteel," you know that the Park, around
                the City Hall, has for years past been in the latter category. Fashion, however, is
                proverbially whimsical, and, this summer, the ban has been taken off. From sundown
                to 9 o'clock, it is decided to be unexceptionable as a promenade. Though surrounded
                with the loudest sort of clatter, it certainly is one of the most agreeable places
                in its quarter of the city for a promenade, especially considering the fountain.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>"Among the peculiar "features" of these times in New York, is the fact that more
                than half the houses and lots of the city, and of Brooklyn, Williamsburg, and the
                other suburban places, are for sale. The same may be said of the farming places
                within 60 or 100 miles of the city. We are a migratory people, that's a fact—every
                body wants to be moving—it makes no difference where, if they only move. With all
                the confusion, however, in trades, sales, etc., there seems to be very little
                evidence of real property—that is, comparatively, little, in our city. Folks appear
                gay and hearty enough, which is the true philosophy.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>  
    </text>  
</TEI>