<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00968">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 September 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00968</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 September 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-09-14">14 September 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 4 September 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-09-04" xml:id="dat1">September 4, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">updated notes for publication</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-08" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-11-11" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc> 
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-09-04"><handShift rend="printed"/>4 September.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Many of the high officers of Government are at present
                sojourning among us; three of the President's Cabinet are here, and it is expected
                that the President<ptr target="med.00968_n2"/> himself will arrive in the course of a week. By good rights New
                York should be the proper place for all these functionaries to reside, in their
                official capacity. It is, in reality more central than Washington, and every way
                more convenient. A <hi rend="italic">second</hi> rate city is liable to objections, as the seat of
                Government; but a large and <hi rend="italic">first class</hi> city is not—indeed it is the proper place.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Main street, Brooklyn, was the scene of a disastrous conflagration this morning.
                Fifteen houses were burnt—several of them used as stores. Much personal property was
                destroyed, besides; and the loss can hardly have been less than $50,000.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>There is a
                "grand mass meeting" of the Free Soilers<ptr target="med.00954_n6"/> at Abingdon Square, this evening. John Van
                Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n3"/> is to hold forth. So it seems he has had to take his coat off again, and mount
                the platform.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Thus far the yellow fever<ptr target="med.00953_n4b"/> has not made its appearance, if the
                physicians can be believed, in New York, although existing for a fortnight past at
                Staten Island. Intercourse is debarred between the city and Quarantine. The occasion
                is seized to try the virtues of a new and powerful disenfectant, prepared by a
                gentleman engaged in an office in the Navy Department here. Certain medical
                personages speak of it as remarkably superior to "any thing out"—as better than
                chlorine, and not at all injurious to the lungs. "Forewarned, forearmed," is the
                motto that ought to keep off contagious diseases. We shall see how it acts in this
                case. I find it altogether impossible to convince folks that the yellow fever is not
                contagious, like small pox. Should we get the malady prevalent, some of your New
                Orleans doctors would come very acceptable here. I believe you have some of the best
                in the world. By the way, how comes on your University? Don't let the New Orleanois
                be discouraged at any difficulties in the way of establishing a school so worthy
                their great city, and so necessary in the South-west.</p> 
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We don't hear any thing more
                of that "Buffalo Hunt on the Rio Grande."<ptr target="med.00968_n3"/> Is it given up? A thousand adventurous
                spirits here hope not. The President, it is true, per the Washington Union, talks
                dignifiedly about observing our "obligations of treaties toward Mexico." Well, let
                him—as far as concerns him. But if there be a real disposition, in earnest, to go on
                this hunt, and three thousand tough fellows could be got together for the purpose,
                with American officers, I should say, "go it;" and it seems difficult to imagine how
                Mr. Polk could stop 'em. However, there may be something about the move, which you
                in New Orleans understand better than we do here. One thing there can be no mistake
                about; that the timid, malignant, idle and shiftless Mexican population south of us,
                <hi rend="italic">must</hi> give way, sooner or later, to Anglo-Saxon energy and selfishness—for we have
                about as much of the last as the first.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The weather here is hot—no rain for a long
                time—gutters abominable—omnibus horses sad and drooping—butter dear and
                scarce—politics waxing fiercer and fiercer—decapitations of office-holding
                Barnburners<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> begun, and doubtless to be continued actively.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer> 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>