<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00824">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 14 April
                    1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schöberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00824</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>Horace Traubel</editor>
                        <title xml:id="ht">With Walt Whitman in Camden (1906–1998)</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                            <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            <biblScope type="page">497–499</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 14 April 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-04-14" xml:id="dat1">April 14, 1888</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of this manuscript is unknown.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-07-27" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-06-19" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-06-13" who="#if">added notes</change>
            <change when="2016-06-03" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-12-07" who="#aa">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Washington D.C.,</name>
                    <date when="1887-04-14">April 14, 1888.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>  
            </opener>
            <p>All echoes are delightful, especially such as this one: I was sitting at breakfast
                yesterday morning, when the lines came into my head which someone has written of
                Milton:</p>
            <p><lg>
                    <l>"Chief of organic numbers,</l>  
                <l>Old poet of the spheres—"<ptr target="med.00824_n2"/></l>
                </lg></p>
            <p>And I thought how much more applicable they were to you than to Milton. Just then the
                postman rang and left me your letter of the 12th!<ptr target="med.00824_n1"/> This
                may have been an Irish echo, but all the same an echo.</p>
            <p>I was very glad to hear from you. I have been longing to send you a word, but you
                can't imagine how hard it is for me to rouse myself to write, in my condition of
                lameness and lethargy. I have lately been undergoing <hi rend="italic">massage</hi>,
                and it certainly was doing me good, but about the first of the month my poor
                massager, a sturdy young German, fell ill with typhoid fever, and I am now sliding
                backward.</p>  
            <p>Today is your day for talking about Mr. Lincoln, but I suppose you will not.</p>
            <p>April 16.—I was interrupted here, and could not resume until now. I must
                certainly try to write to Dr. Bucke.<ptr target="n0119"/> His visit here en route to
                Florida was very pleasant. I am glad to hear that Kennedy's<ptr target="n3039"/>
                book is to come out. I tried to get him some subscribers here, but, alas! my
                wretched lameness prevents me from exerting myself as I want to. Stedman<ptr target="n1043"/> was here during the Authors' week, and told me he had
                subscribed, which was good of him. He spent an evening with us and spoke of you with
                enthusiasm. I read over lately, for the first time, his article on you as it appears
                in the book, and find he has greatly improved it, making many excisions and
                modifications. It gratified me to see that my talk with him after the magazine
                article came out had impressed him. His face is Zionward, and he will be a credit to
                the family yet. He gave me a beautiful account of your last reading of the Lincoln
                Memorial—the look at the theater, the magic scene of you on the stage
                inorbed by the light of the lamp on the table, the little girl coming up to you with
                the basket of flowers, &amp;c., &amp;c. It must all have been very charming.</p>
            <p>I did not even know that you were writing little pieces for the Herald<ptr target="n4133"/> until some
                time after you had begun; then I got the back numbers as far as I could, and cut out
                the pieces, but could not get them all. So I shall be glad to see them in November
                Boughs. I should like to know what arrangement Bennett made with you, whether it
                still continues, &amp;c. I am all in the dark about it. And what is the meaning of
                this onslaught that Tucker<ptr target="nyp.00496_n4"/> makes on you in Liberty—Tucker, who did such
                yeoman's service for us in the fight with Oliver Stevens and Company? I don't
                understand it at all. I hope you have not been writing anything in praise of that
                old dead werewolf, Emperor William. It would be an awful mistake. His was a black
                record. I cannot help thinking that Tucker has made some egregious blunder, but I
                have no light on the matter at all.</p>
            <p>Donnelly's<ptr target="n4108"/> book is announced for May, the printer's strike in
                Chicago having delayed it. All is blooming for him. He is now in England, and there
                is a good deal of excitement about him. The delay in publication has enabled him to
                translate about fifty pages more of the cipher for his volume, which is a decided
                gain for the true believer. Despite my illness and inanition, I am all agog for the
                result.</p>
            <p><lg>
                    <l>"O for the light of another sun,</l>
                <l>With my Bazra sword in my hand!"<ptr target="med.00824_n3"/> </l>
                </lg></p>
            <p>Donnelly has made lately a remarkable discovery—that the two folio editions of
                the play following the edition of 1623, at intervals of nine and twelve years
                respectively, long after Bacon's<ptr target="n4261"/> death, are absolute facsimiles
                of the first, even the same number of words on each page being preserved. As
                stereotype did not then exist, these editions were manifestly in each case reset,
                which could only have been done in this way with great painstaking: and it proves
                that somebody in the interest of Bacon was alive and busy in preserving carefully
                the form of the original folio! This is a swashing blow for the Shakespeareans!</p>
            <p>What an idyl of your room you opened to me in your flash of description—you in
                the big chair, the window open to the sunset, the Easter lilies on the sill, and the
                little bird singing his furious carol! It was quite divine. How I wish you could get
                active and well!</p> 
            <p>If Nelly<ptr target="n4137"/> knew I were writing she would surely send you her love.
                She has not been very well this spring—colds being rampant with everyone.</p>
            <p>Good-bye, dear Walt—that is, au revoir. I hope you will keep fairly well at any
                rate, and that I shall see you before long.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Always affectionately,</salute>
                <signed>W. D. O'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>