<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00960">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 9 August 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>med.00960</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 21 August 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-21">21 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="page">[3]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 9 August 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-08-09" xml:id="dat1">August 9, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806–1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809–1869)—the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)—were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">updated notes for publication</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-11" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-06" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-11-04" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-08-09"><handShift rend="printed"/>August 9, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Public attention here, is largely directed toward the
                Buffalo Convention,<ptr target="med.00956_n8"/> which meets to-day. This convention
                seems to be formed in utter defiance of all precedents and "party usages." Much of
                it is on a charming voluntary principle—I mean that of a man making himself a
                delegate, because so it seems good in his own sight. Any body, therefore, who wanted
                to go to Buffalo, (for $13 and 50 cents, which takes one all the way from New
                York, and back too,) has had his wish gratified, or else it was his own fault.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>That you may realize how politics are broken up here, just
                listen to the following remark made by the Chairman of the Whig<ptr target="med.00961_n4"/> General Committee of New York, to a distinguished
                Editor: "Sir," said the Chairman, "the proper Whig organization of the
                city—the Clay<ptr target="med.00954_n8"/> Whigs—embody six thousand
                votes. We know them all—we know that they are, almost to a man, going for Van
                    Buren."<ptr target="med.00989_n2"/> Now, this gentleman is a reliable authority,
                and has generally been supposed to know what he talks about. What do you think of
                it?</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The principal beauty of our "Barnburner"<ptr target="med.00950_n1"/> friends, consists in their delightful, youthful, aspect
                of <hi rend="italic">defiance</hi>—quite picturesque and refreshing to one's
                tired consciousness of party obedience and "harmony." Nothing will please
                them—these don't-care-a-damnative young men. They reject advice, and insult
                even the senators and venerable editors who give it. They seem to glory in kicking
                up the most precious of rows—in rebelling against all the political etiquette
                of the last thirty years. Then the ease and complacency of the rascals—with
                what cool vanity they dare their elders and superiors in station, to do battle with
                them—either in argument or any other way. It is amazing!</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/> Amid all the wrangles of the politicians, however, a man
                may safely wrap himself up and take comfort in the fact, that the great
                self-interest of the people of the Republic never <hi rend="italic">can</hi> let any
                imminent danger happen to our land. Besides, I am confident that more than a third
                of the Americans are not much interested in <hi rend="italic">party</hi>
                politics—but always hold the balance, and only turn it when the times
                demand.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Quite a startling case of attempted murder has just been
                coming off, over in Brooklyn, in one of the prettiest parts of that pretty city. In
                a long, undulating street, thickly shaded with large trees, and out of the way of
                clatter and the usual city noise—I speak of Johnson street—stands a
                little corner grocery, neater and cleaner than most shops of the kind. It was kept
                by a young German named Behms, and his wife.<ptr target="med.00965_n2"/> Last Sunday
                evening, another German, named Korth,<ptr target="med.00961_n3"/> called upon Behms,
                and complained of being unwell. Mrs. B. wished him to partake of a cup of tea, which
                she said she would prepare for him. Korth, however, declined the tea, but asked for
                a glass of cool water. Behms then went out to get some from the pump; and while he
                was gone, Korth attempted to help himself to some money from the shop till. The
                woman, of course, remonstrated, and tried to prevent him. Korth inflicted wounds
                upon her, of which she has since been at the point of death. He continued to rummage
                the drawer and some other places, after a larger sum of money, $800, which Behms
                had mentioned the reception of, a day or two before. Not finding this, and hearing
                Behms returning, Korth went out the back door, and struck the husband down too;
                after which he took himself off, leaving the two for dead. Behms, however, called
                loudly, and the neighbors came. Mrs. B., upon medical examination, was given over,
                though she fully had her faculties, and her testimony was taken, <hi rend="italic">in extremis</hi>; and
                the above narration is founded upon it. Up to this time, however, she is alive. The
                officers forthwith commenced a search for Korth, but he was not discovered nor
                arrested till the next morning, when he was taken at the foot of Courtland street,
                just as he was stepping on board one of the Albany boats.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>We had a real wonderful meeting, night before last, at
                Vauxhall Garden, in behalf of Irish repeal.<ptr target="loc.03571_n1b"/> Over twenty
                thousand persons were present; and, what was better, the contributions poured in
                liberally. We are daily expecting a formal protest against all this, from that
                "tight little isle" over the ocean.</p>
         
               <p><handShift rend="printed"/>The omnibus war waxeth more and more furious—the
                proprietors<ptr target="med.00960_n4"/> standing on their dignity, and the
                drivers standing <hi rend="italic">out</hi>. It is quite dreadful! Heaven only knows
                what will be the end of these things. It is well the regular army is now disengaged.
                I must give you a good toast, (it has been in some of the papers already,) delivered
                by one of the lunatics at the Utica Asylum, lately:</p>
            <q>
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <p>
                            <handShift rend="printed"/>"<hi rend="italic">The Revolution in Europe</hi>.<ptr target="med.00961_n5"/>—While in the old world the people are trying to
                mould governments after ours—may we take care that we do not spoil the
                pattern."</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Wouldn't it be good to exchange some of our lunatics at
                Washington, and in almost every political gathering, for lunatics of the Utica
                sort?</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Van Buren will undoubtedly be nominated at Buffalo, in the
                course of to-day or to-morrow. You cannot possibly realize the ferocity of feeling
                that exists in this State at the present time, between the "Regulars" and the
                "Bolters." The disputes at the commencement of the present century between the
                Jeffersonians and the Federalists, were milk and honey to the present.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Those stories of <hi rend="itlalic">negroes</hi> going to
                the Buffalo Convention, are nonsense. If any have gone, they were sent by the
                enemies of the Convention. Every effort is determinedly made by these "Free Soilers"
                to steer clear of the Abolitionists proper—a faction who have no respectable
                power, on their own platform, here.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>