<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.00962">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 15 August 1848</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schoeberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="zt">Zachary Turpin</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.00962</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="newspaper">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><choice>
                                <orig>Manahattan</orig>
                                <reg>Walt Whitman</reg>
                            </choice></author>
                        <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 15 August 1848</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">The Daily Crescent</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date when="1848-08-25">25 August 1848</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="page">[2]</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to the Editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily Crescent</hi>, 15 August 1848</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1848-08-15" xml:id="dat1">August 15, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="med">The location of the original manuscript is unknown.
                        Whitman's letters to Alexander Hamilton Hayes (1806&#8211;1866) and John Eliot
                        McClure (ca. 1809&#8211;1869)&#8212;the editors of <hi rend="italic">The Daily
                            Crescent</hi> (New Orleans, Louisiana)&#8212;were published in that newspaper.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Editors of The Daily Crescent">Editors of <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Daily Crescent</hi></persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-11" who="#smb">updated notes for publication</change>
            <change when="2023-04-13" who="#aja">corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-02-13" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2023-02-06" who="#aja">annotations check</change>
            <change when="2022-11-07" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-09-17" who="#smb">encoded</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#zt">transcribed</change>
            <change when="2020-11-01" who="#ss">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place"><handShift rend="printed"/>N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> Y<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ORK</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">ITY</hi>,</name>
                    <date when="1848-08-15"><handShift rend="printed"/>August 15, 1848.</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>During the last six days every body here has been agog
                with the Buffalo Convention,<ptr target="med.00961_n2"/> and matters thereunto
                appertaining. It seems that seventeen States had delegations there&#8212;Ohio by
                hundreds, and New York by thousands.&#8212;From the reports, there were some fifty
                thousand person assembled, about one-third of whom were delegates. Judge McLean<ptr
                    target="med.00956_n2"/> withdrew in the beginning. Senator Hale's<ptr
                    target="nhs.00001_n1"/> friends, however, rallied a very respectable vote for
                him, but not quite enough to take the game; whereupon they gave in with a good
                grace, and Van Buren<ptr target="med.00989_n2"/> was ratified by acclamation.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Much astonishment is felt, however, at the nomination for
                the Vice Presidency. Very few people had hitherto heard of Charles Francis Adams<ptr
                    target="med.00961_n6"/>&#8212;except, perhaps, in the demesnes of Boston, where
                he has occupied, for years past, a position among the editorial corps. What the
                reasons of bringing him forward are, do not as yet appear upon the surface. The
                managing men at Buffalo, however, had some good reasons in their own minds, no
                doubt. McLean or Hale had been generally fixed upon for the station.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>O, what a ferment we are in! The impetus from Buffalo has
                come five hundred miles to us, and little is talked of in the streets and public
                places generally, but the three tickets. Taylor<ptr target="med.00989_n10"/> has
                many firm friends here, notwithstanding the heavy ground-swell that sets in from
                certain quarters against him. Cass,<ptr target="med.00972_n2"/> I judge from what I
                hear and see, is least likely to carry New York of any of the candidates. Indeed,
                the shrewdest politicians do not count this State for the regular Democratic
                nominees at all.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Very many of the "good society" of the town are off to
                watering places, and spots all along shore, and some of them in the woods. They are
                having high times, I see, at Saratoga. Down at Rockaway, and off at Newport, also,
                balls, pic-nics, jollity, courting, promenading, etc., form the happy employment of
                some five thousand, probably more, happy dogs. Happy did I say? Well, who knows that
                they are any happier than we who are comfortably staying at home, and don't stir out
                during the three hours on each side of meridian line?</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>There is a report in town that Gen. Worth<ptr
                    target="med.00962_n3"/> has arrived&#8212;he of the "waving plume." He should
                have come hereafter, or else a couple of months earlier. Just about now, he won't
                find people disposed to pay anybody much attention, except he come to them talking
                politics. The gallant General wrote a gratuitous letter to act on the Baltimore
                    Convention,<ptr target="med.00952_n5"/> in which the desire for <hi
                    rend="italic">something</hi> stood out so prominently that even he who ran might
                read what he, the General, so very much wanted. This letter-writing has killed
                better men than Worth; and it has cooled the ardor of the friends of the latter
                exceedingly. It is every way to be hoped, however, that the gallant General will be
                received by his fellow citizens with due honor and courtesy; for he bore himself
                valiantly and wisely in the field.</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Mr. Trist's<ptr target="med.00962_n4"/> violent and
                passionate attack on the President does not receive much serious attention. The
                Ex-Commissioner overleaps the mark in his fury, and charges too much on his
                extensively abused Excellency of the White House. Probably Trist is a little
                demented&#8212;at least at times. What do you think about it?</p>
            <p><handShift rend="printed"/>Every body is anxious to hear what they have done in
                Ireland.<ptr target="loc.03571_n1d"/> Heaven grant it may be good news for Freedom!</p>
            <closer>
                <signed><handShift rend="printed"/>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ANHATTAN</hi>.</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>  
    </text> 
</TEI> 
