<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="nhh.00001">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>  
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to John Parker Hale, 14 August [1852]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kjb">Kassie Jo Baron</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="jh">Jeff Hill</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor> Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder> National Historical Publications and Records Commission </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p> Copyright © 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, 
                        in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, 
                        Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has 
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>nhh.00001</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to John Parker Hale, 14 August [1852]</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1852-08-14" xml:id="dat1">August 14, [1852]</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="nhs">New Hampshire Historical Society</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="unk"><persName key="Unknown">Unknown</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Hale, John Parker" ref="nhs.00001_n1">John Parker Hale</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-02" who="#smb">final check, update</change>
            <change when="2023-07-27" who="#aja">final corrections for Ed</change>
            <change when="2022-09-19" who="#jh">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-07-15" who="#kjb">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2021-07-29" who="#cn">transcribed,encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="nhh.00001.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">
                        Brooklyn, Saturday morn'g
                        <date when="1852-08-14">
                            August 14
                        </date>
                    </name>
                </dateline>
            </opener> 
            <p>
             A word from a stranger, a young man, and a true 
             Democrat I hope.—</p>
            <p>
             You must not only not decline the nomination of the
             Democracy at Pittsburgh, but you must accept it
             gracefully and cordially.<ptr target="nhs.00001_n2b"/> It is well to know when to
             be firm against others' wishes; but it is better,
             to know when to yield in a manly and amiable
             spirit.—</p>
            <p>
             Out of the Pittsburgh movement and "platform" it may be
             that a real live Democratic party is destined to come 
             forth,<ptr target="nhs.00001_n3"/> which, from small beginnings, ridicule, and odium,
             (just like Jeffersonian democracy fifty years ago,) will
             gradually win the hearts of the people and crowd those who
             stand before it into the sea.—Then we should see an
             American Democracy with thews and sinews worthy this
             sublime age.—</p>
            <p>
             It is from the young men of our land—the ardent and
             generous hearts—that these things are to come.—Do
             you, then, yield to the decision at Pittsburgh, shape your
             acceptance to that idea of the future which supposes that we
             are planting a renewed and vital party, fit to triumph over the
             effete and lethargic organizations now so powerful and so unworthy.
             Look to the young men—appeal specially to them.—Enter
             into this condition of affairs, with spirit, too.—Take two
             or three occasions within the coming month to make personal
             <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="nhh.00001.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
             addresses directly to the people, giving condensed embodiments
             of the principal ideas which distinguish our liberal faith from
             the drag-parties and their platforms.—Boldly promulge
             these in that temper of rounded and good-natured moderation which
             is peculiar to you; but abate not one jot of your fullest radicalism.
             After these two or three speeches, which should be well-considered
             and not too long, possess your soul in patience, and take as little
             personal action in the election as may be.—Depend upon it,
             there is no way so good as this face-to-face of candidates
             and people—in the old heroic Roman fashion.—I would
             suggest that one of these addresses be delivered in New York,
             and one of Cincinnati—with a third either in Baltimore or
             Washington.—</p>
            <p>
             You are at Washington, and have for years moved among the great
             men.—I have never been at Washington, and know none of the
             great men.—But I know the people.—I know well
             (for I am practically in New York) the real heart of this mighty
             city—the tens of thousands of young men, the mechanics,
             the writers, &amp;c &amp;c.—In all these, under and
             <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="nhh.00001.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            behind the bosh of the regular politicians, there burns, almost
            with fierceness, the divine fire which more or less, during all
            ages, has only waited a chance to leap forth and confound the
            calculations of tyrants, hunkers, and all their tribe.—At 
            this moment, New York is the most radical city in America.—It
            would be the most anti-slavery city, if that cause hadn't been
            made ridiculous by the freaks of the local leaders here.—</p>
            <p>
             O my dear sir, I only wish you could know the sentiment of
             respect and personal good will, toward yourself, with which,
             upon seeing a telegraphic item in one of this morning's
             papers, that you would probably decline. I forthwith sat down,
             and have written my thoughts and advice.—I shall make
             no apology; for if sentiments and opinions out of the great 
             mass of the common people are of no use to the legislators,
             then our government is a sad blunder indeed.—</p>
            <p>
             How little you at Washington—you Senatorial and Executive
             dignitaries—know of us, after all.—How little you realize
             that the souls of the pople ever leap and swell to any thing like 
             a great liberal thought or principle, uttered by any well-known
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="nhh.00001.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> 
            personage—and how deeply they love the man that promulges 
            such principles with candor and power.—It is wonderful in your
            keen search and rivalry for popular favor that hardly any one discovers
            this direct and palpable road there.—       
            </p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Walter Whitman</signed> 
                <address>
                    <addrLine>
                        Cumberland st. near Atlantic
                    </addrLine>
                    <addrLine>
                        Brooklyn N.Y.
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
            </closer>
            <note type="editorial" place="right" resp="#unk">
                Walt Whitman Aug 14. 1852
            </note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>