<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch" type="xml"?>  

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="nyp.00565">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ezra Heywood to Walt Whitman, 5 November 1882</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ezra Heywood</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="sd">Sara Duke</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>nyp.00565</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ezra Heywood</author>
                    <title>Ezra Heywood to Walt Whitman, 5 November 1882</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1882-11-05" xml:id="dat1">November 5, 1882</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="nyp">The Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature, New York Public Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Heywood, Ezra" ref="n4285">Ezra Heywood</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-06-20" who="#if">added notes</change>
            <change when="2016-06-16" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-09-22" who="#sd"> transcription and encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place" rend="center">Princeton, Mass.</name>
                    <date when="1882-11-05" rend="center">Nov 5, Y.L.10</date>
                    <date when="1882-11-05" rend="right">1882</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir&#8211;</salute>
            </opener>

            <p>Knowing of your illness, through newspaper reports, I do not
                like to intrude anything upon you, but think perhaps you &amp; those standing
                near you would like to know of the latest said on Leaves of Grass,&#8211; 
                or rather on printed  extracts from it&#8212; for which "offence" I was arrested
                by Anthony Comstock,<ptr target="n4286"/> Oct 26, &amp; am held for trial (first-hearing), Nov. 16, 
                in U.S. Court, 140 Tremont St. Boston, before Commissioner Henry L. 
                Hallett. Nov 2, 1877, Comstock came as "E. Edgewell," a Free Lover; this time
                he is a Labor Reformer, masked under three different aliases &amp; telling a
                dozen lies to get what he calls evidence.  As Mar 18, 1873 he wrote from <choice><sic>Washing.</sic><corr>Washington</corr></choice>
                to furnish truth, ideas not brains to readers. 
                I <choice><sic>inclose</sic> <corr>enclose</corr></choice> one of the slips&#8211; the bit of red&#8211;cloth 
                which now enrages the United&#8211;States, ecclesiastical bull tearing towards us. Human language
                contains no finer type of manly sympathy for the supported "fallen," no more 
                impressive portraiture of the divinity of motherhood than is apparent in these two "obsene" 
                poems. I <choice><sic>inclose</sic><corr>enclose</corr></choice> also the Resolution accepted by the N.E. Free Love Convention in Boston 
                last May, in which Dr. J.H. Savain, the old&#8211;time Anti&#8211;Slavery, Woman Suffrage, 
                &amp; Socialistic reformer read these two poems, to the people assembled, three times, 
                at as many different sessions, as the most significant &amp; interesting scriptures 
                of these times presentable.
            </p>
            <p>Since my release, by President Hayes,<ptr target="n4287"/> Dec 19, 1878, from Dedham Jail, 
            where I was serving out a two&#8211;years sentence for alleged&#8211;mailing a copy of my own book, 
            Cupids Yokes, I was slowly becoming comparatively "respectable" again, when lo, 
            suddenly, I am "of no reputation"! As a notable instance of what you call 
            "color&#8211;blindness" I <choice><sic>inclose</sic><corr>enclose</corr></choice> a clip, from the last 
            Truth Seeker, written by Editor D.M. Bennett<ptr target="n4288"/> who himself served out a years sentence 
            in Albany Penitentiary for alleged&#8211;mailing of Cupids Yokes. What have citizens 
            done that they are afraid or ashamed now? I was glad to reprint&#8211;extended extracts 
            from a Philadelphia paper, relative to your book, in Nov. Word &amp; will send you it 
            soon. As you doubtless know, your book is openly advertised in at least one Boston 
            newspaper, Benj. R. Tucker,<ptr target="n4290"/> the editor  of Liberty, inviting <hi rend="underline">defying</hi> Oliver Stevens, Anthony Comstock, Postmaster Tobey<ptr target="n4289"/> or any 
            other repressive Regulator of morals to order a copy which he promises to <hi rend="underline">send by mail</hi> 
            or otherwise deliver to any address! It is also freely sold on the streets by Josephine 
            S. Tilton, the persistent Socialist once imprisoned for her Faith&#8211; many buying 
            it indeed in bookstores &amp; at news stands all over New England. Though the 
            "sealed order" of events, which we all must obey, sent Comstock up here, to our 
            Mountain&#8211; Home perch in the Air, to snatch me, a comparatively old jail&#8211;bird, 
            first, Mr. Tucker, if they conceal me, will very likely next be "elected" as one 
            of my fellow convicts in Dedham Jail. The end years in the form; rejoicing in the poetic fervor, the devine Afflatus 
            which you incarnate I am ever your greatly indebted reader,</p>

            <closer>
                <signed rend="right">Ezra H. Heywood </signed>
                <signed rend="left"> Walt&#8211;Whitman Esq.</signed>
                <signed rend="center">Camden, N.J. </signed>
            </closer>
            <!-- There is a forward note from Whitman written at the end of the letter, as he was sending it on to someone else. -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
