<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="owu.00030">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Jessie Louisa Whitman to Walt Whitman, 6 March
                    1888</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Jessie Louisa Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="bbb">Blake Bronson-Bartlett</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p> 
                </availability>
            <idno>owu.00030</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Jessie Louisa Whitman</author>
                    <title>Jessie Louisa Whitman to Walt Whitman, 6 March 1888</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1888-03-06" xml:id="dat1">March 6, 1888</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="owu">The Bayley-Whitman Collection, Ohio Wesleyan University,
                        Delaware, OH</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Jessie Louisa" ref="n1055">Jessie Louisa
                        Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-07-25" who="#smb">updated final corrections</change>
            <change when="2018-12-04" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2018-10-05" who="#blh">Second check</change>
            <change when="2018-01-19" who="#aa">Checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2017-10-06" who="#bbb">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="owu.00030.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Hartford</name>
                    <date when="1888-03-06">Mar. 6th/88</date>
                    <name type="place">Direct</name>
                    <name type="place">#15 Washington St</name>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Uncle Walt.</salute> 
            </opener>
            <p>I am afraid you will think my promise to write to you was not sincere but I have had
                very little time to myself for letter writing but now that I have set about to
                redeem my word I hope it will be welcome and receive a speedy reply from you. To
                begin at the beginning of my visit I spent nearly three weeks in New York with Mr.
                &amp; Mrs. Northen<ptr target="n5001"/> and of course<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="owu.00030.002.jpg" type="verso"/> had a splendid opportunity of going
                about and seeing all I wanted in New York. I was quite fortunate with regard to the
                weather as I believe we only had two real stormy days while I was there. One thing I
                enjoyed about as much as any was the exhibition of pictures out at the Museum in the
                Park. Miss Woolf's<ptr target="n5001"/> collection, the very rich lady who died a
                year or so ago, was there also a large number of others including the one given by
                Vanderbilt called "The Horse Fair."<ptr target="owu.00030_n2"/> I believe<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="owu.00030.003.jpg" type="recto"/> looking at beautiful pictures and
                hearing good music are my chief pleasures with of course reading added the last a
                thing one could hardly exist without.</p>
            <p>I went over to Brooklyn to call on Jo. Barkelor.<ptr target="n5001"/> You of course
                remember her, she was so fond Grandma<ptr target="n0705"/> and is one of your ardent
                admirers. I did enjoy seeing her so much as I was unfortunate to miss her when I
                called last July as she had sailed for Europe the day before.</p>
            <p>She is a very lovely and smart<pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="owu.00030.004.jpg" type="verso"/> woman. Well to proceed with my trip I left New York on the
                twentieth of February for Hartford and have enjoyed my visit so far very much. These
                friends were new last fall but I almost feel as if I had known them always,
                particularly one from Ireland who is on a visit to America for
                the first time. Next Saturday I go to another friend's house
                for a couple of weeks which will about end my traveling about and turn my face once
                more towards Burlington. </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Do write me very soon and accept lots of love from<ptr target="owu.00030_n1"/></salute>
                <salute>Your niece</salute>
                <signed>Jessie Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>