<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"
?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pml.00086">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 15 February 1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln
                </sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>
                    National Historical Publications and Records Commission
                </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt> 
                <edition>
                    <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>
                        Copyright © 2016 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may
                        be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication 
                        on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification 
                        of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic 
                        images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            <idno>pml.00086</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Ernest Rhys</author>
                    <title>Ernest Rhys to Walt Whitman, 15 February 1887</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1887-02-15" xml:id="dat1">February 15, 1887</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="pml">The Pierpont Morgan Library, New York</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Rhys, Ernest" ref="loc.03310_n1">Ernest Rhys</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-06-15" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-05-24" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2016-04-25" who="#smb">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="pml_nk.00058_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1887-02-15">15th Feb. '87</date>
                    <name type="place">59 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, London, S.W.<lb/>England.
                    </name>  
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt Whitman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
                Yesterday was indeed a day, for almost every post brought me <choice><orig>despatches</orig><reg>dispatches</reg></choice> in your familiar hand which it always gives me a thrill to see.
                First came the two postcards, then the copy of <hi rend="underline">Specimen Days</hi> &amp; the Camden paper, last the letter which I found waiting on returning at midnight 
                from a journalistic excursion to Fleet Street—where I completed an account of a great fire which has been raging just opposite here in a timber wharf
                for two days &amp; nights,—a most lurid spectacle, with the old Thames as reflector!</p>
            <p>
                I must not decide off-hand about the <hi rend="underline">Specimen Days</hi>,—that is, whether to make two vols. as you suggest, or to try
                &amp; get the whole into one. In the latter case, the book would be rather crowded. We put much less into most of the 'Camelots,' than there is in <hi rend="underline">
                King Arthur</hi>, &amp; give them much larger print, &amp; I want to have you shewn as brightly &amp; impressively as possible in point of typography, &amp;c.
                On the other hand the publishers might not be willing to issue the 2nd vol., supposing we divide, very soon. I will consult with Gordon<ptr target="loc.03316_n1"/> to-day, &amp; you shall hear
                at once when the matter is settled.</p>
            <p>
                I do hope that by this you have decided to send off the extra words of introduction! They would give the book an added "send" into the midst of our readers &amp; do a deal of good so. But I know how things
                are with you, &amp; do not want to give you more trouble than can be helped. For the two addtional photos, many, may thanks! I will see what Gordon says about putting
                the portrait in at p. 122. In such a cheap series we have to be careful about first cost &amp; this hampers us very much.—
            </p>
            <p>
               No! I would not think of putting the copy of <hi rend="underline">Specimen Days</hi> with your corrections into the printer's hands and will get copies 
                from Wilson of Glasow<ptr target="loc.03316_n2"/>, carefully following all your deletions &amp; so on. It is one of the greatest prizes I possess, &amp; someday a sense of its value will
               inspire me, I'm afraid, to beg you to send me a copy of <hi rend="underline">Leaves of Grass</hi> too with your name in it, (&amp; mine, as proof of ownership) &amp; 
                some further inscription as well. You see what it is to give the inch; now I am coolly asking the ell. Most of all
                though, I feel very powerfully impelled to come over to the States this year, for myself. Dr. Bucke<ptr target="n0119"/> pressed me to do so again last week, &amp; things have been working in that direction
                for some time now. W. S. Kennedy<ptr target="n3039"/> has asked me to stay with him too, &amp; there are other friends. If I came, I should have to send letters to the papers here, &amp; 
                perhaps lecture too, to pay my way; for you know the usual straits of a young scribe! I come to my last halfpenny indeed almost every week, &amp; am getting quite 
                used to the condition at last. It educates one's faculties &amp; sympathies tremendously.
            </p>
            <p>
             I expect Gordon will send off the ten guineas at once. I ask him to do so to-day. They shall be sent by P. O. order as you direct to 328 Mickle St.
            </p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="pml_nk.00059_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>