<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="syr.00026">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 25 July
                    1885</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00026</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 25 July 1885</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1885-07-25" xml:id="dat1">July 25, 1885</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-08-04" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-07-01" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-06-04" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-04-01" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-12-02" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2014-11-24">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00096.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">Washington, D.C.<ptr target="syr.00026_n4"/></name>
                    <date when="1885-07-25">July 25, 1885.</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>

            <p> I hope your stroke of exhaustion from the heat was not as serious as the newspaper
                made it seem. I always make allowance for the reporter. The weather here for ten
                days past has been as bad as the Soudan's Torrid. At this moment (Sunday afternoon)
                the clouds have gathered heavily, and the thunder is rumbling so I suppose relief is
                coming. </p>
            <p> I have had a strange illness lately, but hope I am getting better. It took the form
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="syr_kc.00097.jpg" type="verso"/> of utter
                weakness, and for a fortnight I barely had the use of my legs, and tumbled down on
                the slightest provocation. I began to wonder whether I was going to match you. The
                doctor, however, says it will pass if I take great care of myself, requiring me to
                keep as quiet as possible. I suppose it comes form my being much run down. </p>
            <p> I am glad you liked the photo. It is a good likeness, and quite powerful as a
                    picture.<ptr target="syr.00026_n1"/> That Bacon is a great success. If I could
                only get a steel engraving! This is only <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="syr_kc.00098.jpg" type="recto"/> a wood cut, and probably does small
                justice to Vandyk's portrait. The resemblance to the ideal pictures of Shakespeare
                is remarkable&#8212;I think, prophetic.&#8212;Donnelly writes me that the cipher is coming
                out gloriously. It is a complete narrative of Bacon's life and times, regularly
                underlying the text of the plays, and settles the Bacon-Shakespeare question
                conclusively. William will have to step down and out for good. I laugh when I think
                of the chagrin of the Shakespeareans, who have been so insolent and intolerant, and
                suppressed evidence with a high hand.<ptr target="syr.00026_n2"/> Donnelly, when <pb
                    xml:id="leaf002v" facs="syr_kc.00099.jpg" type="verso"/> he was here, got
                quite intimate with me, explained the law of the cipher, and read me a good deal of
                the translation. The cipher is by regular rule, which will stop the mouth of any
                caviller. It is as simple and indisputable as twice two are four, but terribly <hi
                    rend="underline">laborious</hi> to decipher, the process being one of continual
                counting of words. I am amazed at the revolutionary daring of the device on the part
                of Bacon. You will be surprised to see how the corruption of the text is accounted
                for. In every case, so far, where the sense <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="syr_kc.00100.jpg" type="recto"/> is in doubt, it is explained by the
                sacrifice of some word to the exigencies of the cipher. Doubtless the cipher will
                end by telling us where the original true manuscripts are hidden, which I will bet
                are in the Shakespeare monument (not grave) at Stratford. The scene in the cipher
                where Bacon to save the life of his servant, Henry Percy, acknowledges to Queen
                Elizabeth his own authorship of Richard Second and the other plays up to that date,
                is tremendously striking. She calls him, "Thou damned beast," clutches him by the
                beard and beats him with her crutch. No wonder <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00101.jpg" type="verso"/> that Essex meant to stab the old
                termagant (as Bacon calls her in the cipher) with his own hand&#8212;habitually inflicting
                such indignities on the great men around her. Essex himself got a blow in the face
                from her.&#8212;All the account of Shakespeare's raid on Sir Thomas Lucy's park; his
                flight to London; his appearance, ragged and barefooted, in front of the Red Bull
                theatre, bawling for horses to hold, where Bacon first saw him, is quite rich. "A
                good-tempered, ragged wretch," is Bacon's description of him. </p>
            <p> The bit from the "Journal of Commerce" which young Johann <pb xml:id="leaf004r"
                    facs="syr_kc.00102.jpg" type="recto"/> sent you, shows that we still live.
                There was quite a blast for me lately in the Boston "Advertiser"&#8212;very
                friendly, but full of the oddest errors, as, for example, where he makes me very
                finicky about spelling my name with only one n (!!) and has me as librarian of the
                Department, etc. C. W. E. sent the "Journal of Commerce" a list of the poems written
                about you, requested by its correspondent. </p>
            <p> I get the papers you send, including the <hi rend="underline">Tribune</hi> with
                Smalley's letter about Victor Hugo,<ptr target="syr.00026_n3"/> written with his
                usual admirable talent and deformed, as usual, by his meanness. He is the meannest
                man living. I always used to say he could be parsed&#8212;positive Small,
                comparative Smaller, superlative Smalley! </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="syr_kc.00103.jpg" type="verso"/>

            <p> Victor Hugo's death much weakened my appetite for life. I read with interest what he
                said about Shakespeare, but the criticism about his indifference to the lower
                classes does not touch me as true. It never appears to be remarked, that of all the
                wise, compassionate, sympathetic men of that age, not one spoke up for the poor and
                downtrodden. Why? Because they could not! Victor Hugo in that age would have had to
                be silent. One single line in a scene expressing even latent sympathy with the Jack
                Cades or Wat Tylers, would have sent its author at once to the block, and the play
                itself would have been suppressed even before it had appeared, so watchful and
                relentless was the censorship. To realize the bloody, brassy, wanton rigor of the
                military despotism <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="syr_kc.00104.jpg" type="recto"
                /> then in power, one has only to note the treatment Raleigh got. The government
                was simply infernal&#8212;almost inconceivable. The only thing the illuminati of
                that day could do was to set about the slow sap of the monarchy. This was the only
                way they could rehabilitate the commons. To alter your sense a little&#8212;"the
                indirect is as great and real as the direct"&#8212;and the indirect was their only
                weapon or implement. </p>
            <p> I too heard lately from Dr. Bucke,<ptr target="n0119"/> urging me to visit him. I
                wish you could go up there, but have no doubt you are prudent to stay near home. </p>
            <p> Mrs. Gilchrist<ptr target="n0259"/> sent me <pb xml:id="leaf005v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00105.jpg" type="verso"/> a copy of the "Today." I have
                really not had the strength or mind to read what she has written&#8212;I have been
                so ill and feeble&#8212;but intend to soon. I have no doubt her article is good, and
                when I have read it, I mean to write her my thanks. I have an awful pile of
                unanswered letters. </p>
            <p> Decapitation, of which you ask, seems impending, and I am anxiously thinking what
                field will be open to me, when I am shoved out of here. There have been several
                people after my position already. </p>
            <p> I wish you could get stronger in your legs. It would <pb xml:id="leaf006r"
                    facs="syr_kc.00106.jpg" type="recto"/> be such a comfort to be able to
                move about freely. </p>
            <p> I wrote an article defending Mrs Pott's book<ptr target="loc.03298_n6"/> from
                Richard Grant White, and bringing out several vital points in the Bacon-Shakespeare
                controversy. It was rejected by several magazines, but finally accepted by the <hi
                    rend="underline">Manhattan</hi>, the editor, Forman, being immensely taken with
                it. He held it a long time, hoping the magazine would resume, and surrendered it
                with evident reluctance and regret. Now I propose to bring it out in a book or
                brochure, and have written to McKay offering it to him. If you are in the way of <pb
                    xml:id="leaf006v" facs="syr_kc.00107.jpg" type="verso"/> seeing him, give
                me a boost. I think, considering the general interest just now in the question, it
                might really have some sale. </p>
            <p> Since I began the change has come. Last night we had a tremendous rain, and today it
                continued, though moderately. It is a blessed relief. (Today means Monday, the 27th.) </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Good bye. With best wishes and hopes,</salute>
                <salute>Yours always faithfully,</salute>
                <signed>W.D.O'Connor.</signed>
                <salute/>
                <salute>Walt Whitman.</salute>
            </closer>

            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="syr_kc.00108.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" place="top" resp="#ht">see notes Feb 1st 1889</note>

        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>
