<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="syr.00006">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">John Burroughs to Walt Whitman, 30 October 1871</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>John Burroughs</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="al">Ashley Lawson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00006</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use 
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors 
                        and advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
                        has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>John Burroughs</author>
                    <title>John Burroughs to Walt Whitman, 30 October 1871</title>
                    <date cert="low" when="1871-10-30" xml:id="dat1">October 30, 1871</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Burroughs, John" ref="n0129">John Burroughs</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-08-21" who="#smb">corrected citation</change>
            <change when="2023-06-20" who="#aja">final corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-05-09" who="#aja">updated notes</change>
            <change when="2022-10-01" who="#aja">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-02-17" who="#cn">checked, corrected, added notes</change>
            <change when="2021-11-22" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-04-30">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2012-06-18" who="#js">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-05-07" who="#km">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-03-28" who="#al">checked and corrected</change> 
            <change when="2011-08-31" who="#kk">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr.00006.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">London</name> 
                    <date when="1871-10-30">Oct 30, 1871,</date> 
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I send you by this mail the "Dark Blue" containing the second
                part of Noel's<ptr target="n0815"/> article.<ptr target="n0181"/> I think the illustration horrid. 
                It makes you look like a sick monkey. I wonder Hennessy<ptr target="syr.00006_n1"/> could draw such a 
                <choice><sic>charicature</sic><corr>caricature</corr></choice>. From what Conway<ptr target="n0170"/> 
                said I inferred he had seen it and approved of it. I shall tell him what I think about 
                it. I do not think the article amounts to shucks either. Rossetti<ptr target="n0522"/> 
                said Noel was very much engrossed with politics, and it is evident he is engrossed with 
                something else than poetry to write such a mess!
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="syr.00006.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                Of course the article helps, but after <choice><sic>Dowdens</sic><corr>Dowden's</corr></choice><ptr target="n0199"/> 
                noble paper<ptr target="n0692"/> it seems ineffectual enough, though Conway seemed to think it the more feeling 
                of the two.&#8212;I have not seen Conway or Rossetti since I came back from Paris. I shall 
                see Rossetti again but I do not seem to care much about Conway. I doubt if I could ever 
                fraternize with him. He does not impress me as an eminently sincere and loveable person. It 
                may be very cruel for me to say so, but he seems to me like a kind of literary broker, ever 
                on his make, though I have no complaint to make of his treatment of me &amp; it may be if 
                I knew him better I should like 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr_tb.00001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                him more. Rossetti I am drawn toward, and though my first impression of him was that he was 
                a high flown literary cockney, yet I soon saw that it was of no moment 
                and that he was a genuine good fellow. He praises Prof. Dowden whom he has met and says I 
                will like him. I intend to go to Ireland if possible, though it looks doubtful now as 
                Assistant Secretary Richardson<ptr target="syr.00006_n2"/> has impressed me into his service here &amp; 
                proposes to retain me &amp; my party a week or two later than we had contemplated staying. I 
                am at work in the office or Branch of the Treasury Dept here with 4 or 5 other clerks and the 
                beautiful October days are slipping by and I am not tramping about Stratford or up the mountains 
                of Wales or into Ireland 
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="syr.00006.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                as I had promised myself I should be. I have seen enough of cities, &amp; streets &amp; art 
                and pictures &amp; museums to stand me all the rest of my days, and am in a hurry to set my 
                face westward.<ptr target="loc.01700_n1"/> I spent about a week in Paris &amp; got enough of it. I presume I was a little 
                surprised when I went from here, so that I did not relish Paris as I should have done had I 
                come to it fresh. It is certainly a very beautiful city and very clean &amp; tasteful. The ruins 
                are in excellent taste &amp; are the best behaved ruins I ever saw, and the Parisians are the 
                best mannered people I ever saw. I think the waiters in the Hotels could give lessons to princes. 
                They bring you fried eggs on a perfumed napkin, and the napkin on beautiful tissue paper &amp; 
                the whole on a china plate (my paper has got mixed up) 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="syr_tb.00002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                and one hardly knows whether to fall to &amp; eat or to lift up his hands in admiration. Yet for 
                all that I was not deeply impressed with Paris. The aspect of the streets is very monotonous. 
                See one block &amp; you have seen it all. It all seems to have been built the same day &amp; planned 
                by the same architect &amp; the stone were unmistakably all dug from the same quarry. Hence it is 
                not picturesque or quaint or homely like London or grand either: it is brilliant &amp; correct. I 
                was much disappointed in the French soldiers; they are certainly a very inferior looking lot of men; 
                small &amp; dirty &amp; indifferent. I find this is the impression of all Americans I have talked 
                with who have seen them. 
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="syr.00006.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                I believe there are but two more parties coming over with bonds. I hope you &amp; William<ptr target="n2002"/> will 
                be among them. I wrote quite a long letter to William which I hope he received. I have seen Carlyle<ptr target="n0139"/> 
                as I told him, and liked him very much. I am sure you would like him &amp; that he would like you. 
                But I must close, dear Walt, hoping to be in <choice><abbr>W.</abbr><expan>Washington</expan></choice> 
                ahead of the snow birds.</p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Your friend</salute>
                <signed>John Burroughs</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>