<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="syr.00005">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Abraham Stoker to Walt Whitman, 18 February
                    1872</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title> 
                <author>Abraham Stoker</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="js">John Schwaninger</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="me">Marie Ernster</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cn">Cristin Noonan</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="pw">Paige Wilkinson</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aja">Amanda J. Axley</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2023</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00005</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2023 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Abraham Stoker</author>
                    <title>Abraham Stoker to Walt Whitman, 18 February 1872</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1872-02-18" xml:id="dat1">February 18, 1872</date>
                    <idno type="callno"/>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Stoker, Bram" ref="n0602">Bram Stoker</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-06-28" who="#aja">final corrections for Ken</change>
            <change when="2023-05-10" who="#aja">added notes</change>
            <change when="2022-10-03" who="#pw">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2022-02-02" who="#cn">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2021-11-22" who="#me">checked, corrected</change>
            <change who="#ak" when="2015-05-08">added correspondent ref</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-08-15">added schematron declaration</change>
            <change when="2014-08-12" who="#el">made basic checking changes to file</change>
            <change when="2013-02-13" who="#cb">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-27" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-23" who="#js">proofed, added strikethroughs</change>
            <change when="2011-09-26" who="#kk">Syracuse ms; added image links; commented out
                bibl</change>
            <change when="2011-07-25" who="#kk">Transcribed; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr.00005.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">43 Harcourt St Dublin</name>
                    <name type="place">Ireland</name>
                    <date when="1872-02-18">18-2.72</date>
                    <date when="1872-02-18">Feb-18, 1872</date>
                </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>If you are the man I take you to be you will like to get this letter.
                if you are not I don't care whether you like it or not, and only ask you to put it
                into the fire without reading any farther. But
                I believe you will like it. I <choice>
                    <sic>dont</sic>
                    <corr>don't</corr>
                </choice> think there is a man living, even you who are above the prejudices of the
                class of small-minded men&#8212;who wouldn't like to get a letter from a younger
                man, a stranger from across the world&#8212;a man living in an atmosphere prejudiced
                to the truths you sing and your manner of singing them. The idea that arises in my
                mind is whether there is a man living who would have the pluck to burn a letter in
                which he felt the smallest atom of interest without reading it. I believe you would
                and that you believe you would
                yourself&#8212;You
                can burn this now if you like and test yourself and all I will ask for my trouble of
                writing this letter, which for all I can tell you may light your pipe with or apply
                to some more ignoble purpose&#8212;is that you will in some manner let me know that
                my words have tested your impatience. Put it in the fire if you like&#8212;but if
                you do you will miss the pleasure of this next sentence which ought to be that you
                have conquered an unworthy impulse. A man who is uncertain of his own strength <hi
                    rend="underline">might</hi> try to encourage himself by a piece of bravo, but a
                man who can write, as you have written, the most candid words that ever fell from
                the lips of mortal man can have no fear for his own strength.&#8212;a man to whose
                candour Rousseau's Confessions<ptr target="syr.00005_n1"/> is
                reticence&#8212;can have no fear for his own strength. If you have gone this far you
                may read the letter and I feel in writing now that I am talking to you. If I were
                before your face I would like to shake hands with you for I feel that I would like
                you&#8212;I would like to call you Comrade and to talk <pb xml:id="leaf001v"
                    facs="syr.00005.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/> to you as men who are not poets do
                not often talk.<ptr target="syr.00005_n2"/> I think that at first I would be ashamed for a man cannot in a moment break the
                habit of comparative reticence that has become a second nature to him; but I know I
                would not be long ashamed to be natural before
                you. You are a true man and I would
                like to be one myself and so I would feel towards you as a brother and as a pupil to
                his master. In this age no man becomes worthy of
                the name without an effort. You have shaken off the shackles and your wings are
                free. I have the shackles on my shoulders still.&#8212;but I have no wings. If you are going
                to read this letter any further I should tell you that I am not prepared to "give up
                all else" so far as words go. The only thing I am prepared to give up is
                prejudice&#8212;and before I knew you I had begun to throw overboard my
                cargo&#8212;but it is not all gone yet. I do not know how you will take this letter.
                I have not <choice>
                    <sic>adressed</sic>
                    <corr>addressed</corr>
                </choice> you in any form as I have heard that you dislike to a certain degree the
                conventional forms in
                letters. I am writing to you because you are different from other men. if you were the same
                as the mass I would not write at all as it is I must either call you Walt Whitman or
                not call you at all&#8212;and I have chosen the latter course.
                I do not know if it is usual for you to get letters from utter strangers who have
                not even the claim of literary brotherhood to write to you&#8212;if it is you must
                be frightfully tormented with letters and I am sorry to have written this. I have
                however the claim of liking you&#8212;for your words are your own soul and even if
                you do not read my letter it is no less a pleasure to me to write it. Shelley<ptr target="n3069"/> wrote to William Godwin<ptr target="syr.00005_n3"/> and
                they became friends. I am not Shelley and you are not Godwin &amp; so I will only
                hope that some time <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr.00005.003_large.jpg"
                    type="recto"/> I may meet you face to face and perhaps shake hands with
                you&#8212;If I ever do it will be one of the greatest pleasures of my life. If you
                care to know who it is that writes this my name is Abraham Stoker (Junior). My <hi
                    rend="underline">friends</hi> call me Bram. I live at no 43 Harcourt St
                Dublin. I am a clerk in the service of the Crown on a small salary. I am twenty
                four years old. Have been champion at our athletic sports (Trinity College Dublin)
                and have won about a dozen cups. I have also been President of the College
                Philosophical Society and an art and theatrical critic of a daily paper. I am six
                feet two inches high and 12 stone weight naked and used to be 41 or 42 inches round
                the chest. I am ugly but strong and determined and have a large bump over my
                eyebrows. I have a heavy jaw and a big mouth with thick lips&#8212;sensitive
                nostrils&#8212;a snub nose and straight hair. I am equal in temper and cool in
                disposition and have a large amount of self control, and am naturally secretive to
                the world. I take a delight in letting people I don't like&#8212;people of mean or
                cruel or sneaking or cowardly disposition&#8212;see the worst side of me. I have a
                large number of acquaintances and some five or six friends&#8212;all of which latter
                body care much for me. Now I have told you all I know about myself. I know you from your works and your photograph; and if I know anything about you I
                think you would like to know of the personal appearance of your correspondents. You
                are I know a keen physiognomist. I am a believer of the science myself and am in an
                humble way a practicer of it. I was not disappointed when I saw your
                photograph&#8212;your late one in especial. The way I came to <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="syr.00005.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/> like you was this. A notice of your poems appeared some two years ago or more in the "Temple Bar"
                    magazine.<ptr target="n0624"/> I glanced at it and took its dictum as final, and
                laughed at you among my friends. I say it to my own shame but not to my regret for
                it has taught me a lesson to last my life out&#8212;without ever having seen your
                poems. More than a year after I heard two men in College talking of you, one of them
                had your book (Rossetti's Edition)<ptr target="n0520"/> and was reading aloud some
                passages at which both laughed. They chose only those passages which are most
                foreign to British ears and made fun of them. Something struck me that I had judged
                you hastily. I took home the volume and read it far into the night. Since then I
                have to thank you for many happy hours, for I have read your poems with my door
                locked late at night, and I have read them on the sea shore where I could look all
                round me and see no more sign of human life than the ships out at sea: and here I
                often found myself waking up from a reverie with the book lying open before me. I
                love all poetry and high generous thoughts make the tears rush to my eyes&#8212;but
                sometimes a word or a phrase of yours takes me away from the world around me and
                places me in an ideal land surrounded by realities more than any poem I ever read.
                Last year I was sitting on the beach on a summer's day reading your preface to the
                Leaves of Grass as printed in Rossetti's Edt., for Rossetti is all I have got till I
                get the complete set of your works which I have ordered <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                    facs="syr.00005.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/> from America). One thought struck
                me and I pondered over it for several hours&#8212;"the weather-beaten vessels old
                ships entering new ports"<ptr target="syr.00005_n4"/> you who wrote the words know them better than I do: and to
                you who sing of your own land of Progress the words have a meaning that I can only
                imagine. But be assured of this Walt Whitman that a man of less than half your own
                age reared a conservative in a conservative country and who has always heard your
                name cried down by the great mass of people who mention it here felt his heart leap
                towards you across the Atlantic, and his soul swelling at the words or rather the
                thoughts. It is vain for me to try to quote any instances of what
                thoughts of yours I like best, for I like them all and you must feel that you are
                reading the true words of one who feels with you. You see I have called you by your
                name I have been more candid with you&#8212;have said more about myself to you than
                I have ever said to any one before&#8212;You will not be angry with me now if you
                have read so far you will not laugh at me for writing thus to you. It was with no
                small effort that I began to write and I feel reluctant to stop, but I must not tire
                you any more. If you ever would care to have more you can imagine, for you have a great heart, how
                much pleasure it would be to me to write more to you, how sweet a thing it is for a
                strong healthy man with a woman's eyes and a child's wishes to feel that he can
                speak so to a man who can be if he wishes father and brother and wife to his soul.
                I don't think you will laugh Walt Whitman, nor despise me, but at all events I thank you for all
                the love and sympathy you have given me in common with my kind.</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Bram Stoker</signed>
            </closer>
        </body>
    </text> 
</TEI>
