<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>
 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="syr.00024">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 25 May
                    1886</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt> 
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian Faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>syr.00024</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2010 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <author>William D. O'Connor</author>
                    <title>William D. O'Connor to Walt Whitman, 25 May 1886</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1883-05-25" xml:id="dat1">May 25, 1886</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="syr">Walt Whitman Collection, Special Collections Research
                        Center, Syracuse University Library, Syracuse, N.Y.</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="ht"><persName key="Traubel, Horace">Horace
                    Traubel</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="O'Connor, William D." ref="n2002">William D. O'Connor</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-22" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-06-25" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2015-05-16" who="#ss">added annotations</change>
            <change when="2014-11-21" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2014-10-22" who="#ak">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="syr_kc.00084.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top left">see notes March 5 <hi rend="underline">1889</hi></note>
            <opener>
                <dateline> 
                    <name type="place">Washington, D.C.<ptr target="syr.00024_n4"/></name>
                    <name type="place">Life Saving Service.</name>
                    <date when="1886-05-25">May 25, 1886.</date> 
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Walt:</salute>
            </opener>
 
            <p> I got your letter of April 12, and since, your postal cards of April 19 and 26
                    respectively.<ptr target="syr.00024_n1"/> Also the envelope containing
                    Kennedy's<ptr target="n3039"/> admirable review of the Longfellow memoir. I have
                been proposing to write to you every day, but it is not easy, I am so poorly. My
                lameness is very bad, and I am very exhausted before many hours pass each day. I
                have piles of unanswered letters. My special trouble now is what they call <hi
                    rend="underline">schlerosis</hi>&#8212;an induration of the lower part of the
                spinal <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="syr_kc.00085.jpg" type="verso"/> cord, a bequest
                of the inflammation caused by the nervous prostration. This it is which makes me so
                lame and strengthless, and unless the doctor can break it up (he is using
                electricity) the result, he tells me, will be paralysis. However, this is some way
                off, and I'm not dead yet! </p> 
            <p> John Burroughs<ptr target="n0129"/> has been here, and gives me an account of your
                health, which makes me feel very badly.<ptr target="syr.00024_n2"/> He told me
                especially of the trouble I share with you&#8212;constipation; and this you <hi
                    rend="underline">must</hi> not, Walt, allow to continue. The very worst aperient
                you could use will do you <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="syr_kc.00086.jpg" type="recto"
                /> less harm than constipation. But there are aperients which are harmless, or
                almost nearly so, and I send you a packet of one which answers this description. It
                is known as Liquorice Powder, and is excellent. The dose is one teaspoonful in, say,
                a half goblet of water, when going to bed, to be taken when necessary. You will find it
                easy and excellent. It is composed only of powdered liquorice and <choice><orig>sulpher</orig><reg>sulfur</reg></choice>, and is
                really without bad effect. Please try it. I have never been troubled with
                costiveness in all my life, but now, like yourself, I have a <pb xml:id="leaf002v"
                    facs="syr_kc.00087.jpg" type="verso"/> partial paralysis of the bowels, and
                must, under medical orders, resort to artificial means, and this is my remedy.
                Anything is better than constipation. The physical feelings it induces are dreadful,
                to say nothing of the constant danger to life. </p>
            <p> I was delighted beyond measure at the success of your lecture. I wish I could have
                been there. The account in the <hi rend="underline">Press</hi> was splendid. Great are Talcott Williams<ptr
                    target="nyp.00459_n4"/> and Thomas Donaldson,<ptr target="syr.00024_n3"/> and
                blessed be their names. </p>
            <p> I had a letter from Dr. Bucke at London. He seems to be having a good time. </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="syr_kc.00088.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p> I am glad you liked the little book. If I could only have written it over, I would
                have made it fuller and better. But when the time came for publishing, I was too ill
                to write.&#8212;I am obliged to you for the notice in the <hi rend="underline">North
                    American</hi> (G.E.M.). It lets out the delicious fact that White had seen the
                article&#8212;probably some magazine that had it, broke faith, and showed it to
                him&#8212;and so he got a full excoriation before crossing Styx, for after he died, I
                took out the severest parts from the <hi rend="underline">MS</hi>. Big rascal! He
                well <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="syr_kc.00089.jpg" type="verso"/> knew the baseness
                of his attack on the <hi rend="underline">Promus</hi> book<ptr target="n4112"/>. I have the best of reasons for believing that he
                was secretly a Baconian, but with his editions of Shakespeare, etc., at stake, the
                balance was on the other side of the ledger for him. </p>
            <p> I am much grieved to learn that Mrs. Pott<ptr target="loc.03298_n6"/> is seriously ill. Nervous prostration.
                Between her tremendous labors on the Bacon subject, her large household duties, and
                her ministrations among the London poor, she has broken down. I feel very anxious
                about her. </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="syr_kc.00090.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <p> Donnelly's<ptr target="n4108"/> boom increases. There is an article in the 19th Century Magazine on his
                cipher, which will make an excitement and greatly raise his credit. He writes me
                that he expects to be ready to publish by June. </p>
            <p> We have had strange weather here. Cold and hot by turns, and rain without stint. Did
                you see the electric storm on Saturday night? I never witnessed such magnificent
                lightning. </p>
            <p> I hope this will find you in good time. </p>
            <closer>
                <salute>Always Affectionately</salute>
                <signed>WDO'Connor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
                <p>Walt Whitman.</p>
            </postscript>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="syr_kc.00091.jpg" type="recto"/>
             <note type="editorial" resp="#ht" place="top">see note Mar 5 <hi rend="underline">1889</hi></note>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
