<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="tex.00452">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to Thomas Donaldson, 11 August
                    [1886]</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>       
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Sch&#246;berlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="kb">Kyle Barton</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>tex.00452</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to Thomas Donaldson, 11 August [1886]</title>
                    <date cert="medium" when="1886-08-11" xml:id="dat1">August 11, 1886</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="tex">The Walt Whitman Collection, Harry Ransom Humanities
                        Research Center, The University of Texas at Austin</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc><handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="td"><persName key="Donaldson, Thomas">Thomas Donaldson</persName></handNote>
        </handNotes>

            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Donaldson, Thomas" ref="n6011">Thomas Donaldson</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-07-16" who="#ss">corrected.</change>
            <change when="2015-05-20" who="#nhg">checked, corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-05-19" who="#ak">added enclosure</change>
            <change when="2015-05-18" who="#nhg">added image names, corrected, added correspondent ref</change>
            <change when="2015-03-25" who="#kb">edited</change>
            <change when="2014-10-24" who="#ss">encoded and annotated from Miller.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="tex.00328.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#td" place="top">Lecture by Walt Whitman on Abraham Lincoln, Phil. <hi rend="underline">April 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1886</hi> |
                Given me by Whitman |
                T.D. Aug 11&#8212;/86.
            </note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="tex.00328.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="tex.00328.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="editorial" resp="#td" place="top">Original notes of Mr Whitmans Lecture on Abraham Lincoln&#8212;delivered by Mr Whitman&#8212;at Chestnut St. Opera House, Phil. Pa&#8212;April 15, 1886. He gave these notes to me Aug 12&#8212;1886</note>
            <!--Donaldson has pasted Whitman's envelope to him on this page-->
            <note type="editorial" resp="#td" place="left"> Rec'd August 12&#8212;1886 | Thos Donaldson</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="tex.00328.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="tex.00328.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="tex.00328.006.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline>
                    <name type="place">328 Mickle Street</name>
                    <name type="place">Camden<ptr target="tex.00452_n1"/></name>
                    <date when="1886-08-11" rend="right">Aug: 11 <note type="editorial" resp="#ww" place="right">&#8212;<hi rend="underline">1886</hi></note> noon</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>My dear friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I send enclosed a full report of my Lincoln lecture for our friend Bram Stoker, as
                you request<ptr target="tex.00452_n2"/>&#8212;</p>
            <p>Nothing very new with me&#8212;I am standing the summer pretty well, so far, go out
                with the rig every day&#8212;Hot here as I write, by the open window.</p>
            <p>&#8212;I have finished the <hi rend="underline">Army Hospitals</hi> article for the <hi
                    rend="underline">Century</hi> &#38; sent it on, &#38; it has been accepted &#38;
                handsomely paid for. (Will not be out I think for several months)&#8212;W Sloane
                Kennedy, of Belmont, Mass. (near Boston) has written a book ab't
                me&#8212;supplementing Dr Bucke's&#8212;has something to say ab't you<ptr
                    target="tex.00452_n3"/>&#8212;&#38; full of contemporary statistics&#8212;Send
                me word what day to come over&#8212;say from 2 to 5 p m&#8212;&#38; have a chat with
                you&#8212;</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer> 
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="tex.00328.007.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="tex.00328.008.jpg" type="recto"/>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="tex.00328.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
 <figure facs="tex.00452.001.jpg">
                     <head type="main-authorial"/>
                     <figDesc>A photograph of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>

                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="tex.00328.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="tex.00328.011.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top">(autograph</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top">Walt Whitman <lb/>June 9 '86</note>
 <figure facs="tex.00452.002.jpg">
                     <head type="main-authorial"/>
                     <figDesc>An photograph of Walt Whitman, accompanied by his autograph.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="tex.00328.014.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="tex.00328.015.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <head><handShift rend="printed"/>WALT WHITMAN</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                    <date when="1886-04-15">April 15, 1886,</date> at <handShift rend="manuscript"/>Chestnut St Opera House <handShift rend="printed"/>Philadelphia.
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    How often since that dark and dripping Saturday&#8212;that chilly April day, now <handShift rend="manuscript"/>twenty-one <handShift rend="printed"/>years bygone&#8212;my heart has entertain'd the dream, the wish, to give of Abraham Lincoln's death its own special thought and memorial. Yet now the sought-for opportunity offers, I find my notes incompetent, (why, for truly profound themes, is statement so idle? why does the right phrase never offer?) and the fit tribute I dreamed of waits unprepared as ever. My talk here indeed is less because of itself or anything in it, and nearly altogether because I feel a desire, apart from any talk, to specify the day, the martyrdom. It is for this, my friends, I have called you together. Oft as the rolling years bring back this hour, let it again however briefly be dwelt upon. For my own part, I hope and intend, till my own dying day, whenever the 14th or 15th of April comes, to annually gather a few friends, and hold its tragic reminiscence. No narrow or sectional reminiscence. It belongs to These States in their entirety&#8212;not the North only, but the South&#8212;perhaps belongs most tenderly and devoutly to the South, of all: for there, really, this man's birth-stock. There and thence his antecedent stamp. Why should I not say that thence his manliest traits&#8212;his universality&#8212;his canny, easy ways and words upon the surface&#8212;his inflexible determination and courage at heart? Have you never realized it, my friends, that Lincoln, though grafted on the West, is essentially, in personnel and character, a Southern contribution?</p><note type="authorial" place="right"><handShift rend="manuscript"/><hi rend="underline">to printer</hi> dont mind the different type</note>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    Though by no means proposing to resume the Secession War to-night, I would briefly remind you of the public conditions preceding that contest. For twenty years, and especially during the four or five before the war actually began, the aspect of affairs in the United States, though without the flash of military excitement, presents more than the survey of a battle, or any extended campaign, or series, even of Nature's convulsions. The hot passions of the South&#8212;the strange mixture at the North of inertia, incredulity, and conscious power&#8212;the incendiarism of the Abolitionists&#8212;the rascality and grip of the politicians, unparalleled in any land, any age. To these I must not omit adding the honesty of the essential bulk of the people everywhere&#8212;yet with all the seething fury and contradiction of their natures more aroused than the Atlantic's waves in wildest equinox.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    What could be more ominous, (though generally unappreciated then)&#8212;what more significant than the Presidentiads of Fillmore and Buchanan? proving conclusively that the weakness and wickedness of elected rulers, backed by our great parties, are just as likely to afflict us here, as in the countries of the Old World, under their monarchies, emperors and aristocracies. In that Old World were everywhere heard underground rumblings, that died out, only again surely to return. While in America the volcano, though civic yet, continued to grow more and more convulsive&#8212;more and more stormy and threatening.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    In the height of all this excitement and chaos, hovering on the edge at first, and then merged in its very midst, and destined to play a leading part, appears a strange and awkward figure.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="tex.00328.016.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="tex.00328.017.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p><handShift rend="manuscript"/><hi rend="underline">First sight of Mr Lincoln</hi></p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    I shall not easily forget the first time I ever saw Abraham Lincoln. It must have been about the 18th or 19th of February, 1861. It was rather a pleasant afternoon in New-York City, as he arrived there from the West, to remain a few hours, and then pass on to Washington, to prepare for his inauguration. I saw him in Broadway, near the site of the present Post Office. He came down, I think, from Canal-st., to stop at the Astor House. The broad spaces, sidewalks and street in the neighborhood and for some distance, were crowded with solid masses of people&#8212;many thousands. The omnibuses and other vehicles had all been turned off, leaving an unusual hush in that busy part of the city. Presently two or three shabby hack barouches made their way with some difficulty through the crowd and drew up at the Astor House entrance. A tall figure stepped out of the centre of these barouches, paused leisurely on the sidewalk, looked up at the dark granite walls and looming architecture of the grand old hotel&#8212;then, after a relieving stretch of arms and legs, turned round for over a minute to scan slowly and good-humoredly the appearance of the vast and silent crowds. There were no speeches&#8212;no compliments&#8212;no welcome&#8212;as far as I could hear, not a word said. Still much anxiety was concealed in that quiet. Cautious persons had feared some marked insult or indignity to the President-elect&#8212;for he possessed no personal popularity at all in New-York City, and very little political. But it was evidently tacitly agreed that if the few political supporters of Mr. Lincoln pres<handShift rend="manuscript"/>ent <handShift rend="printed"/>would entirely abstain from any demonstration on their side, the immense majority, who were any thing but supporters, would abstain on their side also. The result was a sulky, unbroken silence, such as certainly never before characterized so great a New-York crowd.</p>
                <p>              <handShift rend="printed"/>      
                    Almost in the same neighborhood I distinctly remembered seeing Lafayette, on his visit to America in 1825. I had also personally seen and heard how Andrew Jackson, Clay, Webster, Hungarian Kossuth, Filibuster Walker, the Prince of Wales on his visit, and other c&#232;l&#233;bres, native and foreign, had been welcomed there, at various times&#8212;all that indescribable human roar and magnetism, unlike any other sound in the universe, the glad exulting thunder-shouts of countless unloosed throats of men! But on this occasion, not a voice&#8212;not a sound.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    From the top of <handShift rend="manuscript"/>an <handShift rend="printed"/>omnibus, (driven up one side, close by, and blocked by the curbstone and the crowds) I had a capital view of it all, and especially of Mr. Lincoln, his look and gait&#8212;his perfect composure and coolness&#8212;his unusual and uncouth height, dress of complete black, stovepipe hat pushed back on the head, dark-brown complexion, seamed and wrinkled yet canny-looking face, black, bushy head of hair, disproportionately long neck, and hands held behind as he stood observing the people. He looked with curiosity upon that immense sea of faces, and the sea of faces returned the look with similar curiosity. In both there was a dash of comedy, almost farce, such as <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> puts in his blackest tragedies. The crowd that hemmed around consisted, I should think, of thirty to forty thousand men, not a single one his personal friend&#8212;while I have no doubt (so frenzied were the ferments of the time) many an assassin's knife and pistol lurked in hip or breast-pocket there, ready, soon as break and riot came.</p>
                <p>          <handShift rend="printed"/>          
                    But no break or riot came. The tall figure gave another relieving stretch or two of arms and legs; then with moderate pace, and accompanied by a few unknown looking persons, ascended the portico steps of the Astor House, disappeared through its broad entrance&#8212;and the dumb-show ended.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="tex.00328.018.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="tex.00328.019.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    I saw Abraham Lincoln often the four years following that date. He changed rapidly and much during his Presidency&#8212;but this scene and him in it, are indelibly stamped upon my recollection. As I sat on the top of my omnibus, and had a good view of him, the thought, dim and inchoate then, has since come out clear enough, that four sorts of genius, four mighty and primal hands, will be needed to the complete <handShift rend="manuscript"/>the <handShift rend="printed"/>limning of this man's future portrait&#8212;the eyes and brains and finger-touch of Plutarch and &#198;schylus and Michel Angelo, assisted by Rabelais.
                </p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>THE WAR&#8212;<handShift rend="manuscript"/>Future literature of it.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    And now (Mr. Lincoln passing on from this scene to Washington, where he was inaugurated, amid armed cavalry, and sharpshooters at every point&#8212;<handShift rend="manuscript"/>(<handShift rend="printed"/>the first instance of the kind in our history, and I hope it will be the last) how the rapid succession of well-known events, <handShift rend="manuscript"/>(<handShift rend="printed"/>too well known&#8212;I believe, these days, we almost hate to hear them mentioned<handShift rend="manuscript"/>)<handShift rend="printed"/>&#8212;the National flag fired on at Sumter, the uprising of the North in paroxysms of astonishment and rage, the chaos of divided councils, the call for troops, the first Bull Run, the stunning cast-down, shock, and dismay of the North: and so in full flood the Secession War. Four years of lurid, bleeding, murky, murderous war. Who paint those years, with all their scenes?&#8212;the hard-fought engagements&#8212;the defeats, plans, failures&#8212;the gloomy hours, days, when our Nationality seemed hung in pail of doubt, perhaps death&#8212;the Mephistophelean sneers of foreign lands and attach&#233;s&#8212;the dreaded Scylla of European interference, and the Charybdis of the tremendously dangerous latent strata of secession sympathizers throughout the Free States (far more numerous than is supposed)&#8212;the long marches in Summer&#8212;the hot sweat, and many a sunstroke, as on the rush to Gettysburg in '63&#8212;the night battles in the woods, as under Hooker at Chancellorsville (a strange episode)&#8212;the camps in Winter&#8212;the military prisons&#8212;the hospitals&#8212;(alas! alas! the hospitals).</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    The Secession War? Nay, let me call it the Union War. Though whatever called it is even yet too near us&#8212;too vast and too closely overshadowing&#8212;its branches unformed yet (but certain), shooting too far into the future&#8212;and the most indicative and mightiest of them yet ungrown.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    A great literature will yet arise out of the era of those four years, those scenes&#8212;era compressing centuries of native passion, first-class pictures, tempests of life and death&#8212;an inexhaustible mine for the histories, drama, romance and even philosophy of peoples to come&#8212;indeed the verteber of poetry and art (of personal character, too,) for all future America&#8212;far more grand, in my opinion, to the hands capable of it, than Homer's siege of Troy, or the French wars to Shakespeare.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>But I must leave these speculations and come to the theme I have assigned and limited myself to.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Real events of the murder</hi></p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    Of the actual murder of President Lincoln, though so much has been written, probably the facts are yet very indefinite in most persons' minds. I read from my memoranda, written at the time, and revised frequently and finally since.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    The day, April 14, 1865, seems to have been a pleasant one throughout the whole land&#8212;the moral atmosphere pleasant too&#8212;the long storm, so dark, so fratricidal, full of blood and doubt and gloom, over and ended at last by the sun-rise of such an absolute National victory, and utter break-down of secessionism&#8212;we almost doubted our own senses! Early herbage, early flowers, were out. (I remember where I was stopping at the time, the season being advanced, there were many lilacs in full bloom. By one of those caprices that enter and give tinge to events without being at all a part of them, I find myself always reminded of the great tragedy of that day by the sight and odor of these blossoms. It never fails.)</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    But I must not dwell on accessories. The deed hastens. The popular afternoon paper of Washington, the little <hi rend="italic">Evening Star</hi>, had spattered all over its third page, divided among the advertisements in a sensational manner, in a hundred different places, "The President and his Lady will be at the Theatre this evening." (Lincoln was fond of the theatre. I have myself seen him there several times. I remember thinking how funny it was that he, in some respects the leading actor in the stormiest drama known to real history's stage through centuries, should sit there and be so completely interested and absorbed in those human jack-straws, moving about with their silly little gestures, foreign spirit, and flatulent text.)</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf010v" facs="tex.00328.020.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="tex.00328.021.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p><handShift rend="manuscript"/>Ringing down the curtain</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    Thus the visible incidents and surroundings of President Lincoln's murder, as they really occurred. Thus ended the attempted secession of these States. Thus the four years' war. But the main things come subtly and invisibly afterward, perhaps long afterward&#8212;neither military, political, nor (great as those are,) historical. I say, certain secondary and indirect results, out of this death, are, in my opinion, greatest. Not the event of the murder itself. Not that Mr. Lincoln strings the principal points and personages of the period, like beads, upon the single string of his career. Not that his idiosyncracy, in its sudden appearance and disappearance, stamps this Republic with a stamp more marked and enduring than any yet given by any one man&#8212;(more even than Washington's). But, joined with these, the immeasurable value and meaning of that whole tragedy lies, to me, in senses finally dearest to a Nation, (and here all our own)&#8212;the imaginative and artistic senses&#8212;the literary and dramatic ones. Not in any common or low meaning of those terms, but a meaning precious to the race, and to every age. A long and varied series of contradictory events arrives at last at its highest poetic, single, central, pictorial denouement. The whole involved, baffling, multiform whirl of the secession period comes to a head, and is gather'd in one brief flash of lightning-illumination&#8212;one simple, fierce deed. Its sharp culmination, and as it were solution, of so many bloody and angry problems, illustrates those climax-moments on the stage of universal Time, where the Historic Muse at one entrance, and the Tragic Muse at the other, suddenly ringing down the curtain, close an immense act in the long drama of creative thought, and give it radiation, tableau, stranger than fiction. Fit radiation&#8212;fit close! How the imagination&#8212;how the student loves these things! America, too, is to have them. For not in all great deaths, nor far or near&#8212;not Caesar in the Roman Senate-house, or Napoleon passing away in the wild night-storm at St. Helena&#8212;not Paleologus, falling, desperately fighting, piled over dozens deep with Grecian corpses&#8212;not calm old Socrates, drinking the hemlock&#8212;outvies that terminus of the Secession War, in one man's life, here in our midst, in our own time&#8212;that seal of the emancipation of three million slaves&#8212;that parturition and delivery of our at last really free Republic, born again, henceforth to commence its career of genuine homogeneous Union, compact, consistent with itself.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="manuscript"/><hi rend="underline">Only Battles and Deaths Condense a Nationality</hi></p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    Nor will ever future American Patriots and Unionists, indifferently over the whole land, or North or South, find a better seal to their lesson. The final use of the greatest men of a nation is, after all, not with reference to their deeds in themselves, or their direct bearing on their times or lands. The final use of a heroic-eminent life&#8212;is its indirect filtering into the nation and the race, and to give, often at many removes, but unerringly, age after age, color and fibre to the personalism of the youth and maturity of that age, and of mankind. Then there is a cement to the whole people, subtler, more underlying, than any thing in written Constitution, or courts or armies&#8212;namely, the cement of a death identified thoroughly with that people, at its head, and for its sake. Strange, (is it not?) that battles, martyrs, agonies, blood, even assassination, should so condense&#8212;perhaps only really, lastingly condense&#8212;a nationality.</p>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    I repeat it&#8212;the grand deaths of the race&#8212;the dramatic deaths of every nationality&#8212;are its most important inheritance-value&#8212;in some respects, beyond its literature and art&#8212;(as the hero is beyond his finest portrait, and the battle itself beyond its choicest song or epic.) Is not here indeed the point underlying all tragedy? the famous pieces of the Grecian Masters&#8212;and all masters? Why, if the old Greeks had had this man, what trilogies of plays&#8212;what epics&#8212;would have been made out of him! How the rhapsodes would have recited him! How quickly that quaint tall form would have entered into the region where men vitalize gods, and gods divinify men!</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf011v" facs="tex.00328.022.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf012r" facs="tex.00328.023.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p><handShift rend="printed"/>
                    When, centuries hence, (as it must, in my opinion, be centuries hence before the life of these States, or of democracy, can be really written and illustrated,) the leading historians and dramatists seek for some personage, some special event, incisive enough to mark with deepest cut, and mnemonize, this turbulent nineteenth century of ours, (not only these States, but all over the political and social world)&#8212;something, perhaps, to close that gorgeous procession of European feudalism, with all its pomp and caste-prejudices, (of whose long train we in America are yet so inextricably the heirs)&#8212;something to identify with terrible identification, by far the greatest revolutionary step in the history of the United States, (perhaps the greatest of the world, our century)&#8212;the absolute extirpation and erasure of slavery from the States&#8212;those historians will seek in vain for any point to serve more thoroughly their purpose, than Abraham Lincoln's death.
                    
                    Dear to the Muse&#8212;thrice dear to Nationality&#8212;to the whole human race&#8212;precious to this Union&#8212;precious to Democracy&#8212;unspeakably and forever precious&#8212;their first great Martyr Chief.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf012v" facs="tex.00328.024.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf013r" facs="tex.00328.025.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf013v" facs="tex.00328.026.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>       
