<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uva.00430">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Walt Whitman to William Sloane Kennedy, 11 April
                    1887</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="rf">Ryan Furlong</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="if">Ian faith</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ss">Stefan Schöberlein</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>National Historical Publications and Records Commission</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                        Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>uva.00430</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Walt Whitman to William Sloane Kennedy, 11 April 1887</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1887-04-11" xml:id="dat1">April 11, 1887</date>
                    <idno type="callno">Box-folder: 4:3</idno>
                    <orgName xml:id="uva">Papers of Walt Whitman (MSS 3829), Clifton Waller Barrett
                        Library of American Literature, Albert H. Small Special Collections Library,
                        University of Virginia</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="text" xml:id="rel01" target="uva.00489"/>
                    <relatedItem type="document" target="wwa.00597"/>
                    <note type="project" target="#rel01">
                        Whitman wrote this letter on the verso of the first page of a letter he had received on March 29, 1887 from Ernest Rhys.
                        He included the full letter from Rhys as an enclosure for Kennedy. 
                    </note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Kennedy, William Sloane" ref="n3039"/>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-12-03" who="#smb">final check, corrected, added notes and multigenre encoding</change>
            <change when="2016-05-27" who="#ss">checked and corrected</change>
            <change when="2016-05-24" who="#if">edited</change>
            <change when="2016-04-21" who="#rf">encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader> 
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="uva_ej.00134_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <opener>
                <dateline> 
                    <name type="place" rend="right">Camden</name>
                    <date when="1887-04-11">April 11, '87—noon</date>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I send you Rhys's<ptr target="loc.03310_n1"/> letter to me rec'd yesterday—Tho
                I suppose the disagreeable item in it, relating to the pub'n of y'r book, has been
                already written to you ab't by R—My <hi rend="underline">under the weather
                    spell</hi> still continues, but with a slight let up.—I expect to go on
                to New York to speak my "Death of Lincoln" piece,<ptr target="yal.00238_n3"/>
                Thursday afternoon next—Probably the shake up will do me good—I drove
                over last evening to spend a couple of hours with my friends Mr &amp; Mrs. Talcott
                    Williams,<ptr target="loc.05142_n5"/> Phila: &amp; take dinner
                there—Enjoyed all— —I receive the <hi rend="underline">Transcripts</hi> &amp; look them over—then send them to O'Connor<ptr target="n2002"/>— I don't make much reckoning of the NY
                performance—the best is to be borne in mind,(&amp; warmly borne in mind) by a
                few dear NY friends—Sunny &amp; summery weather here &amp; my canary is
                singing like a house a fire—</p>
            <closer>
                <signed>Walt Whitman</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="uva_ej.00133_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="uva_ej.00131_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="uva_ej.00132_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="uva_ej.00131_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">59 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea,</name>
                        <name type="place">London, S.W. England</name>
                        <date when="1887-03-29">29th March 1887.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Walt Whitman</salute>
                </opener> 
                <p>Your letter of the 15th with the 'Additional Note' was not long in following the
                    other,<ptr target="uva.00489_n2"/> &amp; with it the 'Specimen Days' vol. is now
                    splendidly complete.<ptr target="uva.00489_n3"/> As the book stands now, there is a native unity about it, more
                    I think than when it was given together with the 'Democratic Vistas.' These later
                    parts of the original 'S. Days &amp; Collect' will follow naturally as the more
                    theoretic exposition of your life &amp; thought, prepared for effectively &amp; made
                    so of greater effect, it seems to me. With the D. Vistas completed<ptr target="uva.00489_n1"/> in turn, my cup
                    will be overflowing indeed. It is something I think of enthusiastically that soon
                    they will both be in the hands of the gay fellows everywhere, whose energies will
                    presently be master of the spirit of the time. And what you have added to the book
                    is so exactly what was wanted to give it direct appeal to us here, &amp; bring it into touch.
                    Personally I cannot say how grateful I feel for these gifts you have made me the
                    almoner of. As for the 'Democratic Vistas,' I hope you will be able to let us have
                    some of the essays &amp; papers that have appeared in the Critic &amp; other
                    publications, to add to it. As you know, the copy we have now by us is hardly enough
                    to make a full volume. You shall be duly apprised of the publishing details, of both
                    vols. as time goes on. We propose an interval of four <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="uva_ej.00132_large.jpg" type="verso"/> to six or eight months between the
                    2 vols. so that there is plenty of time to settle about the 2nd. Already the news that
                    you have published additional matter to the 'Specimen Days in America' has excited
                    great interest among those who know you here.</p>
                <p>I told you I was going to see Mrs. Costelloe<ptr target="loc.02189_n1"/> the other
                    evening. Count Stenbock<ptr target="n3135"/> arrived here in a fast hansom in his
                    usual erratic way, &amp; whirled me off there about nine o'clock, &amp; we had 'a
                    good time' then till midnight, including the brewing of a wassail bowl 
                    (non-alcoholic) with comic result by Steinbock &amp; an American girl who was there.
                    Mrs. Costelloe impressed me most delightfully. She is one of the five or six noblest
                    women I have come across; I say this quite deliberately. I would give a great deal
                    to be able to meet &amp; talk with such an one often, &amp; I am sorry that the C's
                    are going away to the country for Easter for my own sake; though on the other hand it
                    is a sin that such a superb creature should be cooped up in a place like London,
                    under society restrictions at all, &amp; as she is nearing the time of motherhood,
                    one ought only to be glad at her escape to the fields &amp; flowers &amp; free air.
                    Costelloe<ptr target="n6114"/> himself is of too <hi rend="underline">hard</hi>
                    an intellectuality I am afraid, to give us much in common, but I get on with almost
                    everybody, &amp; I can see that he is at any rate a very genuine &amp; capable
                    fellow in his way.—By the by Mrs. C. shewed me two portraits of you which I
                    had not seen before, &amp; she told me to ask you for a copy of one, called by her
                    the <hi rend="underline">King Lear</hi> one. She said <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="uva_ej.00133_large.jpg" type="recto"/> she would tell you about it in her
                    next letter. Before we came away, she read out your preface to the assembled little
                    company of guests—mainly Americans, &amp; it was received with enthusiasm, for
                    besides its own natural effect she read it very impressively. Curiously enough Roden
                    Noel<ptr target="n0815"/> had been there the same afternoon. I go down to dine
                    with him occasionally at his place near the Crystal Palace. He is very sympathetic
                    with L. of G. Costelloe was rather making fun of him from Mrs. C's description,
                    because he accepted Hegel &amp; spiritualism &amp; sundry other paradoxical
                    positions on thought. There is a fine fund of manhood in Noel though. He is better
                    on the sea-shore than in his study, where indeed he is rather apt to grow
                    unprofitably vague over questions of poetry &amp; philosophy, which is to say Roden
                    Noel &amp; Hegel chiefly.</p> 
                <p>I had a piece of rather awkward news about W.S. Kennedy's<ptr target="n3039"/> book<ptr target="duk.00813_n1"/>
                    this morning. After writing many times in vain to Wilson,<ptr target="loc.03316_n2"/> I had a note from his
                    brother to say that he is ill again, &amp; cannot arrange about the book at present,
                    returning it to me accordingly. It is very unfortunate indeed, for it is very
                    difficult to get a book of unconventional character afloat in the cockney world of
                    publishers. There is some chance of Wilson's being able
                    to take the book in the autumn, but that is such a long time to wait.<ptr target="uva.00489_n4"/></p>
                <p>Spring has fairly set in here at last. I hope it is the same with you. I have many a
                    good ramble far &amp; wide here, &amp; there is much to see on the riverside always.
                    They are building a new bridge (Battersea Bge) close by, &amp; I often go &amp;
                    watch them at their pile-driving &amp; so on. The thump of the monkey on the piles
                    goes on night &amp; day; after dark they have an electric light which sends a fine
                    gleam across here. But it's <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#smb" cert="low">short</unclear>-time, &amp; 
                    I must stop for to-day. Goodbye!</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>Ernest Rhys</signed>  
                </closer>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="uva_ej.00134_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>