<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="yal.00297">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">William Sloane Kennedy to Walt Whitman, 27 February 1889</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author>William Sloane Kennedy</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kw">Kara Wentworth</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="blh">Breanna Himschoot</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="aa">Alex Ashland</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor> Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of
                    Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder> National Historical Publications and Records Commission </funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588–4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p> Copyright © 2020 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only. </p>
                </availability>
            <idno>yal.00297</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>William Sloane Kennedy</author>
                    <title>William Sloane Kennedy to Walt Whitman, 27 February 1889</title>
                    <date cert="high" when="1889-02-27" xml:id="dat1">February 27, 1889</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="yal">Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare
                        Book and Manuscript Library</orgName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="sender">
                    <persName key="Kennedy, William Sloane" ref="n3039">William Sloane Kennedy</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="recipient">
                    <persName key="Whitman, Walt">Walt Whitman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-01-27" who="#smb">updated corrections</change>
            <change when="2019-10-01" who="#smb">final check, corrected</change>
            <change when="2019-05-22" who="#aa">second check</change>
            <change when="2019-04-29" who="#blh">first check</change>
            <change when="2017-01-24" who="#kw">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc> 
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="yal.00297.001_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place"> Belmont<ptr target="yal.00297_n1"/></name>
                        <date when="1889-02-27">Feb 27. '89</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear W.W:—</salute> 
                </opener> 
                <p>The German Grashalme<ptr target="nyp.00628_n3"/> rec'd.! How honors thicken
                    &amp; cluster. This book is a remarkable step forward. Do you know it gave me a
                    curious (perhaps to you not altogether intelligible) feeling as I read yr
                    familiar poems in the foreign tongue I have so long been reading. I seemed to
                    see to feel <hi rend="underline">you</hi> doubled, foreignized, <hi rend="underline">speaking</hi> over there the same message to a new nation;
                    &amp; I also imagined this as but the beginning of a long pilgrimage you are to
                    make around the world, uttering yr gospel in the thousand tongues of men. It was
                    a very <unclear reason="illegible" resp="#blh" cert="medium">peculiar</unclear>
                    feeling &amp; something grand &amp; thrilling in its forecast, or prophecy-tinge.</p>
                <p>I give you here an accurate line for line translation of all of Knortz's<ptr target="uva.00476_n1"/> and Rolleston's<ptr target="n1027"/> prefaces
                    although I don't deem them worth much (for novelty), except the inevitable
                    biographical summary of Rolleston. The translations are <hi rend="underline">very well</hi> done. The German tongue (flexible, many-inflected, wide
                    ranging language) lends itself admirably to yr your! long sentences. They have
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="yal.00297.002_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="yal.00297.003_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    translated the very best of the poems for foreign presentation, I think.</p>
                <p>Do you know anything abt how Rolleston came to be so good a German scholar?
                    Studied in Germany when a boy doubtless? Do you know whether he or Knortz is
                    married?</p>   
                <p>Give my love to Dr. B.<ptr target="n0119"/></p>
                <p>You can make any use you want to of the transl. tho' I merely made it for you.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed rend="right">WS Kennedy.</signed> 
                </closer>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="yal.00297.004_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="enclosure">
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="yal.00297.005_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
           <opener> 
              <salute>My Dear W Whitman,<ptr target="yal.00297_n5"/></salute>
           </opener>
                <p>Yr letter<ptr target="yal.00297_n2"/> &amp; papers both rec'd with thanks. I
                    have written lately one of the most elaborate things I ever did—on the
                    nature of Poetry—going deep down, canvassing all nature for analogies
                    (Ruskin's five vols of Mod Painters helping me much)<ptr target="yal.00297_n3"/>
                    going over all the poets, &amp; taking yr Burial Hymn of Lincoln as the model of
                    the poetical style of the future.<ptr target="yal.00297_n4"/> My article is <hi rend="underline">scientific</hi>, I even reverently analyze Shakespeare's
                    technique &amp; <hi rend="underline">prove</hi> that he inclined more &amp; more
                    to prose, abandoning rhyme. I show that yr your! long twenty syllable, &amp; twenty-five
                    syllable lines are the first true heroics ever written
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="yal.00297.006_large.jpg" type="verso"/>in a Germanic tongue, and that
                    while rhymes &amp; the clang-tints of verse will continue, you have revolutionized the
                    technique of the drama &amp; the epic.</p>
                <p>I am cunning on
                    acct of our enemies, &amp; only introduce my great
                    friend—yourself—at the close, when I have cut the other poets to
                    pieces &amp; have interrogated Nature &amp; compared the two—herself &amp;
                    the poets.</p>   
                <p>I had been reserving this piece of work until I moved into my new house. I
                    married a darling little wife six months ago, &amp; she &amp; I have built a
                    pretty cottage in Belmont—on the hill—magnificent view, at night the
                    illuminated world of Boston twinkling below us—the revolving "Boston
                    Light" out—flashing away in the harbor, lime-lights bright &amp; numerous.
                    By day birds &amp; squirrels in the numerous cedars at our door—a perfect
                    forest of Virginia cedars. We have half an acre with trees (wild) &amp; are in
                        <hi rend="underline">complete solitude</hi> in our eyrie,–no
                    neighbors within sight, except through the trees. Is not this tempting?
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="yal.00297.007_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                And now does it not tempt you to come &amp; see me? Let me <hi rend="underline">beg of you</hi> if you come to Boston, to let me know at once, &amp; I will
                    escort you out, &amp; <choice>
                        <orig>instal</orig>
                        <reg>install</reg>
                    </choice> you in our prophet's chamber, where there is a fireplace, &amp; a
                    great prospect, with deserted woodland walks <hi rend="underline">right at
                        hand</hi>. Will you promise? Write &amp; tell me. Mrs K.<ptr target="loc.02897_n3"/> goes in to the city every day, so we shd have the
                    day to ourselves, I also go in nearly every day, &amp; you cd have the house to
                    yourself much of the time. Do come &amp; stay two weeks if you can. We have no
                    girl (servant) to bore us. I am a little nobody, but I reverence you, &amp; that
                    sheds a little borrowed greatness on me.</p>
                <p>I sent my article on poetry to the Century. They ordered an article on E.E.
                        Hale,<ptr target="n1514"/> wh. I have sent also. I have a splendid plum for you in that.
                    Hale wrote an appreciative review of yr first book in '56 or '60, also in the North
                    American, &amp; he told me that he thought he shd stand by every word of it
                    to-day, But that's nothing, after all.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>aff.</salute> 
                    <signed rend="right">W.S. Kennedy.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="yal.00297.008_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="yal.00297.009_large.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="yal.00297.010_large.jpg" type="verso"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>